so I was trying to figure out how to do
photo realistic AI photos and it was
stabil diffusion by itself is not doing
that well like the faces look all
mangled y um and it doesn't have enough
resolution or something to to do that
well so but I started seeing these these
um base models These Fine tun models and
people were training on porn and I would
try them and they would be very
photorealistic they would have bodies
that actually made sense like body uh
Anatomy um but if you look at the
photorealistic models that people use
now still there's still core porn there
like of naked people so I need to prompt
out the nak and everybody needs to do
this with AI startups with imaging you
need to prompt out the naked stuff you
have to keep reminding the model you
need to put clothes on yeah don't put
naked because it's very risky I have
Google Vision that checks every photo
before it's shown to the user to like
check detor oh nfw detector because you
get the journalists get very
angry the following is a conversation
with Peter levels also known on X as
levels IO he is a self-taught developer
and entrepreneur who designed programmed
shipped and ran over 40 startups many of
which are hugely successful in most
cases he did it all by himself while
living the digital Nomad life in over 40
countries and over 150 cities
programming on a laptop while chilling
on a couch using vanilla HTML jQuery PHP
and SQL light he builds and ships
quickly and improves on the fly all in
the open documenting his work both his
successes and failures with a raw
honesty of a true Indie hacker Peter is
an inspiration to a huge number of
developers and entrepreneurs who love
creating cool things in the world that
are hopefully useful for people this was
an honor and a pleasure for me this is
Alex Freedman podcast to support it
please check out our sponsors in the
description and now dear friends here's
Peter
levels you've launched a lot of
companies and built a lot of products as
you say most failed but some succeeded
what's your philosophy behind building
the startups that you did I think my
philosophy is very different than most
people in startups because most people
in startups they they build a company
and they raise money right and they hire
people and then they build a product and
they find something that makes money and
I don't really raise money I don't use
VC funding I do everything myself I'm
designer I'm the developer I make
everything I make the logo so for me I'm
much more Scrappy and and because I
don't have funding like I need to I need
to go fast I need to make things fast uh
to see if an ID works right I have an
IDE in my mind and I build it build it
like a mro mini startup um and I launch
it very quickly like within you know two
weeks or something of building it and I
check if there's demand if people
actually sign up and not just sign up
but if people actually pay money right
like they need to take out their credit
cards pay me money and then I can can
see if the idea is validated and most
ideas don't work like as you say most
feel so there's this rapid iterative
phase where you just build a prototype
that works launch it yeah see if people
like it improving it really really
quickly to see if people like it a
little bit more enough to pay and all
that that that whole rapid process is
how you think of I think it's it's like
it's very rapid and it's like um if I
compare to for example Google you know
like our big tech companies especially
Google right now is kind of struggling
like they made like Transformers they
made all they invented all the AI stuff
years ago and they never really shipped
like they could have shipped jet gbt for
example I think I heard in 2019 and they
never shipped it because they were so
stuck in bureaucracy but they had
everything they had the data they had
the tech they had the engineers and they
could Didn't Do It um and it's because
these big organizations it's it it can
make you very slow so being alone by
myself on my laptop like you know in my
underwear in a hotel room or something I
can ship very fast and I don't need to
like I don't need to ask like legal for
like oh can you vouch for this you know
I can just go and ship you always code
in your underwear the your profile
picture you're like slouching a couch
and your underwear chilling a laptop no
no but it's I do wear like shorts a lot
and I I usually just wear shorts and no
T-shirt cuz I'm always too hot like I'm
always overheating thank you for showing
up not just in your underwear but
wearing shorts I know you know I still
wearing this for you but thank you um
thank you for dressing up I think it's
cuz I since I go to the gym I'm always
too hot what's your favorite EX in the
gym man over press over press like like
shoulder press yeah okay but it feels
good cuz you're doing like you do you
win cuz when you what is it I do 60
kilos so it's like 120 lbs or something
like it's it's it's my only thing I can
do well you know in the gym and you
stand like this and you're like I did it
you know like a winner pose yeah Victory
pose uh I do bench press squads
deadlift hence the uh the mug yeah
talking to my therapist it's a deadlift
yeah because it acts like therapy for me
you know yeah yeah it is which is
controversial to say like if I say this
on Twitter people get angry physical
hardship is a kind of therapy yeah I
just rewatched uh Happy People year in
the tiger that Warner Herzog film where
they
document people that are doing trapping
they're essentially just working for
survival in the wilderness year round
yeah and there's a deep happiness to
their way of life because they're so
busy in it in nature yeah 100% like
there's something about that physical
physical yeah toil yeah my dad taught me
that my dad always do does like
Construction in the house like he's
always re renovating the house he breaks
through one room and then he goes to the
next room and he's just going in a
circle around the house for like the
last 40 years so but so he's always
doing construction the house and it's
his Hobby and he like he taught me when
when I'm depressed or something um he
says like get a big like what do you
call like a big uh mountain of sand or
something from construction just get a
shovel and uh bring it to the other side
and just you know do like physical labor
do like hard work and do something like
get set a goal do something and I I kind
of did that with startups too yeah
construction is not about the
destination man it's about the journey
yeah yeah sometimes I wonder people who
are always remodeling their house is it
really about the remodeling or is it's
not is it about the project Journey the
puzzle of it no he doesn't care about
the results well he shows me he's like
it's amazing I'm like yeah it's amazing
but um then he wants to go to the next
room you know but I think it's very
metaphorical for work cuz I also I never
stop work I go to the next website or I
make a new one right or I make a new
startup so I'm always like like give you
something to wake up in the morning and
like you know have coffee and then uh
kiss your girlfriend and then you have
like a goal not today I'm going to fix
this feature or today I'm going to fix
this bog or something I'm going to do
something you have something to wake up
to you know and I think um maybe
especially as a man also women but you
need you need a hard work you know you
need like an Endeavor I think how much
of the building that you do is about
money how much is it about just a deep
internal happiness it's about fun cuz I
was cuz I was doing it when I didn't
make money right that's the point so I
was always coding I was always I was
making music I made electronic music
drama based music like 20 years ago and
I was always making stuff so I think a
creative expression is like a meaningful
work that's so important it's so fun
it's so fun to have like a daily
challenge where you try figure stuff out
but but the interesting thing is you
built a lot of successful products and
you never really wanted to take it to
that level where you scale real big
andell it to aan something like this
yeah the problem is I don't dictate that
right like if more people start using IF
Millions people s start using it and it
becomes big um I'm not going to say oh
stop signing up to my website and pay me
money but I never raised funding for it
and I think because I don't like this
the stressful life that comes with it
like I have a lot of um founder friends
and they tell me secretly like with
hundreds of millions of dollars in
funding and stuff and they they tell me
like next time if I'm going to do it I'm
going to do it like you
because it's more it's more fun it's
more Indie it's more chill it's more
creative they don't like this they don't
like to be manager right you become like
a CEO you become a manager and um I
think a lot of people that start
startups when they become a CEO they
don't like that job actually but they
can't really exit it you know but they
like to do the ground work the coding so
I think that keeps you happy like doing
something creative yeah it's interesting
how people are pulled towards that to
scale to go really big and you don't
have that honest reflection with
yourself like what actually makes you
happy because for a lot of great
Engineers what makes them happy is the
building the the quote unquote
individual contributor like where you're
actually still coding or you're actually
still building and they let go of that
and then they become unhappy um but some
of that is the sacrifice needed to have
a impact of scale if you truly believe
in a thing you're doing but like look at
Elon he's doing things million times
bigger than me right and
um would I want to do that I don't know
you can really choose these things right
but I really respect that I think elon's
very different from VC Founders right VC
start it's like software there's a lot
of bullshit in this world I think
there's a lot of like dodgy Finance
stuff happening there I think um and I
never have like concrete evidence about
it but your gut tells you something's
going on with like companies getting
sold to friends and VCS and then they do
reciprocity and this Shady Financial
dealings with Elon does not he's just
raising money from investors and he's
actually building stuff with he needs
the money to build stuff you know hard
Hardware stuff um and that I really
respect you said that there's been a few
low points in your life you've been
depressed and the building is one of the
ways you you get out of that but can you
talk to that can you take me to that
place to that time when you were in at a
low point so I was in Holland and I
graduated University and I didn't want
to like get a normal job and I was
making some money with YouTube because I
had this music career and I uploaded my
music to YouTube and YouTube started
paying me like uh with AdSense like
$22,000 a month $2,000 up and all my
friends got like normal jobs and we
stopped hanging out cuz people would
like in University hang out you know you
chill each other's houses uh you go
party but when people get jobs they only
party like in the weekend and they don't
hang anymore in the week because you
need to be at the office and I was like
this is not for me I want to do
something else and I was starting
getting this like I think it's like
Saturn return this you know when you're
turn 27 it's like some concept where
Saturn returns to the same place in the
orbit that it was when you're born I'm
learning some it's some astrology thing
you know so many truly special artists
died when they were 27 exactly sum of 27
man and it was for me like I started
going crazy because I didn't really see
like my future in Holland buying a house
going living in the suburbs and stuff so
it flew out I went to Asia started
digital nomading and did that for a year
and then that made me feel even worse
you know CU I was like Alone um in hotel
rooms like looking at the ceiling like
what am I doing with my life like this
is uh like I was working on startups and
stuff and YouTube but it's like what is
the future here you know like uh is this
is this something while my friends in
Holland were doing really well and with
a normal life you know um so it was
getting very depressed and like I'm like
an outcast you know and my money was was
shrinking I wasn't making money anymore
lot making $500 a month or something and
I was you know looking at the ceiling
thinking like now I'm like 27 I'm a
loser and that's the moment when I
started building like startups and it
was because my dad said like if you're
depressed you need to you know get sand
get a shovel start shoveling doing
something you can't just sit still which
is kind of like a interesting way to
deal with depression you know like it's
not like oh let's talk about it it's
more like let's go do something and um
and I started doing a project called 12
startups in 12 months where every month
I would make something like a project
and I would launch it with stripe so
people could pay for it so the basic
format is try to build a thing put it
online and put stripe to where you can
pay money for it yeah add a stripe check
I'm not sponsored by stripe but add a
stripe checkout button is that still
like the the easiest way to just like
pay for stuff stripe 100% like I think
so yeah it's a cool company they just
made it so easy you can just click and
yeah and they're really nice like the
CEO Patrick is really nice behind the
scenes it must be difficult to like
actually make that happen cuz that used
to be a huge problem like just Merchant
just just adding a thing a button where
you can like pay for a thing dude it's
dude I know this because when I was when
I 9 years old I was making websites also
and I tried to open a merchant account
there was like before tribe you would
have like um I think it was called World
pay so I had to like fill out all these
forms and then I had to F them to
America from Holland with my dad's facts
um and my dad had to it wasn't my dad's
name and he to sign for this and he
started reading these terms and
conditions which was like he's liable
for like 100 million in Damages and he's
like I don't want to sign this I'm like
Dad come on I need a merchant account I
need to make money on the internet you
know and he signed it and we sent we fax
it to America and I had a merchant
account but then never nobody paid for
anything so that was the problem you
know yeah but it's much easier now you
can sign up you add some codes and um
yeah so 12 startups in 12 months yeah so
what how do you what startup number one
what what was that what like what what
were you feeling what were you sitting
behind the computer like how much do you
actually know about building stuff at
that point I could I could code a little
bit because I did the YouTube channel
and I made a website for I would make
websit for like the YouTube channel it
was called panda mix show and it was
like these electronic music mixes like
dubstep or dral base or Tech in our
house I saw one of them had like flash
were you using flash yeah my album my CD
album was using flash yeah yeah I sold
my CD yeah kids flash was Flash was
software this is like the the break like
Grandpa you know but flash was cool yeah
and there was what's it called boy I
should remember this action script
there's some kind of programming
language scpt yeah yeah script in flash
back then that was the JavaScript you
know the JavaScript yeah and I I thought
that's going to that's supposed to be
the dynamic thing that takes over the
internet I invested so many hours in
learning Steve Jobs killer Steve Job
said flesh sucks stop using it every was
like okay that guy was right though
right yeah I I don't know yeah well it
was it was a closed platform I think and
Clos but it's ironic cuz Apple you know
they're not very open right but back
then Steve was like this is closed we
should not use it and it's as security
problems I think which sounded like a
copout like I just wanted to say that to
make it look kind of bad um but flash
was cool yeah yeah it was cool for a
time yeah H listen animated gifts were
cool for a time too yeah they came back
in a different way yeah as a meme though
I mean like I I remember when gifts were
actually cool not ironically cool like
there's like on the internet you would
have like a Dancing Rabbit or something
like this and that was really exciting
no you had like the you know Lex
homepage you Le everything was centered
yeah and you had like Peter's homepage
and then the on construction yeah GIF
which was like a guy like with a helmet
and the lights banners uh yeah that's
how before like Google AdSense you would
have like banners for advertising it was
amazing yeah and and a lot of links to
porn I think yeah where the Merion
accounts people would use for people
would make money a lot only money made
on internet was like porn or a lot of it
yeah it was it was a dark place it's
still a dark place yeah and but there's
Beauty in the darkness anyway so you
were uh you did some basic HTML yeah
yeah but I had to learn the actual like
coding so I uh this was good it was a
good good idea to like every monom lunch
a startup so I could uh learn to code
learn basic stuff and but it was still
very Scrappy because I didn't have time
to which was on purpose like didn't have
time to spend a lot of um I had a month
to do something so I couldn't spend more
than a month and I was pretty strict
about that um and I published it as a
blog post so people I think I put it on
Hacker News and people would check like
kind of like oh did you actually you
know I felt like accountability because
I put it public that I actually had to
do it do you remember the first one you
did I think it was playing my inbox cuz
back then my friends we would send we
would send like cool was before Spotify
we would send like uh 2014 we would send
music to each other like YouTube links
uh like this is a cool song this is a
cool song and it was the these giant
email trads on Gmail and they were like
unnavigable so I made an app that would
log into your Gmail get them emails and
find ons of YouTube links and then make
like kind like a gallery of your your
songs like essentially Spotify and my
friends loved it was it scraping it like
what was no it uses like poop like pop
or IMAP you know it would actually check
your email so that like privacy concerns
because it would get all your emails to
find YouTube links but then I would I
wouldn't save anything um but that was
fun it was like and that that first
project already would get like pressed
like it went on think like um some tech
media and stuff and I was like that's
cool like it didn't make money there was
no payment button but it was uh it was
actually people using it I think tens of
thousands of people used it that's a
great idea I wonder why like why why
don't we have that why don't we have
things that access Gmail and extract
some useful aggregate information yeah
you could tell GMA like don't give me
all emails just give me the ones with
YouTube links you know or something like
that yeah I mean there is a whole
ecosystem of like apps you can build on
top of the Google but people don't never
do this I've seen a few like Boomerang
there's a few apps that are like good
but just I wonder what maybe it's not
easy to make money I think it's hard to
get people to pay for these like
extensions and plugins you know cuz it's
not like a real app so it's not like
people don't value it people value oh
this a plugin should be free you know
when I want to use a plugin in Google
Sheets or something I'm not going to pay
for it like it should be free which is
but if you go to a website and you
actually okay I need this product I'm G
to pay for this because it's a real
product so even though it's the same
code in the back it's a plugin you know
yeah I mean you can do it through like
extensions like Chrome extensions
through from the browser side yeah but
who pays for Chrome extensions right
like barely anybody so nobody uh that's
not a good place to make money probably
yeah that sucks like chromic extension
should be a extension for your startup
you know you have a product yeah oh we
also have a Chrome extension you know I
wish the Chrome extension would be the
product I wish Chrome would support that
like where you could pay for it easily
cuz like imagine I can imagine a lot of
products that would just live as
extensions like improvements for social
media like it's like gpts you know gpts
yeah like these CH gpts they they going
to charge money for it now and you get a
ref ref share I think from an open AI I
made a lot of them also why we'll we'll
talk about it so let's rewind back it's
a pretty cool idea to do 12 startup in
12 months what what's it take to build a
thing in in in 30 days like at that time
how hard was
that I think the hard part is like
figuring out what you shouldn't add
right what you shouldn't build because
you don't have time so you need to build
a landing page well you need to make the
you know you need to build the product
actually because it need to be something
they pay for um do you need to build a
login system like maybe no you know like
maybe you can build some Scrappy login
system like for fot you sign up you pay
strap checkout and you get a login link
and when I started it was only a login
link with a hash and that's just a
static link so it's very easy to log in
yeah it's not so safe you know what if
you leak the link and now I have real
Google login but that took like a year
so keeping it very Scrappy is very
important to because you don't have time
you know you need to focus on um what
you can build fast uh so money stripe uh
build a product build a landing page um
you need to think about how are people
going to find this so are you going to
put it on Reddit or something how are
you going to put it on Reddit without
being looked at as a spammer right like
um if you say hey this is my new startup
you should use it no nobody's it gets
deleted you know M um maybe if you find
a problem that a lot of people on Reddit
already have on subreddit you know like
and you solve that problem say sub
people I made this thing that might
solve your problem and maybe it's free
for now you know like uh that could work
you know but you need to be very you
know um narrow it down what you're
building time is limited yeah actually
can we go back to the you laying in a
room feeling like a loser yeah I still
feel like a loser sometimes what's what
can you can you speak to that feeling to
that place of just like feeling like a
loser and cuz I think a lot of people in
this world are laying in a room right
now listening to this and feeling like a
loser okay so I think it's normal if
you're young that you feel like a loser
first of all especially when you're 27
yes yeah especially there's like a peak
yeah yeah think a peak and so I would
not kill yourself it's very important
just get through it you know but uh
because you have nothing you have
probably no money you have no business
you have no job you have you like Jeremy
Peterson said this I saw it somewhere
like the reason people are depressed
because they have nothing they don't
have a girlfriend they don't have a or
boyfriend they don't have a you need
stuff you need like or a family you need
things around you you need to build a
life for yourself if you don't build a
life for yourself you'll be depressed so
if you're alone in Asia in a hostel
looking at the ceiling and you don't
have any money coming in you don't have
a girlfriend you don't of course you're
depressed press is logic but back then
if you're in a moment you think this is
not logic there's something wrong with
me you know yeah um and and also I think
I started going I started getting like
anxiety and I think I started going a
little bit crazy where I think travel
can make you insane and I know this
because I know that there's like digital
Nomad that they kill themselves and I
don't I haven't checked like this the
comparison with like Baseline people
like suicide rate but I have a hunch um
especially in the beginning when it was
a very new thing like 10 years ago that
it can be very ecologically taxing and
you're alone a lot back then when you
travel alone there was no other digital
Nance back then a lot so you're in a
strange culture you look different than
everybody like you're in I was in Asia
like you everybody's really nice in
Thailand but you're not part of the
culture you're traveling around you're
hopping from City to City you don't have
a home anymore MH you feel this rooted
and you're constantly in the outcast in
in that you're different from everybody
else yes exactly but people treat like
Thailand people are so nice but you
still feel like Outcast and and then I
think the the digital n i met then were
all kind of like it was like shady
business you know but they were like
Vigilantes cuz it was a new thing and
like one guy was selling illegal drugs
was American guy was selling illegal
drugs via UPS to Americans you know on
this website they were like a lot of
drop shippers doing Shady stuff um
there's a lot of shady things going on
there and they were they didn't look
like very balanced people they didn't
look like people I wanted to hang with
you know so I also felt Outcast from
other foreigners in Thailand other
digital Nomads and I was like man I made
a big mistake and then I went back to
Holland and then I got even more
depressed you said digital Nomad what is
digital Nomad what is that way of life
what is the philosophy there and the
history of the movement I I struck upon
it on accident because I I was like I'm
going to graduate University and then
I'm going to I need to get out of here
I'll fly to Asia because I've been
before in Asia I studied in Korea in
2009 like study exchange I was like Asia
is easy Thailand's easy I'll just go
there figure things out and it's cheap
it's very cheap changai I would live
like for $150 per month rent for like a
private room pretty good so I struck on
this on next I was like okay there's
other people on laptops working on their
startup or working remotely back then
nobody worked remotely but they worked
on their their businesses right um and
they would you know live in like
Colombia or uh Thailand or Vietnam or
Bali they would live kind of like a more
cheap places and it looked like a very
adventurous life like you travel around
you build your business there's no
pressure from like your Home Society
right like you're American so you're you
get pressure from American soci telling
you kind of what to do like you need to
buy a house or you need to this stuff I
had this in Holland too and you can get
away from this pressure you can find
kind of feel like you're free you're
kind of there's nobody telling you what
to do but that's also why you start
feeling like you go crazy because you
are you are free you're dis attached
from anything and anybody um you're
disattached from your culture you're
disattached from the culture you're
probably in because you're staying very
short I think France kofka said I'm free
therefore for I'm lost man that's so
true yeah that's exactly the point and
yeah freedom is like it's the definition
of no constraints right like anything is
possible you can go anywhere and
everybody's like oh that must be super
nice you know like Freedom you must be
very happy and it's the opposite like I
don't think that makes you happy I think
constraints probably make you happy and
that's a big lesson I learned
then but what what were they making for
money what what so you're saying they
were doing Shady stuff at that time for
me you know because I was more like a
developer I wanted to make startups kind
of and and it was like um it was like
drugs being shipped to America like diet
pills and stuff like non FDA proofed
stuff you know and they would like there
was no like e they were like they would
would save beers they would laugh about
like all the dodgy shit kind of they're
doing you know ah that part of okay kind
of vibe you know like kind of sleazy
Ecom Vibe I'm not saying all Ecom is SLE
you know but right but you know this
Vibe it could be a Vibe and your your
Vibe was more buol shit that's ethical
you know the guys with sports cars in
Dubai these people you know yes Ecom
like oh bro you got a drop ship and
you'll make 100 million a month like
those people was this shit and I I was
like this is not my people yeah I don't
I mean there's nothing wrong with any of
those individual components judg but but
there's a
foundation that's not quite ethical I
what is that I don't know what that is
but yeah I get you no I like I don't
want to judge it was more I know that
for me it wasn't my world it wasn't my
subculture I want to make cool shit you
know but they also think their cool shit
is cool so you know uh but I wanted to
make like real like startups and that
was my thing I would read Hacker News
you know like why combinator and they
were making cool stuff so I wanted to
make cool stuff I mean that's a pretty
cool way of life just if you romanticize
it for a moment it's very romantic man
it's very it's colorful you know like if
I think about the memories I mean what
are some happy memories just like
working working cafes or working
in just the
freedom that that uh envelops you from
with that that way of life cuz anything
is possible you can just get up was
amazing like we would work like you
would I would make friends and we would
work until you know 6:00 a.m. in Bali
for example with like um with Andre my
best friend who who still my best friend
and we and other friends and we would
work until like the morning when the sun
came up because at night the co-working
space was silent you know there was
nobody else and I would wake up like 6
p.m. or 5:00 p.m. I would drive to the
cing space on a motorbike I would buy
like uh 30 hot lattes from a cafe how
many 30 cuz there was like there was
like six people coming or we didn't know
sometimes people would come in and did
you say
3030 yeah nice and we would drink like
four per person or something you know
uhhuh man it's B I don't know if they
were powerful lattes you know but they
were lattes and um we would put in
plastic bag and I would drive there and
all the coffee was like falling you know
everywhere and then we'd go into course
and have these coffees here and we'd
work all night we'd play like techno
music and everybody would just work on
their like this was literally like
business people they would work in their
startup and we would all try and make
something and then the Sun would come up
and the morning people the you know the
the yoga uh yoga girls and yoga guys
would come in you know after the yoga
class at 6 and they say hey good morning
and we're like we look like this you
know and we're like what's up how are
you doing and we didn't know how bad we
looked you know but it was very bad and
uh then we'd go home sleep in like a
hostel or a hotel and do the same thing
and again and again and again and it was
this lockin mode you know like
working um and that was very fun so it's
just a a bunch of you music blasting all
through the night yeah more like like
indust not like see I for
me it's such an interesting thing
because the speed of the beat affects
how I feel about a thing So the faster
it is the more anxiety I feel but that
anxiety is channeled into productivity
but if it's a little too fast I start
the anxiety overpowers don't like drama
base music probably not no it's too fast
I mean for working I have to I have to
play with it it's like you can actually
like I can adjust my level of anxiety
this must be a better word than anxiety
it's like uh productive anxiety that I
like whatever that is it also depends
what kind of work you do right like if
you're writing you probably don't want
drama based music I think for codes like
industrial techno this kind of stuff
kind of fast it works well because you
really get like locked in and combined
with caffeine you know you go you go
deep you know and and I think you
balance on this edge of anxiety because
this caffeine is also hitting your
anxiety and you want to be on the edge
of anxiety with this techno running
sometimes it gets too much like stop the
Techno stop the music it's
like but uh but those are good memories
you know and also like travel memories
like you go from City to City yeah and
it feels like it's kind of like Jet Set
life like it's it's feels very beautiful
like you're you're seeing a lot of cool
cities and what was your favorite place
you remember you visited I think still
like uh Bangkok is the best place and
Bangkok and changai I think Thailand is
very special like I've been to the other
place like I've been to Vietnam and I've
been to South America and stuff I still
think Thailand wins in how nice people
are how easy of a life people have their
everything's cheap yeah good well bangok
is getting expensive now but changai is
still cheap I think when you're starting
out it's a great place man the air
quality sucks it's a big problem so um
and it's quite hot but that's a very
cool place um pros and cons I love
Brazil also my girlfriend is Brazilian
but I do love not just because of that
but I like Brazil brail uh the problem
still is the safety issue you know like
it's it's like in America like it's
localized it's hard for Europeans to
understand like safety's localized to
specific areas so if you go to the right
areas it's amazing Brazil is amazing if
you go to the wrong areas like you maybe
you die MH right yeah yeah I mean that's
true it's not true in Europe feel in
Europe is much more true more average
you're right you're right there it's
more averaged out yeah I like it when
there's strong neighborhoods when you're
like you cross a certain Street and
you're in in a dangerous part of town
man yeah it's I I I like it I like
there's certain cities in the United
States like that yeah I like that and
you're saying Europe is you don't feel
scared well I don't I like danger BJJ no
not even just that I think danger is
interesting so danger reveals something
about yourself about others also I like
the full range of humanity yeah so I
don't like the mellowed out aspects of
humanity I I have friends like theom
friends that are exactly like this like
they go to like the the kind of broken
areas you know like they like this
reality they like this authenticity more
they don't like luxury they don't like
oh yeah I hate luxury yeah it's very
European of you like wait was that
that's a whole another conversation so
you uh you uh quoted Freya Stark quote
to awaken quite alone in a strange town
is one of the most Pleasant Sensations
in the world yeah uh do you remember a
time you awoken in a strange town and
felt like that we're talking about small
towns or Big Towns or man anywhere I
think I wrote it in some blog post and
like it was a common thing when you
would wake up and this was like because
I have this website I started a website
about this D Nom like called Nomad
list.com and there was a community so it
was like 3, and other digital no man
because I was feeling lonely so I built
this website and I stopped feeling
lonely like I started make organizing
meetups and making friends and um and it
was very common that people would say
they would wake up and they would forget
where they are yeah like for the first
half minute and I had to look outside
like where am I which country which
sounds really like privileged but it's
more like funny like you literally don't
know where you are because you're so dis
rooted um but there's something man it's
like Anthony berdan you know there's
something pure about this kind
of vagab Bor travel thing you know like
it's behind me I think I don't like now
I travel with my girlfriend right it's
very different but it is romantic like
memories of this kind of like Vagabond
individualistic solo life but the thing
is didn't make me happy but it was very
cool but it didn't make me happy right
it made me anxious there's something
about it that made you anxious I don't
know I still feel like that it's a cool
feeling it's scary at first but then you
realize where you are and you and I
don't know it's like you'll awaken to
the possibilities of this place when you
feel like that it's like great and it's
even when you're doing some basic travel
I go to San Francisco or something El
yeah you have like the novelty effect
like you're in a new place like here
things are possible you know you you
you're you don't get bored yet
and and that's why people get addicted
to travel you know back to startups you
wrote a book on uh how to do this thing
and gave a great talk on it how to do
startups the book's called make
bootstrappers handbook yeah I was
wondering if you could go through some
of the steps it's idea build launch grow
monetize automate and exit there's a lot
of fascinating ideas in each one so idea
stage yeah how do you find a good idea
so I think you need to be able to spot
problems so for example you can go in
your daily life like when you wake up
and you're like what is stuff that I'm
really annoyed with that's like um in my
daily life that doesn't function well
and that's a problem that you can see
okay maybe that's something I can add
right code about you know code for and
it will make my life easier so I would
say make like a list of all these
problems you have and like idea to solve
it and see which one is like viable you
can actually do something and then start
building it so that's that's a really
good place to start
become open to all the problems in your
life like actually start noticing them I
think that's actually not a trivial
thing to do to realize that some aspects
of your life could be done way way
better yeah cuz we kind of very quickly
get accustomed to discomforts exactly uh
like for example like door knobs yeah
like design of certain things like new
cream and door off well that when I know
how much uh incredible design work has
gone into it's really interesting doors
and door knobs just the Design of
Everyday Things forks and spoons it's
going to be hard to come up with a fork
that's better than the current Fork
designs yeah and the other aspect of it
is you're saying like in order to come
up with interesting ideas you got to try
to live a more interesting life yeah but
that's where travel comes in yeah
because when I started traveling I
started seeing stuff in other countries
that you didn't have in Europe for
example or America even like if you go
to Asia uh like dude especially 10 years
ago nobody knew about this like weads
all these apps that they already had
before we had them these everything apps
right like now elon's trying to make X
this everything app like WeChat the same
thing like in Indonesia or tand do you
have one app that you can order food
with you can order groceries you can
order massage uh you can order car
mechanic um anything you can think of is
in the app and that stuff for example
you you know that's called like
Arbitrage you can go to back to your
country and build that same app for your
country for example so you start seeing
um problems you start seeing solutions
that other countries already other
people already did in the rest of the
world and also traveling in general just
gives you more problems cuz travel is
uncomfortable you know um airports are
horrible airplanes are not comfortable
either there's a lot of problems you
start seeing just getting out of your
house you know but also you can I mean
in the digital world you can just go
into different communities and see what
can be improved by the in that yeah yeah
but what specifically is your process of
generating ideas do you like do idea
dumps like do you have a document where
you just keep writing yeah I used to
have like a because when I was when I
wasn't making money I was trying to like
make this list of ideas to see like so I
need to build I was thinking
statistically already like I need to
build all these things and one of these
will work out probably you know so I
need to have a lot of things to try um
and I did that right now I think like
because I already have money I can do
more things uh based on technology so
for example AI when I found out about
when stable diffusion came or C gbt and
stuff all this thing all these things
were
like I didn't start working with them
because I had a problem I had no
problems but I was very curious about
technology and I was like playing with
it and figuring out like first just
playing with it and then and then you
find something like okay this generates
St Fusion generates houses very
beautiful and Interiors you know so it's
less about problem solving it's more
about the possibilities of new things
you can create yeah but that's very
risky because that's the G is like a
solution trying to find a problem yeah
and usually it doesn't work and that's
very common with with startup FS I think
they they have Tech but actually people
don't need to Tech right can you
actually explain it'd be cool to talk
about some of the stuff you created can
you explain um this photo.com yeah yeah
so it's like fire your photographer the
idea is like you don't need a
photographer anymore you can train
yourself as AI model and you can take as
many photos you want anywhere in any
clothes uh with facial expressions like
happy or sad or poses uh all this stuff
so how does how does it work so this is
uh you send me a link to a gallery of
ones done on me which is so on the left
you have the prompts the Box yeah so you
can write like so model is your model
this Lex Freedman so you can write like
model as a blah blah blah whatever you
want y then press the button and it will
take photos take will take like photos
what are you using for the hosting for
the compute replicates okay replicate
decom they're very very goods okay it's
cool like this interface wise it's cool
that you're showing how long it's going
to take this is amazing so it's taking a
I'm presuming you just loaded in a few
pictures from the internet yeah so I
went to Google images St in Lex Freedman
I added like 10 or 20 images you can
open them in the gallery and you can use
your cursors to yeah so some don't look
like you so the hit or miss rate is like
I don't know say like 50/50 or something
but when I was watching your Tweet like
it's been getting better and better and
better it was very bad in beginning it
was so bad but still people sign up to
it you know
uh there's there's two luxes is great
it's getting more and more sexual it's
making me very uncomfortable man but
that's the problem with these models cuz
no we need to talk about this cuz the
models the fusion yeah so the
photorealistic models that are like fine
tuned they were all trained on porn in
the beginning and there was a guy called
Hassan so I was trying to figure out how
to do photo realistic AI photos and it
was stable diffusion by itself is not
doing that well like the faces look all
mangled yep
um and it doesn't have enough resolution
or something to to do that well so but I
started seeing these these um base
models these fine tune models and people
would train on porn and I would try them
and they would be very photo realistic
they would have bodies that actually
made sense like body uh Anatomy um but
if you look at the photorealistic models
that people use now still there's still
core of porn there like of naked people
so I need to prompt out the nak and
everybody needs to do this with AI
startups with imaging you need to prompt
out the naked stuff you need to put a
you know naked um you have to keep
reminding the model you need to put
clothes on yeah don't put naked because
it's very risky I have Google Vision
that checks every photo before it's
shown to the user to like check foror oh
nfw detector because you get the
journalists get very angry if they you
know you if you sex there was a
journalist I think that would got angry
that used this and was like oh it it
made me it showed like a nipple because
Google Vision didn't detect it so
there's like these kind of problems you
need to deal with you know that's what
I'm talking about this is with cats
but look at the cat face it's also kind
of mangled you know I'm I'm uh I'm a
little bit disturbed you can zoom in on
the cat if you want like like yeah this
is a very sad cat it doesn't have a nose
it doesn't have a nose but this man but
this is the problem with AI startups
because they all act like it's perfect
like this is groundbreaking and but it's
not perfect it's like really bad you
know half the time so if I wanted to
sort of update model as yeah so you
remove this stuff and you write
like whatever you want like in Thailand
or something or in Tokyo uh in Tokyo
yeah and then you can say like at night
with neon lights like you can add more
detail to make I'll go in Austin do you
think you'll know in Texas in Austin
Texas cowboy hats in Texas yeah as a as
a
cowboy as a cowboy it's going to go so
uh towards the porn Direction it's it's
man I hope not this is the end of my
career
or the beginning it depends we can send
you a push notification when your photos
are done all right
cool yeah let's see oh wow so this whole
interface you've built this is really
well done J cury so I still use J cury
the only one still after this day you're
not the only one the entire of the web
is PHP thep and jur yeah and SQL lights
you're just like one of the top
performers from a programming
perspective that are still like openly
talking about it but every everyone's
using PHP like if you look most of the
web is still probably PHP 70% it's
because of Wordpress right cuz the blogs
are that's true yeah um true I'm seeing
a Revival now people are getting sick of
Frameworks um like all the JavaScript
Frameworks are so like what do you
called like wieldy like they're so it
takes so much work to just maintain this
code and then it updates to a new
version you to change everything BEP
just stays the same and works yeah and
can you actually just speak to that
stack you you build all your websites
apps startups projects all of that with
mostly vanilla HTML yeah uh JavaScript
with J jQuery PHP and cool white so that
that's a really simple stack and you get
stuff done really fast that can you just
speak to the philosophy behind that I
think it's accidental because that's the
thing I I knew like I knew PHP I knew
HML um CSS you know because you make
websites and when my startup started
taken off I didn't have time to I
remember putting on my to-do list like
learn node.js cuz I it's important to
switch you know cuz this obviously is
much better language than PHP and I
never learned it I never did it uh
because the time I I these things were
growing like this and I was launching
more project and I never had time it's
like one day you know I'll I'll start
coding properly and I never got to it I
I sometimes wonder if I need to learn
that stuff it's still to-do atem for me
to really learn node.js or or flask or
these kind of react yeah react and it's
there it feels like a responsible
software engineer should know how to use
these but you can get stuff
done so fast with vanilla versions of
stuff yeah it's like software developers
if you want to get a job and there's
like you know people making stuff like
startups and if you want to be
entrepreneur probably you maybe
shouldn't I wonder if there's like I
really want to measure performance and
speed I think there's a deep wisdom in
that yeah I do think that Frameworks and
just constantly wanting to learn the new
thing this complicated way of software
engineering gets in the way I'm not sure
what to say about that because
definitely like you shouldn't build
everything from just vanilla JavaScript
or vanilla C for example C++ When You're
Building Systems engineering is like
there's a lot of benefits for a pointer
safety all that kind of stuff so I I
don't know but it just feels like you
can get so much more stuff done if you
don't care about how you do it man this
is my most controversial take I think
and maybe I'm wrong but I feel like
there's Frameworks now that raise money
they raise a lot of money like they
raise 50 million 100 million 300 million
dollars and the idea is that you need to
make the developers the new developers
like when you're 18 or 20 years old
right um get them to use this framework
and then add a platform to it like where
the framework can it's open source but
you probably should use the platform
which is paid to use it and the the cost
of the platforms to host it are a
thousand times higher than just hosting
it on a simple AWS server or VPS on
digital ocean right um so there's
obviously like a monetary incentive here
like we want to get a lot of developers
to use this technology and then we need
to charge them money because they're
going to use it in startups and then the
starts can pay for the bills um but what
that it kind of destroys the
the information out there about learning
to code because they you know they pay
YouTubers they pay influencers developer
influen is a big thing to like um and
same thing what happens with like uh
nutrition in Fitness or something same
thing happens in developing they pay
this influen to promote the stuff use it
make stuff with it make demo product
with it and then a lot of people like
wow uh use this and I started noticing
this because when I was ship my stuff
people would ask me what are you using I
I would say I just PHP JQ why does it
matter and people would start kind of
attacking me like why are you not using
this new technology this new framework
this new thing and I say I don't know
cuz this PHP thing works and I don't
really I'm optimizing for anything just
doing it just works and I never
understood like why uh like I understand
there's new technologies that are better
and it should be Improvement but I'm
very suspicious of money just like
lobbying there's money in this developer
framework scene there's hundreds of
millions that goes to ads or influenc or
whatever it can't all go to developers
you don't need Developers for framework
and it's open
source to make a lot of more money on
these startups so that's a really good
perspective but in addition to that is
like when you say
better it's
like can we get some data on the better
because like I want to know from the
individual developer perspective and
then from a team of five team of 10 team
of 20 developers
yeah uh measure how productive they are
in uh shipping features how many bugs
they create
how many security holes uhp was not good
of security for a while but now it's
good in theory in theory is it though
now no no now as as you're saying it I
want to know if that's true because PHP
was just the majority of websites on the
internet could be true is it just over
represented same with WordPress yes
there's a reputation that WordPress has
a gigantic number of security holes I
don't know if that's true I I know it
gets attacked a lot because it's so
popular it definitely does have security
holes but maybe a lot of other systems
have security holes as well anyway like
I just sort of questioning the
conventional wisdom that keeps wanting
to push software Engineers towards
Frameworks towards
complex like uh super complicated sort
of software engineering approaches that
stretch out the the time it takes to
actually build a thing 100% And it's the
same thing with big corporations 80% of
the people don't do anything it's like
it's not efficient and and if you if
your your your benchmark is like uh
people building stuff that actually gets
done and like for society right like if
we want to save time we should probably
use technology that's
um that's simple that's pragmatic that's
like that works uh that's not overly
complicated doesn't make your life like
a living hell you know and use a
framework when it obviously solves a
problem a direct problem that you of
course you yeah of course I'm not saying
you should code without a framework you
should use whatever you want
but yeah I think it's suspicious you
know and um and I think when I talk
about on Twitter like there's a lot this
this Army comes out you know this this
these framework armies yeah man
something my gut tells me you I want to
ask the framework Army what have they
built this week it's the Elon question
what did you do this week yeah did you
make money with it you know did you
charge users is it a real business and
um yeah uh so going back to the Cowboy
first of all some don't look like you
right but some do every aspect of this
is pretty incredible I'm also just
looking at the interface it's really
well done so this is all just jQuery and
yeah this is really well done so like
tell take me through the Journey of
photo AI like you don't know much most
of the world doesn't know much about uh
stable diffusion or any of this any of
the generative AI stuff and so you're
thinking okay how can I build cool stuff
with this what was the origin story of
photo AI I think uh it started cuz
stable diffusion came out so stable
diffusion is like this the first like
generative image mod model AI model and
um I started playing with it like you
could install it on your Mac like
somebody forked it and made it work for
MacBooks so I downloaded it and uh
cloned the repo and started using it to
generate images um and it was like
amazing like it would I found it on
Twitter because you see things happen on
Twitter and I I would post what I was
making on Twitter as well and you could
make any image you could write a prompt
to essentially write a prompt and then
it generates a photo of that or image of
that um in any style like they would use
like artist names to make like a Picasso
kind of style and stuff um and I was
trying to see like what is it good at is
it good at people no it's really bad at
people but it was good at houses so
architecture for example I would
generate like architecture houses um so
I made a website called this house does
exist. org and it generated like they
called like house porn and that one like
house porn it's like a subreddit so and
this was stable diffusion like the first
version so looks really you can click
for another photo so it generates like
all these kind of non-existing houses it
is house point but it looked kind of
good you know like especially back then
now things look much
better um this really really well
done wow and it also generates like a
description and you can up vote is it
nice up vote it man there's so much to
talk to you about like the choices here
is this is very Scrappy in the bottom
there's like a ranking of the most up
voted houses so these are the top voted
if you go to old time you see quite
beautiful
ones yeah so this one is my favorite the
number one it's like kind of like a um
how is this not more popular it was
really popular for like a while but then
people got so bored of it I think cuz I
was getting bored of it too like just
continuous house porn like everything
starts looking the same but then I
thought it was really good at interior
so I pivoted to interior ai.com
where um I tried to like upload first
generate interior designs and then I
tried to do like there was a new
technology called image to image where
you can input an image like a photo and
it would kind of modify the thing mhm so
you see it looks almost the same as
photo it's the same code essentially um
nice so I would I would upload a photo
of my interior where I lived and I would
ask like change this into like a I don't
know like maximalist design you know and
it worked and it worked really well so I
was like okay this is a startup because
obviously interior design Ai and
nobody's doing that yet so I launched
this and it was successful and made like
in within a week made 10K 20K a month
and now still makes like 40K 50k a month
uh and it's been like two years so then
I was like how can I improve this
interior design I need to start learning
fine-tuning and fine tuning is where you
have this existing AI model and you fine
tune it on the specific goal you wanted
to do so I would find really beautiful
interor design make a gallery and um
train a new model that was very good at
interior design and it worked and I used
that as well and then for fun I uploaded
photos of
myself and here's where it happened uh
and to train myself like and this would
never work obviously and it worked and
actually it started understanding me as
a concept so my face worked and and you
could do like different styles like me
as a like very cheesy medieval warrior
all this stuff so I was like this is
another a startup so now I Avatar ai. me
I couldn't get the do and this was uh
this was yeah Avatar ai. me well now it
forwards to phot because I pivoted got
it but this was more like
cheesy thing so this is very interesting
because this went so viral it made like
I think like 150k in a week or something
it's the most money I ever made and um
and then big this is very interesting
the big VC companies like lenza which
are much better at iOS and stuff than me
I didn't have IOS app they quickly build
the IOS app that does the same and they
found technology and it's all open
technology so it's good and I think they
made like $30 million with it yeah they
they became like the top grossing app
after that um and it was how how do you
feel about that I think it's amazing
honestly and it's not like you didn't
have like a feeling like ah fuck no I
was a little bit like sad cuz all my
products would work out and I never had
like real Fierce competition and now I
have like Fierce competition from like a
a very skilled High sent like iOS
Developer Studio or something that and
and they already had an app they had an
app in the app store for like um I think
retouching your face or something so
they were very smart they add these
avatars to there it's a feature they had
the users they do a push notification to
everybody who have these avatars Yeah
man they made C I think they made they
made so much money and um I think they
did a really great job and uh I also
made a lot of money with it but that was
I I I quickly realized it wasn't my
thing because it was so cheesy it was
like kit you know it's kind of like um
me as a Barbie or me as a you know it
was too cheesy I wanted to go for like
what's a real problem we can solve
because this is going to be a hype this
is going to be and it was a hype this
Avatar um it's like let's do real
photography like how can you make people
look really photorealistic and it was
difficult and that's why these offs word
because they were all like in a Cheesy
you know Picasso style and art is easy
because you interpret the the all the
problems that AI has with your face are
like artistic you know if you call it
Picasso but if you make a real photo all
the problems with your face like it just
you look wrong you know mhm so I started
making photo AI which was like a pivot
of it where it was like a photo studio
um where you could take photos without
actually needing a photographer needing
a studio you don't just you know you
just type it and I've been working on it
for like the last yeah it's really
incredible that journey is really
incredible let's go to the beginning of
photo AI though cuz I remember seeing a
lot of re really hilarious photos I
think you were using yourself as a case
study right yeah yeah so what uh there's
a tweet here
sold
$100,000 in AI generated avatars yeah
it's a lot like it's a lot for anybody
it's a lot for me like uh making 10K a
day on this you know that's
amazing that's amazing and then the
nested tweet like that's a launch tweet
and then the before there is like the me
hacking on it oh I see so that
okay so October 26 2022 I trained an ml
model on my
face sure because my eyes are quite far
apart I learned when I did YouTube I
would put like a photo of like my DJ
photo you know my mixure and people
would say I look like a hammerhead shark
was like the top comment so then I
realized my eyes are far apart uh yeah
the internet helps you realiz who how
you look you know boy do I love the
internet first first
trap what what is is this wait it's
water from the waterfall but the
waterfall is in the back you know so
what's going
on so this is how much of this is real
it's all AI it's all AI yeah that's
pretty good though for the early days
exactly so but this was hit or miss so
you had to do love curation cuz 99% of
it was really bad MH so these are the
photos I uploaded how many photos did
you use only these I will try more up to
date picks later these are the these are
the only photos you uploaded yeah wow
wow wow okay so like you were learning
all this super quickly what uh what are
some like interesting details you
remember from that time for like what
you have to figure out to make it work
and for people just listening he
uploaded just uh just a handful of
photos that don't really have a good
capture of the face and he's able to or
I think it's cropped it's like a cropped
by the by the the layout but they're
they're Square photos so they're 512 by
512 mhm because that's stable fusion um
but nevertheless not great captures the
face like it's not it's not like a uh
collection of several hundred photos
that it's like exactly like I I would
imagine that too when I started I was
like a this must be like some 3D scan
technology right yeah so I think the
cool thing with AI it trains the concept
of you so it's literally like learning
just like any AI model leurs it learns
how you look so I I did this and then I
was getting so I was getting DMs like
telegram messages like how can I do the
same thing I want these photos my
girlfriend wants these photo so I was
like okay this is obviously a business
but I didn't have time to code it uh
make a whole like app about it so I made
a HTML page um registered a domain name
and this was not even it was a stripe
payment link which means you have uh
literally link to stripe to pay but
there's no code in the back so all you
know is you have customers that paid
money then I added like a some uh a typ
form link so Ty form is a site where you
can have create like your own um input
form like Google forms so they would get
a email with a link to the type form or
actually just a link after the checkout
and they could upload their photos so
enter their email upload the photos and
um and I launched it and I was like here
first sale so this October
2022 and I think within like the first
24 hours was like I'm not sure it was
like a thousand customers or something
um but the problem was I didn't have
code to automate this so I had to do
manually so the first few hundred I just
literally took their photos uh train
them and then I would generate the
photos with the prompts and I had this
text file with the promps and I would do
everything manually and this quickly
became way too much so but that's
another constraint like I was forced to
code something up uh that would do that
and that was essentially making it into
a real website right so first it was the
type form and they uploaded through the
typ form strip check out form yeah and
then you were like that image is
downloaded did you write a script to
export down download the images myself
it's a zip file unzip file you unzipped
it un yes and then I no I'm because you
know do things don't skill Paul graah
says right so uh and then I would train
it and then I would email them the
photos I think from my personal email
say here's your here's your avatars you
know and they liked it they were like
wow it's
amazing you emailed them with your
personal email it didn't have an email
address on this domain and this is like
a 100 people yeah and then you know who
signed up uh like man I cannot say but
really famous people like really really
like billionaires famous Tech
billionaires did it and I was like wow
this is crazy and I sent I was like so
scared to message them so I said thanks
so much for using my sites you know he's
like yeah amazing app gra work so it's
like this is different than normal
reaction you know it's Bill Gates isn't
it can say
anything just like shirtless P gdpr you
know like privacy European regulation
canot share anything but I was very I
was like Wow and uh but this shows like
so you make something and then if it
takes off very fast you're like it's
validated you know you're like
here's something that people really want
but then also I thought this is hype
this is going to die down very fast and
I did because it's too cheesy but you
have to automate the whole thing how'
you automate it so like what's the AI
component like how hard was that to
figure out okay so that's actually in
many ways the easiest thing because
there is all these platforms already
back then there was platforms for uh
fine-tune St diffusion um like now I use
replicate back then I use different
platforms um which was funny because
that platform when this thing took off I
would tweet cuz I tweet always like how
much money these websites make and then
so the the you called vendor right the
the G the platform that did the gpus
they increased their price for training
from $3 to $20 after they saw that I was
making so much money so immediately my
profit is gone because I was selling
them for
$30 and I was in a slack with them like
saying what is this like can you just
put it back to $3 they say yeah maybe in
the future we're looking at it right now
I'm like what are you talking about like
you just took all my money you know and
they're smart well they're not that
smart because like you also have a large
uh platform and a lot of people respect
you so you can literally come out and
say that they're not I think it's like
kind of dirty to cancel a company or
something I I prefer just bringing my
business elsewhere but there was no
elsewhere back then right so I started
talking to other um AI model ml
platforms so replicade was one those
platforms and I started dming the CEO
say can you please create like it's
called dream Boo this fine tuning of you
yourself can you add this to your site
CU I need this cuz I'm being price gods
and he said no because it takes too long
to run it takes half an hour to run and
we don't have the gpus for it I said
please please please and then after a
week they said we're doing it we're
launching this and then this company
became it was like not very famous
company it became very famous with this
stuff because suddenly everybody was
like oh we can build similar apps like
Avatar apps and everybody started
building Avatar apps and everybody
started using replicate for it um and it
was from these early DMS with like the
CEO like Ben Fish very nice guy and he
was like
they never price go me they never treat
me bad they always been very nice it's
it's a very cool company so you can run
any ml model any AI model llms you can
run on here and you can scale yes they
scale yeah yeah and I mean you can do
now you can click on the model and just
run it already it's like super easy you
log in with GitHub um that's great and
by running it on the website then you
can automate with the API you can make a
website that runs the model generate
images generate text generate vide
generate music generate spech find two
models do anything yeah it's very cool
company nice and you're like growing
with them essentially they grew because
of you because it's like a big use case
yeah like the the website even looks
weird now it it started as like a
machine learning platform that was like
I didn't even understand what it did it
was just too to ml you know like you
would understand because you're in the
ml world I wouldn't understand now it's
newb friendly yeah exactly and I didn't
know how it worked and um but I knew
that they could probably do this and
they did it they built the models and
now I use them for everything and we
trained like I think now like 36,000
models 36,000 people already but is
there some tricks to fine tuning to like
the collection of photos that are
provided like how do you like yes man
it's so many Hecks the hack it's like
100 Hecks to make it work what what's
what are some my secrets now well not
not the secrets but the more like
insights maybe about the human face and
the human body like what what kind of
stuff get messed up a
lot I think people well man it's thing
people don't know know how they look so
um yeah they generate photos of
themselves and then they say ah it
doesn't look like me yeah but it then
you know you can check the training
phones it does look like you but you
don't know how you look so there's a
face dysmorphia of yourself that you you
have no idea how you look yeah that's
hilarious I mean I've got to one one of
the least Pleasant activities in my
existence is having to listen to my
voice and look at my face so I get to
like
really really have to sort of uh coming
to terms with the reality of how I look
and how I sound and everybody and but
people often don't right like you have a
distorted view perspective I know that
like I would if I would make a selfie
how I think I look that I that's nice
other people think that's not nice but
then they make a photo of me I'm like
that's super ugly but then they're like
no that's how you look and you look nice
you know so how other people see you is
nice so you need to ask other people to
choose your photos yeah you shouldn't
choose them yourself because you don't
know how you look
yeah you don't know what makes you
interesting what makes you attractive
all this kind of stuff and a lot of us
this is dark aspect of psychology we
focus on some small flaws yeah this why
I hate plastic surgery for example
people try to remove the flaws when the
flaws are the thing that makes you
interesting and attractive I learned
from the hammerhead shark eyes this the
stuff about you that looks ugly to you
and it's probably that What Makes You
original makes you nice and people like
it about you and it's not like oh my God
and people notice it people notice your
Hammer had eyes you know but it's like
that's me that's my face so I'm I love I
love myself and that's confidence and
confidence is attractive yes right
confidence is attractive but yes
understanding what makes you beautiful
it's the breaking of symmetry makes you
beautiful it's the breaking of the the
average face makes you beautiful all
that yeah and obviously different for
men and women at different ages all this
kind of stuff but be Underneath It All
the personality all of that when when
the
face comes alive that also is the thing
that makes you Beau beautiful but anyway
you have to figure all that out with AI
yeah one thing that worked was like um
people would upload full body photos of
themselves so I would crop the face
right because and then the model knew
better that we're training mostly the
face here but then I started losing uh
resemblance of the body because some
people are skinny some people are
muscular whatever so you want to have
that too uh so now I mix full body
photos in the training with face photos
face crops uh and it's all automatic
like um and I know that other people
they they use again AI mod to detect
like what are the best photos in this
training set and then train on those but
it's all it's all about training data
and that's with everything in AI like
how good your training data is is in
many ways more important than how many
steps you train for like how many months
or whatever with these gpus like um the
golds do you have any guidelines for
people of like how to get good data how
to give good data to find tune on like
the photos should be diverse so for
example if I only upload photos with a
brown shirt or green shirt the mulle
think that I'm training the green shirt
so the things that are the same every
photo are the concepts that are trained
what you want is your face to be the
concept that's strains um and everything
else to be diverse like different so
diverse lighting as well diverse yeah
Outside Inside uh but there's no like
this is the problem there's no like
manual for this and nobody knew we were
all just especially two years ago we're
all hacking trying to test anything
anything you can think of and uh it's
frustrating it's one of the most
frustrating and also fun and challenging
things to do because with AI CU it's a
black box and like carpati I think says
this like uh we don't really know how
this thing works but it does something
but nobody really knows why right like
we cannot look into the the model of an
llm like what is actually in there we
just know it's like a 3D Matrix of
numbers right um so it's very
frustrating CU some things you that
would be you think they're obvious that
they will improve things will make them
worse and there's so many parameters you
can tweak so you're testing everything
to you know improve things I mean
there's a whole field now of mechanistic
interpretability that like studies that
tries to figure out tries to break thing
apart and understand how it works but
you know there's also the data side and
the the actual like consumer facing
product side of figuring out how do you
get it to generate a thing that's
beautiful or interesting or naturalistic
all that kind of stuff and you're like
at the Forefront of figuring that out
about the human face and humans really
care about the human face yeah very vain
yeah like me you know like I want to
look good in your podcast for example
yeah for sure and one of the things I
actually would love to uh like
rigorously use Photo AI because for the
thumbnails I take portraits of people I
didn't I don't know shit about
photography uh I basically used your
approach for photography I like Google
how do you take photographs yeah
camera lighting and also it's tough
because maybe you could speak to this
also but like with
photography no offense to any they're
true artists great photographers but
like people like take themselves way too
seriously think you need a whole lot of
equipment you definitely don't want one
light you need like five lights I know
like and you have to have like the
lenses and I talked to to a guy an
expert of uh shaping the sound in a room
okay and cuz I was thinking I'm going to
do a podcast Studio whatever I should
probably like treat the do a sound
treatment on the room and like when he
showed up and analyzed the room he
thought everything I was doing was
horrible and then that's when I realized
like you know what I don't need experts
in my life he kick him out of the house
no I didn't kick him I me I said Thank
you thank you very much thank you great
tips all I just I just felt like there
is you know focus on whatever the
problems are use your own judgment use
your own instincts don't listen to other
people and only consult other people
when there's a specific problem and you
consult them not to offload the problem
onto them but to gain wisdom from their
perspective even if their perspective is
ultimately one you don't agree with
you're going to gain wisdom from that
and just I ultimately come up with like
a PHP solution PHP and jQuery solution
the PHP Studio like have a little
suitcase I use like uh just the the
basic sort of uh consumer type of stuff
one light it's great yeah and look at
you you're like one of the top podcasts
in the world and you get millions of
views and it works and the people that
spend so much money on optimizing for
the best sound for the best studio they
get like 300 views you know so what is
this about this is about that either you
do it really well or also that a lot of
these things don't matter like what
matters is probably the content the
podcast like you get interesting guest
focus on the stuff that matters yeah and
I think that's very common they called
gear acquisition syndrome like gas like
people in any industry do this they just
buy all the stuff there was a meme
recently like you buy what's the name
for the guy that buys all the stuff
before he even started doing the hobby
right um marketing you know marketing
does that to people they want to buy
this stuff yeah but like
man you you can make a you can make a
Hollywood movie on an iPhone you know if
the content is good enough it's it and
it will probably be original because you
would be using an iPhone for it you know
so that said I so the reason I brought
that up with
photography there is wisdom from people
and one of one of the things I realized
you probably also realized this but how
much power light
has to uh to convey emotion you just
take one light and move it around say
you're sitting in the darkness mooving
around your face the different positions
are having a second light potentially
you can play with how a person feels
just from a generic face it's
interesting like you can make people
attractive you can make them ugly you
can make them scary you can make them
lonely all of this and so you kind of
real start to realize this and uh I
would definitely love AI help in uh
creating great portraits of people guest
photos yeah guest photos for example
that's a small use case but for me
that's
a I suppose it's an important use case
because like I want people to look good
but I also want to capture who they are
maybe my conception of who they are what
makes them beautiful what makes their
appearance powerful in some ways
sometimes it's the eyes often times it's
the eyes but there's certain features of
the face can sometimes be really
powerful and I can't it's it's also kind
of awkward for me to take yeah yeah yeah
photographs so I'm not collecting enough
yeah photographs for myself to do it um
with just those photographs if I can
load that off fun to Ai and then start
to play with like lighting you should do
this and you should probably do it
yourself like you can get use photo but
it's even more fun if you do it yourself
so you train the models you can learn
about like control net control net is
where for example your photos and your
podcast are usually like from the angle
right so you can create a control net
face posst that's always like this so
every model every photo you generate
uses this control net uh pose for
example I think it would be very fun for
you to try out that stuff do you play
with lighting at all do you play with
lighting with with man actually this
like this week or recently there's a new
model came out that can adjust the light
of any photo but also AI image uh with
stable diffusion uh I think it's called
relight and it's amazing like you can
you can upload kind of like a a light
map so for example red purple blue and
it uses that light map to change the
light on the photo to you you input it's
amazing so there's for sure a lot of
stuff you can do uh what's your advice
for people people in general on how to
learn all the state-of-the-art AI tools
available like you mentioned new models
coming out all the time yeah like what
how do you pay attention how do you stay
on top of everything I think you need to
join Twitter X you know X is amazing now
and the whole AI industry is on X and
they're all like anime avatars so it's
funny because uh my friends asked me
this like what who should I follow to
stay stay up to date and I say go to x
and follow all the AI anime model that
this person is following or follows and
I sent them some URL and they all start
laughing like what is this but they're
real like people hacking around in AI
they get hired by big companies and
they're on X and most of them are
Anonymous this is very funny they're
they use anime avars um I don't um but
those people hack around and they they
publish what they're discovering um they
talk about papers for example uh so yeah
definitely X it's great I almost
exclusively all the people I follow are
AI people people yeah it's a good time
now it well but also just brings
happiness to my to my soul cuz there's
so much turmoil on Twitter yeah like
politics and stuff there's battles going
on it's like a war zone and it's nice to
just go into this happy place to where
people are building stuff yeah 100% I
like Twitter that for that most like
building stuff like yeah seeing other
cuz it inspires you to build and it's
it's just fun to see other people share
what they're discovering and then
you're like okay I'm going to make
something too it's just super fun and so
if you want to start go on X and then I
would go to replicate and start trying
to play with models and when you have
something that kind of you you manually
enter stuff you set the parameters
something that works you you can make an
app out of it or website can you speak a
little bit more to the process of it
becoming better and better and better
photo yeah so I had this photo and a lot
of people using it there was like a
million or more photos a month being
generated and I discovered I was testing
parameters like increase the step count
of generating a photo or changing the
sampler like a scheduler like you have
DPM two caras all these things I don't
know anything about but I know that you
can choose them when you generate image
and they have different resulting images
but I didn't know which one was were
better so I would do it myself test it
but then I was like why don't I test on
these users because I have a million
photos generated anyway so un like 10%
of the users I would um randomly test
parameters and then I would see if they
would because you can favor it photo or
you can download it I would measure if
they favored or like the photo and then
I would AB test and you test for
significance and stuff uh which
parameters were were better and which
were worse so you're starting to figure
out which Which models are actually
working well and then if it's
significant enough data you switch to
that for the whole you know all the
users and so that was that was like the
Breakthrough to make it better just use
the users to improve it themselves and I
tell them when they sign up we do
sampling we do testing on your photos
with random parameters and that work
really well I don't do a lot of testing
anymore because it's like I kind of
reached like a diminishing point where
it's like it's kind of good um but
that's there was a breakthrough yeah so
it's really about the parameters and
models that CH and letting the
users help do the search in the space of
models and parameters for you yeah but
actually so like stable diff Fusion I
used 1.5 two 2.0 came out as stab Fusion
XL came out all these new versions and
they were all worse and so the core
scene of people are still using 1.5
because it's like it's also not like
what do you call neutered like they they
neutered like to make it super like with
safety features and stuff so most of the
people are still on stable diffusion 1.5
and meanwhile stable diffusion the
company went like the CEO left um a lot
of drama happened because they couldn't
make money and yeah so they gave us it's
very interesting they gave us this this
open source model that everybody uses
they raised like hundreds of millions of
dollars it all they didn't make any
money with it or not a lot they did an
amazing job and now everybody use this
open source model for free and they did
you know it's amazing like it's a it's
amazing you're not even using the latest
one you're say no and the strange thing
is that this company raised hundreds of
millions but the people that are
benefiting from it are really small like
people like me who make these small apps
that are using the model and and now
they're starting to charge money for the
new models but the new models are not so
good for people do not sell open source
right yeah it's interesting because open
source is so impact in the AI space but
you wonder like what is the business
model behind that but it's enabling this
whole ecosystem of companies that yeah
they're using open source models it's
kind of like those Frameworks but then
they didn't you know bribe enough
influencers to use it um and they didn't
charge money for the platform you know
okay so back to your book and the
ideas we didn't even get to the first
step uh generating ideas so you had the
notebook and you're filling it up how do
you know when an idea is a good one like
what you you have this just flood of
ideas how do you pick the one that you
actually try to build man mostly you
don't know like mostly I choose the ones
that are most viable for me to build
like I cannot build a space company now
right would be quite challenging but I
can build something actually write down
like space company no I I think asteroid
mining would be very cool because like
you you go to an asteroid you take some
stuff from there you bring it back you
sell it you know it's but then you need
to do and you can hire someone to launch
the thing so all you need is like the
robot that goes to the asteroid you know
and Robotics interesting like I want to
also learn robotics so maybe that could
be I think both the asteroid Mining and
the robotics is yeah
together I feel like no exactly this is
it this is says we do this not because
it's easy but because we thought it
would be easy exactly that's me with
that's me with Aster mining exactly
that's why I should do this it's not
Nomad list.com it's it's
you have to like build stuff you have to
gravity is really hard to overcome yeah
but it seems man I sound like idiots
probably now but it sounds quite
approachable like relatively
approachable you don't have to build a
rocket you oh you use something like
SpaceX SpaceX to send your your you know
this dog robot or whatever so is there
actually exist a notebook where you
wrote Don estro might no I used back
then I used Trello Trello yeah but now I
don't really I use telegram I write down
like saved messages and I have like idea
I write down you type to yourself on you
know like cuz you use WhatsApp right I
think so you have like message to
yourself thing also yeah so yourself on
telegram yeah you use like a notepad not
forget stuff and then I pinets you know
I love how like you're not using super
complicated systems or whatever you know
people use obsidian now there's a lot of
these um yeah a notion where you have
systems for not taking you're not you're
notepad you're notepad.exe guy if you're
a Windows user man I saw some YouTubers
doing this like there's a lot of these
productivity gurus also and they do this
whole like iPad with a pencil and then I
also had an iPad and I also got the
pencil and I got this app where you can
like draw on paper like um draw like a
calendar you know like like people
students use this and you do coloring
and stuff and I'm like dude I did this
for a week and I'm like what am I doing
with my life like I can just write it as
a message to myself and it's good enough
you know speaking of ideas you shared a
tweet explaining why the first idea
sometimes might be a brilliant idea the
reason for this you think is the first
idea submerges from your subconscious
was actually boiling your brain for
weeks months sometimes years in the
background the eight hours of thinking
can never compete with a Perpetual
subconscious background job so this is
the idea that if you think about an idea
for 8 hours versus like the first idea
that pops into your mind yeah and
sometimes there is
subconscious like stuff that you've been
thinking about for many years that's
really emerges I wrote it wrong because
I don't know I'm not native English but
it emerges from your subconscious right
it comes from the like a water here your
subconscious in here it's boiling and
then when it's ready it's like ding it's
like microwave comes out and there you
have your idea you think you have ideas
like that yeah all the time 100% it's
just stuff that's been like there yes
yeah and I also it comes up and I bring
it I send it back you know like send it
back to the kitchen boil more yeah and
it's like a soup that of ideas that's
cooking it's 100% this is how my brain
works and I think most people but it's
also about the the timing sometimes you
have to send it back not just because
you're not ready but the world is not
ready yeah so many times like starter
fins are too early with their idea yeah
100% robotics is an interesting one for
that because like there's been a lot of
Robotics companies that failed yeah
because it's been very difficult to
build a robotics company make money
because there the manufacturing like the
cost of everything the intelligence of
the robot is enough is not sufficient to
create a compelling enough product from
which to make money so all so there's
this long line of Robotics companies
that' tried they had Big Dreams and they
failed yeah like Boston Dynamics I still
don't know what they're doing but they
always upload YouTube videos and it's
amazing but I feel like a lot of these
companies don't have a it's like a
solution looking for a problem for now
you know military obviously is usess but
like and do I do I need like a robotic
dog now for my house I don't know like
it's fun but it doesn't really solve
anything yet I feel the same kind of
with VR like it's really cool like apple
Vision Pro is very cool doesn't really
solve something for me yet and that's
kind of the the tech looking for a
solution right but one day will when the
person on computer when the Mac came
along there was a big switch that
happened it somehow captivated
everybody's imagination you could like
the application the killer apps became
apparent you can type in a computer but
did they became apparent like
immediately back then they also had like
this thing like we don't need these
computers uh they're like a hype and um
and it also went like in kind of like
you know W yeah yeah but the hype is the
thing that allowed the thing to
proliferate sufficiently to where people
Minds would start opening up to it a
little bit the possibility of right now
for example with the robotics there's
very few robots in the homes of people
exactly yeah the the robots that are
there are roombas so the vacuum cleaners
or they're Amazon Alexa yeah or
dishwasher I mean it's essentially a
robot yes but the the intelligence is
very limited I guess there one way we
can summarize all of them except Alexa
which is pretty intelligent
but uh is is limited with the kind of
ways it interacts with you it's you know
that that's just one example yeah I
sometimes think about that is like if
some people in this world were kind of
born in their whole existence is
like they were meant to build the thing
yeah you know like I sometimes wonder
like what my what I was meant to do you
have these plans for your life you have
these
dreams I think you're meant to build
robots Okay me personally maybe maybe
um that that that's a sense I've I've
had but it could be other things it
could hilariously enough be the thing I
was meant to be is to talk to people
yeah which is weird because I always was
anxious about talking to people it's
like a really yeah I'm scared of this I
scared yeah exactly I'm scared of you
it's just anxiety throughout social
interaction in general I'm an introvert
that hides from the world so yeah it's
really strange yeah but that's that's
also kind of Li like life brings you to
it's very hard to um super intently kind
of choose what you're going to do with
your life it's it it's more like surfing
you're surfing the waves you go in the
in the ocean you see where you end up
you know yeah yeah and there's Universe
has a kind of sense of humor yeah I
guess you have to just yeah allow
yourself to be carried away by the wayes
yeah exactly yeah yeah have you felt
that way in your life yeah all the time
like yeah that's like I think that's the
best way to live your life so whatever
to happen like do you know what you're
doing in the next few years is it
possible that it'll be completely like
changed possibly I I think relationships
like you want to hold relationships
right you want to hold your girlfriend
you want to become wife and all the
stuff but uh you should I think you
should stay open to where like like for
example where you want to live like I
don't know we don't know where we want
to live for example um that's something
that will figure itself out it will
crystallize where you know you will get
you will get sent by the waves to
somewhere where you want to live for
example what you're going to do I think
that's a really good way to live your
life it's I I think most stress comes
from trying to control like hold things
like um it's kind of Buddhist you know
you need to like lose control let it
lose and then things will happen like
when you do mushrooms when you do drugs
like psychedelic drugs the people that
starts that are like control freaks get
bad trips right because you need to let
go like I'm pretty control freak
actually and um when I did mushrooms
when I was 17 I I it was very good and
at the end it wasn't so good cuz I tried
to control was like ah now it's going
too much you now I need to let's stop
bro you can't stop it you need to go
through with it you know and so I think
it's a good manhor for life I think
that's you know very tranquil way to
lead your life yeah actually when I um
took
kaasa that lesson is deeply within me
already that you can't control anything
yes I think I probably learned that the
most in Jiu-Jitsu so just let go and
relax yeah and that's why I had just an
incredible experience there's like
literally no negative aspect to my iasa
experience or any psychedelics I've ever
had some of that could be with my
biology or my genetics whatever but some
of it was just not trying to control and
just surf the way for sure I think most
stress in life comes from trying to
control so once you have the idea yeah
step two build how do you think about
building The Thing Once you have the
idea I think you should build with the
technology that you know so for example
um Nomad list which is like this website
I made to figure out the best cities to
live and work as digital Nomad uh it
wasn't a website it launched as a Google
spreadsheet so it was a public Google
spreadsheet anybody could edit and I was
like I'm collecting like cities where we
we can live as eom with the internet
speed the cost of living um you know
other stuff and I would I tweeted it and
I would and back then I didn't have a
lot of followers I had like a few
thousand followers or something and it
went like viral for my skill viral back
then you know which was like five
retweets and um and a lot of people
started editing it and there was like
hundreds of cities in this list like
from of the world with all the data was
very crowdsourced and then I made that
into a website so figuring out like what
technology you can use that you already
know so if you cannot code you can use a
spreadsheet if you cannot um use a
spreadsheet like whatever you can always
use a for example a website generator
like weeks or something or Squarespace
right like you don't need to code to
build a startup all you need is a idea
for a product um build something like a
landing page or something um put a
stripe button on there and then make it
um and if you can code use the language
that you already you know and start
coding with that and see how far you can
get you can always rewrite the code
later like the tax stack is not actually
it's not the most important of a
business when you're starting out a
business the important thing is that you
validate that there's a market that
there's a product that people want to
pay for um so use whatever you can use
and if you canot code use you know
spreadsheets landing page generators
whatever yeah and the crowdsourcing
element is
fascinating uh it's cool it's cool when
a lot of people start using it you get
to learn so fast yeah uh like i' I've
actually did the spread sheeet thing you
share a spreadsheet
publicly and I made it editable yeah
interesting things start happening yeah
I did it for like a a workout thing cuz
I was doing a large amount of push-ups
and pull-ups every day yeah I remember
this man yeah and like and and IDE
Google Sheets is pretty Limited in that
everything's allowed so people could
just write anything in any and they can
create new uh sheets new tabs and he
just
exploded and uh one of the things that I
really enjoyed is there's very few
trolls um because actually other people
would delete the trolls there would be
like this weird war of like of they they
want like to protect the thing it's an
immune system that's inherent to the
thing it becomes a society you know in a
spreadsheet and then there's the out
Outcast who go to the bottom of the
spreadsheet and they would try to had
messages and they like I don't want to
be with the cool kids up at the top of
the spreadsheet so I'm going the bottom
yes it's fast I mean but that kind of
crowdsourcing element is really powerful
and if you can create a product that use
that as a to his benefit that's that's
really nice like any kind of voting
system any kind of rating system for A
and B testing is really really really
fascinating so anyway so NAD list is
great I would I would love for you to
talk about that but one sort of way to
talk about it is
uh through you building uh Hood Maps
yeah so you've you did an awesome thing
which is document yourself building the
thing and doing so in just a handful of
days like three four five days so people
should je definitely check out the video
in the in the blog post um can you can
you explain what Hood Maps is and what
this whole like this process was so I
was traveling and I was still trying to
find like problems right and I would go
I would I would discover that like
everybody's experience of a city is
different because they stay in different
areas yeah so I'm from Amsterdam and
when I grew up uh in Amsterdam or didn't
grew up but I lived there University I
knew that Center is like in Europe the
centers are always tourist areas so
they're super busy they're not very
authentic the cult they're not really
Dutch culture it's Amsterdam tourist
culture you know so when people would
travel to amam would say don't go to the
center go to you know Southeast um of
the center the yordan or the pipe or
something more hipster areas like a
little more authentic culture of
Amsterdam that's where I would live you
know and where I would go um and I
thought this could be like a app where
you can have like a Google Maps and you
put colors over it you have like areas
that are like color coded like red is
tourist green is Rich you know green
money yellow is hipster you can figure
out where you need to go in a city when
you travel because I was traveling a lot
I wanted to go to the cool spots so just
use color color yeah yeah and I would
use a canvas so I thought okay what do I
need I need to did you know that you
would be using a canvas no I didn't know
it was possible cuz I didn't no some
this is the cool this is the cool thing
people should really check out this how
it started because like you honestly
capture so beautifully the The Humbling
aspects of the embarrassing aspects of
like not knowing what to do it's like
how do I how do I do this and you like
document yourself yeah you're right dude
I feel embarrassed about
myself oh really yeah it's called being
alive nice um so you're like you don't
know anything about so canvas is a way
is HTM yes HTML
five thing that allows you to draw
shapes draw images just draw pixels
essentially so yeah and that's there was
special back then because before you
could only have like elements right so
you want to draw a pixel use a convos
and I knew I needed to draw pixels
because I need to draw these colors and
I thought like okay I'll get like a
Google Maps iframe embed and then I'll
put a div on top of it with the colors
and I'll do like opacity 50 you know so
it kind of shows um so I did that with
convos and then I started drawing um and
then I felt like obviously other people
need to edit this cuz I cannot draw all
these things myself so I crowdsourced it
again and I uh you would draw on the map
and then it would send the pixel data to
the server it would put it in the
database and then I would have a robot
running like a Cron job MH which every
week would calculate or every day would
calculate like okay so mm Center there's
like six people say it's tourist this
part of the center but two people say
it's like hipster okay so the tourist
part wins right it's just an array so so
find the most common value in a little
pixel area on a map so so that so most
people say it's tourist it's tourist and
it becomes redh and I would do that for
you know older GPS Corners in the world
can we just clarify do you have to be as
a human that's contributing to this do
you have to be in that location to make
the label or no people just type in
cities and go like go berserk and start
drawing everywhere would they draw
shapes or would they draw pixels man
they drew that crazy stuff like
offensive symbols I cannot mention they
would draw penises I mean that's
that's obviously a guy I would do the
same thing draw penises that's the first
thing when I show up to Mars and there's
no cameras I'm drawing penis on the same
man I do it in the snow you know but the
penises did not become a problem because
I knew that not everybody would draw a
penis and not in the same place so most
people would use it fairly so just if I
had enough crowdsource data so you have
all these pixels on top of each it's
like a layer of pixels and you choose
the most common pixel so yeah it's just
like a bow but in visual format and it
worked and uh we didn't we had enough
data and and and it was like cities that
did really well like Los Angeles a lot
of people started using it uh like most
datas in Los Angeles because uh Los
Angeles is has defined neighborhoods
yeah and not just in terms of the the
official labels but like what they're
known for yeah what are the do you did
you provide the categories that they
were allowed to use as labels the colors
yeah as colors so it used like I think
you can see there there's like hipster
tourist rich
business so there's always a business
area right and then there's a
residential residential is gray so I
thought those were the most common
things in the city kind of and a little
bit Mimi like it's almost fun to label
it as yeah I mean obviously it's
simplified and but you need to simplify
this stuff you know you don't want to
have too many categories and it's
essentially just like like using a you
know paintbrush where you you select the
color in the bottom you select the
category and you start drawing there's
no instruction there's no manual um and
then I also added tagging so people
could like write something on a specific
location so don't go here or like here's
like um nice cafes and stuff and man the
memes that came from that and I also
added up voting so that the tags could
be upvoted so the memes that came from
that is like amazing like people in Los
Angeles would write crazy stuff it would
go viral in all these cities you can
allow allow your location and it will
probably send you to Austin okay so
we're
looking uh oh boy uh drunk hipster
uh air bro and Bros air bro BR hipster
girls who do cocaine I saw a guy in a
fish costume get beaten up here yep that
seems also ACC overpriced and
underwhelming uh let me see let me make
sure this is accurate uh let's
see 36th for people who know Austin know
that that's
important to label six street is uh
famous in Austin dirty six drunk Fat
Boys accurate drunk Fat Bros continued
on six very well West Sixth drunk douche
Bros go from frat to douche douche I
mean it's very accurate so
far uh they only let hot people live
here
that's I think that might be accurate uh
it's like the
district exercise freaks on the river
yeah that's true dog Runners accurate
saw a guy in the fish costume get beat
up here I want to know the story like so
that's that's all user contributed yeah
and that's like stuff I couldn't come up
with it because I don't know Austin I
don't know the memes here in the
subcultures and then me as a USIC can
upload or downlo this so this is
completely Crown cuz of RIT you know up
down vote took it from there hey that's
really really really powerful single
people dogs accurate at which point did
it go from colors to the actually
showing the text I think I added the
text like a week a week after and uh so
here's like the pixels so that's really
cool the pixels how do you go from that
that's a huge amount of data so there's
yeah uh we're now looking at an image
where it's just a sea of pixels that
call of different colors in in a city so
how do you combine that to be a thing
that actually makes some sense I think
here the problem was that you have this
data but it's like it's not locked to
one location yeah so I had to normalize
it so when you click when you draw on a
map it will show you the specific pixel
location and you can convert the pixel
location to a GPS coordinate right like
latitude longitudes but the number will
have a lot of commas or a lot of
decimals right because it's very
specific like it's like this specific
part of the table so what you want to do
is you want to take that pixel and you
want to normalize it by removing like
decimals um which I discovered so that
you you're talking about this
neighborhood this or this street right
so that's what I did I just took the
decimals off and then I saved it like
this and then it starts um going to like
a grid and then you have like a grid of
data you get like a pixel map kind of
and then you said it looks kind of ugly
so then you smooth it yeah I started
adding blurring and stuff I think now
it's it's not smooth again because I
liked it better people like the pixel
look kind of yeah a lot of people use it
and it keeps going viral and every time
my my maps Bill uh like map box I had to
stop using first used Google Maps it
went viral and Google Maps it was out of
credits so I and I had to so funny
during when I launched it went viral um
Google Maps the map didn't load anymore
it says over the limit you need to
contact Enterprise sales and I'm like I
but I need now like a map so and I don't
want to contact Enterprise sales I don't
want to go on a call schedule with some
calendar so I switched to mapbox and
then had mapbox for years and then it
went viral and I had a bill of $20,000
was like last year um so they helped me
with the bill they said you know you can
pay less and then I now switch to like a
open source kind of um map platform so
it's very expensive project and it never
made any dollar money but it's very fun
but it's very expensive what do you
learn from that so like from that
experience cuz when you leverage
somebody else's through the API yeah I
mean I don't think a map hosting service
should cost this much you know but uh I
could host it myself but that would be I
don't know how to do that you know but I
could do that yes it's super complicated
I think that the thing is more about
like you can't make money with this
project I tried to do many things to
make money with it and it's it's uh it
hasn't worked you talked about like
possibly doing advertisements on it or
some somehow or people sponsoring it
yeah well it's really surprising to me
that people don't want to advertise on
it I think map apps are very hard to
like monetize like Google Maps also
doesn't really make money like sometimes
you see these ads but I don't think
there's a lot of money there um you
could put like a banner ad but it's kind
of ugly and the project is kind of like
it's kind of cool so it's it's kind of
fun to like subsidize it it's kind of a
little bit part of nomad list like I put
it on Nomad list in the cities as well
um but I also realized like you don't
need to monetize everything like some
projects are just cool and you know it's
like it's cool to have Hood Maps exist I
I I want this to exist right yeah
there's a bunch of stuff you've created
that I'm just glad exists in this world
that's true and it's a whole another
puzzle and I'm surprised to figure out
how to make money off of it I'm
surprised Maps don't make money but
you're right it's it's hard it's hard to
make money cuz there's there's a lot of
compute required to actually bring it to
life also where do you put the ad right
like if you have a website you can put
like a ad box or you can do like a
product placement or something but
you're talking about a map app that
where 90% of the interface is a map so
what are you going to do you're going to
like like it's hard to figure out where
is this yeah and people don't want to
pay for it no exactly because if you
make people pay for it you lose 99% of
the user base and you lose the
crowdsource data so it's not fun anymore
it stops being accurate right so you
kind of they pay for it by crowdsourcing
the data but then yeah it's fine you
know it doesn't make money but it's it's
cool but that said NAD list makes money
yeah so what was the story behind Nomad
list so Nomad list started because uh I
was in Chang maai in Thailand which is
now like the second City here and I was
you know working on my laptop um I met
like other NS there and I was like okay
this seems like a cool thing to do like
work on your laptop in a different
country kind of travel around uh but
back then the internet everywhere was
very slow so the internet was fast in
for example Holland or United States but
in a lot of parts in in you know South
America or Asia was very slow like 0.5
megabits so you you couldn't watch a
Youtube video um Thailand weirdly had
like quite fast internet but I wanted to
find like other cities where I could go
to like work on my laptop whatever and
travel and but we needed like fast
internet so I was like let's you know
crowdsource this information uh with a
spreadsheet and I also also needed to
know the cost of living cuz I didn't
have a lot of money I had $500 a month
so I had to find a place where like the
rent was like you know $200 per month or
something where I had you know some
money uh that I could actually rent
something and um and there was NAD list
and it still runs now I think it's now
almost 10 years so just to describe how
it works like I'm looking at Chang ma
here there's a total score it's rank
number two yeah that's like a number
score 4.82 uh like by members but it's
uh it's looking at the internet in this
case it's fast yeah fun temperature
humidity air quality safety food safety
uh crime racism or lack of crime lack of
racism educational level power grid
vulnerability to climate change income
level it's a little much you know
English speak it's awesome it's awesome
walkability keep adding stuff cuz for
certain groups of people certain things
really matter and this is really cool
happiness I'd love to ask about that not
life free Wii by
AC uh female friendly freedom of speech
AP and not so good in tit you know
values derived from National statistics
my yeah I like how that one has I need
to do that because the the data sets are
usually National they're not on City
level right so I don't know about the
freedom of speech between Bangkok or
changai I know in Thailand I mean this
is really fascinating so this is for
City yeah it's basically raiding all the
different things that matter to you in
Internet and this is all crowdsourced
well so it started crowdsourced but then
um I realized that you can download more
accurate data sets from like public
Source like World Bank they have a lot
of public data sets United Nations and
you can download a lot of data there
which you can you know freely use like I
I started getting FR cross data where
for example people from India they
really love India and they would submit
the best scores for everything in India
and not just like one person but like a
lot of people they would love to pump
India and I'm like I love India too you
know but uh that's not valid data so you
started getting discrepancy in the data
between people where people wear from
and stuff so I I started switching to
data sets and um and now it's mostly
data sets but one thing that's still
crowdsource is so people add where they
are they add their travels to their
profile and I use that data to see which
plac are upcoming and which places are
popular now so about half the ranking
you see here is based on actual digital
NAD who are there you can click on a
city you can click on people and you can
see the people the users that are
actually there and it's like 30,000 or
40,000 members so these people are in
Austin now and 1,800 remote work is in
Austin now now of which eight plus
members checked in U members who will be
here soon and go yeah so we have meetups
so people organize their own meetups and
we have about I think like 30 30 per
month so it's like one Meetup a day and
I don't do anything they organize
themselves so I just it's a whole Black
Box it just runs and I don't do a lot on
it it pulls data from everywhere and it
just
works cons of Austin is too expensive
very sweaty and humid now difficult to
make friends difficult to make friends
interesting right I didn't know that
difficult to make friends Austin but
this all crowd but mostly it's Pros uh
safe fast internet I don't understand
why it says not safe for women to check
the data set it feels safe the problem
with a lot of places like United States
is that it depends per area right so if
you get like City level data or Nation
level data it's like Brazil's worst
because the the range in like safe and
wealthy and and not safe is like huge so
you can't say many things about Brazil
so once they actually show up to the
city how do you figure out what uh what
area like where to get fast internet for
example like for me is all it's
consistently a struggle to figure out
like hotels with fast Wi-Fi for example
like a place okay okay I show up to a
city there's a lot of fascinating
puzzles and I haven't figured out a way
to actually solve this puzzle when I
show up to City figuring out where I can
get fast internet
connection and uh for podcasting
purposes where I can find a place with a
table that's quiet right that's not easy
construction sounds all kinds of sounds
you have to learn about all the sources
of sounds in the world and also like the
the quality of the room because the more
um the the emptier of the room and like
if it's just walls without any curtains
or any of this kind of stuff then
there's
uh echo in the room anyway but you you
figure out that a lot of hotels don't
have tables they don't have like normal
this weird desk right yeah they have
it's not a center table yep and if you
want to get a nicer hotel where it's
more spacious and so on they usually
have these like Boutique like fancy
looking like modernist annoy tables that
don't it's too Desy it's too design
they're not really real tables why don't
you get Ikea buy Ikea yeah before you
arrive you order an Ikea like n this
they get desks I feel like you should be
able to show up to a place and have have
the desk like it's not unless you stay
there for a long time just the entire
assembly all that Airbnb is so
unreliable it's the the the range and
quality that you get is is is
huge hotels have a lot of problems pros
and cons like hotels have the problem
that the pictures somehow never have
good representative pictures of what's
actually going to be in the room and
that's a problem like and you fake
photos man if I could have the kind of
data you have on NAD list for hotels
yeah man I would and I feel like you can
make a lot of money on that too yeah the
booking fees affiliate right I thought
about this idea because we have the same
problem like I go to hotels and there's
specific ones that are very good and I
know now the chains and stuff and but
even even if you go some chains are very
bad in a specific City and very good in
other cities and each individual hotel
has a lot of kinds of rooms yeah like
you you some are more expensive some are
cheaper and so on but you can get the
details
of what's in the room like what's the
actual layout of the room what is the
view of the rooman I feel like as a
hotel you can win a lot so first you
create a service that allows you to have
like high resolution data about a hotel
then one hotel sign signs up for that I
would 100% use that website to look for
a hotel instead of the crappy
Alternatives that don't give any
information and I feel like there'll be
this pressure for all the hotels to join
that site and you can make a shit ton of
money cuz hotels make a lot of money I
think it's true but the problem is with
these hotels like it's it's same with
airline industry why does every Airline
website suck when you try book book a
flights yeah it's like very strange like
why does it have to suck obviously
there's competition here why doesn't the
best website win what's the explanation
of that man I thought about this for
years so I think it's like I have to
book the flight anyway like I know
there's a route that they take and I
need like I need to buy book for example
Qatar airlines and I and I need to get
through this process
so the the the and with a hotel is
similar you need a hotel anyway so so do
you have time to like figure out the
best one not really you kind of just
need to get the place booked and you
know you need to get the flight and
you'll go through the pain of this
process and that's why this process
always sucks so much with hotels and
Airline websites and stuff because they
don't have an incentive to improve it
because generally only for like a super
upper segment of the market I think like
super high luxury it affects the actual
booking right I don't know I think that
that's a good interesting Theory I think
that must be a different Theory my my
theory would would be that great
Engineers like great software Engineers
are not allowed to make changes yeah
basically like there's some kind of
bureaucracy there's way too many
managers there's a lot of
bureaucracy and uh great Engineers show
up they try to work there and they
they're not allowed to really make any
contributions and then they leave and so
you have a lot of mediocre software
Engineers they're not really interested
in improving any of the thing and like
literally they would like to improve the
stuff but the
bureaucracy um of the place plus all the
bosses is all the high up people are not
technical people probably they don't
know much about web web dev they don't
know much about programming so they just
don't give any respect like you have to
give the freedom and the respect to
Great Engineers as they try to do great
things that feels like an explanation
like if you were a great programmer
would you want to work at America
Airlines or no no I'm I'm torn on that
cuz I I actually as somebody lost
program would love to work at America
Airlines so I can make the thing better
yeah but for I would I would work there
just to fix it for myself you know yeah
for yourself and then you just know how
much suffering you alleviated how
much just oh you imagine all the
thousands maybe millions of people that
go to that website and have to click
like a million times it often doesn't
work it's clunky all that kind of stuff
you you're making their life just so
much better yeah but there there must be
an explanation has to do with managers
and bureaucracies like I don't I think
it's money do you know
booking.com sure so it's the boooking
it's the biggest boooking website in the
world it's dutch actually and um they
have teams CU my friend worked there
they have teams for a specific part of
the website like a 10 by 10 pixels area
where they they run tests on this so
they run tests like and they're famous
for this stuff like oh there's only one
room left right with this red letter
it's like one room left book now you
know and they got a fine from the
European Union about this kind of
interesting so they have all these teams
and they run the test for 24 hours they
go to sleep they wake up next day they
come to the office and they see okay
this performed better this website has
become a monster but it's the most
Revenue generating hotel booking website
in the world is number one so that shows
that it's not about like user experience
it's about like I don't know about
making more money and you know not every
company but you know if they if if
they're optimizing it's a public company
if they're optimizing for money but you
can optimize for money by disrupting
like making it way better yeah but it's
always startups they start with
disrupting like booking also started
startup 1997 and then they become like
the old shit again like you know Uber
now starts to become like a taxi again
right it was very good in the beginning
now it's kind of like taxis now in many
places are better they're nicer than
Ubers right so it's like the circle I
think some of it is also just it's hard
to have Ultra competent Engineers yeah
like stripe seems like a trivial thing
but it it's hard to pull off like why
was it so hard for Amazon to have buy
with one click which I think is a genius
idea make buying easier
like make it as as frictional as as
possible just click a button once and
you bought the thing yeah as opposed to
most of the web was a lot of clicking
and it often doesn't work like with the
airlines remember the forms would delete
you could CLI next submit and would 404
or something or your internet would go
down your modem yeah man and I would
have an existential crisis like the
frustration would take over my whole
body and I just wanted to quit life for
a brief moment there yeah yeah I'm so
happy to form stays in Google Chrome now
when something goes wrong but that's so
Google somebody did Google improv
Society with that right yeah and one of
the challenges of Google is to have the
freedom to do that they don't anymore
there's a bunch of bureaucracy yeah go
there's so many brilliant brilliant
people there but it just moves slowly
yeah I wonder why that is maybe that's
the natural way of a company but you
have people like Elon who rolls in and
just fir most most of the folks and
always oper like push the company to
operate as a startup even when it's
already big yeah but I mean Apple does
this I like I started in business school
Apple does competing product teams that
operate as startups so three to five
people they make something they have
multiple teams who make the same thing
the best team wins so you need to I
think you need to emulate like a a free
market inside a company to make it
entrepreneurial you know yeah and you
need entrepreneurial mentality in a
company to to come up with new ideas and
do it better so one of the things you do
really really well is learn a new thing
like you're trying to you have an idea
you try to build it and then you learn
everything you need to in order to build
it you have your current skills but you
need learn just the minimal amount of
stuff so you're a good person to ask
like what how do you
learn how do how do you learn quickly
and effectively in just the stuff you
need you did um just by way of example
you did a 30 days learning session on 3D
yeah where you documented yourself
giving yourself only 30 days to learn
everything you can about yeah I tried to
learn virtual reality CU I was like this
was like same as AI it came up Suddenly
like 2016 2017 with I think HTC VI this
big VR glasses before Apple Vision Pro
and I was like oh this is going to be
big so I need to learn this so I I know
I know nothing about 3D I installed like
um I think unity and like blender and
stuff and I started learning all this
stuff
um because I thought this was like a new
you know n technology that was going to
be big and if I had to skill for it uh I
could use this to build stuff and so I
think with learning for me it's like it
I think learning is so funny because
people always ask me like how how do I
how do you learn to code like should I
learn to code and I'm like I don't know
like I'm Every Day I'm learning it's
kind of cliche but every day I'm
learning new stuff so every day I'm
searching on Google or asking out cat
gbt how to do this thing how to do this
thing every day I'm getting better at my
skill so you never stop learning so the
whole concept of like how do you learn
well you never end so where do you want
to be do you want to know a little bit
do do you want to know a lot do you want
to do it for your whole life or so I
think taking action is the best step to
learn so making things like you know
nothing just start making things okay so
like how to make a website search how to
make a website or nowadays you ask jbt
how do I make a website where do I start
it generates codes for you right copy
the code put it in a file save it open
it in Google Chrome or whatever you have
a website and then you start tweaking
with it and you start okay how do I add
a button how do I add AI features right
like nowadays so it's like by taking
action you can learn stuffff much faster
than reading books or actually I'm
curious let me ask perplexity how do I
make a
website I'm just curious what it would
say I hope it goes with like really
basic vanilla Solutions Define your
website's purpose choose a domain name
select a web hosting provider choose a
website or Builder or CMS website build
platform like wi for Squarespace is what
I said yeah landing page
what what do I how do I say if I want to
programming it program it myself design
your website create essential Pages yeah
even tells you to launch it right like
start your website cool well I mean you
could do that yeah but this is literally
it like it's this is if you want to make
a this is the basic like Google
analytics but you can't make Nomad list
with this way so with Wix like with ah
no you can you can get pretty far I
think these website Builders are pretty
Advanced like all you need is a grid of
images right that are clickable that
open like another page yeah you can can
get quite far how do I learn to
program choose a programming language to
start with yeah free code Camp is
good work through a resources
systematically practice coing regularly
for 30 60 minutes a day consistency key
join programming communities like
reddits
yeah yeah it's pretty it's pretty good
yeah it's pretty good so I think it's
it's a very good starting ground because
imagine you know nothing and you want to
make a website you want to make a
startup this is like that's why the man
the power of AI for education is going
to be insane like people anywhere can
can ask this question and start building
stuff yeah clarifies it for sure and
just start building like keep build
build like actually apply the thing
whether it's AI or uh any of the
programming for web development yeah
just have a project in mind which I love
the idea of like
12 startups in 12 months or
like build a project almost every day
just build a thing yeah and get it to
work and finish it every single day
that's a cool experiment I think that
was the inspiration there was a girl who
did
160 websites in 160 days or something
like lit mini websites yeah and uh and
she learned to go that way so I think
it's good to set yourself challenges you
know like don't you can go to some
coding boot camp but I don't think they
actually work I think it's better to do
like for me outto deduct like
selflearning and setting yourself like
challenges and just getting in but you
need discipline you know you need to
discipline to keep to keep doing it and
coding you know coding is very it's a
steep learning curve to get in it's very
annoying working with computers is very
annoying uh so it can be hard for people
to keep doing it you know yeah that
thing of just keep doing it and don't
quit that urgency that's required to
finish a thing that's why it's really
powerful when you documented this the
creation of hood Maps or the like a
working prototype that there's a just a
constant frustration I guess it's like
how do I do this and then you look it up
and you're like okay you have to
interpret the different options you have
you're like and then just try it and
then and then there's a dopamine Rush of
like o it works cool man it's amazing
and it's I I live streamed it it's on
YouTube and stuff people can watch it
and it's amazing when things work it's
look it's just like amazing that you I
look very not I don't look far ahead so
I only look okay what's the next problem
to solve and then the next problem and
at the end you have a whole app or
website or thing you know but I think
most people look way too far ahead you
know they look it's like this poster
again like you shouldn't you don't know
how hard it's going to be so you should
only look like for the next thing the
next little challenge the next step and
then see where you end up and assume
it's going to be
easy yeah exactly yeah be naive about it
because it's it's you're going to have
very difficult
problems a lot of the big problems won't
be even Tech we'll be like public right
like maybe people don't like your
website like um you will get canceled
for a website for example like a lot of
things can happen what's it like
building in public like you do like
openly where you're just iterating
quickly and you're getting people's
feedback so there there's the power of
the crowdsourcing but there's also the
the negative aspects of people being
able to
criticize so man I think haters are
actually cuz I think a lot of haters
have good points and it takes like
stepping away from the emotion of like
uh ah your website sucks because blah
blah blah and you're like okay just
remove this your website sucks because
it's personal you know what did he say
why did he didn't not like it and you
figure out okay he didn't like it
because the sign up was difficult or
something or it wasn't the data they say
no this data is not accurate or
something right okay I need to improve
the quality of data this hater has a
point think it's dumb to completely
ignore your haters you know and also you
man I think I've been there when I was
like 10 years old or some you're on the
internet you just shouting crazy stuff
that's like most of Twitter you know or
half Twitter so you you have to take it
with grain of salt um yeah you man you
need to grow a very thick skin like on
Twitter on X like people say but I mute
a lot of people like I found out I muted
already 15,000 people recently I checked
so in in 10 years I muted 15,000 people
so that's like like that's one by one
manual 15 yeah oh wow so, 1500 people
per year and I don't like like to block
cuz then they get angry they make a
screenshot and they say ah you block me
so I just mute and it disappear and it's
amazing so you mentioned Reddit So Hood
maps that make it to the front page of
Reddit yeah yeah it did yeah yeah yeah
it did it was amazing and my server
almost went down and I was checking like
Google analytics was like 5,000 people
on the website or something or crazy and
it was a night and was amazing um I man
I think nowadays honestly Tik Tok uh
YouTube Reals Instagram reals a lot of
apps get very big from people T making
Tik Tok videos about it so let's say you
make your own app you can make a video
for yourself like oh I made this app uh
this is how it works blah blah blah um
and this is why I made it for example
and this is why you should use it and if
it's a good video will take off and you
will get man you I got like
$20,000 extra per month or something
from a Tik Tok from one Tik Tok video
like it made a photoi by you or somebody
else by some random guy so there's all
these AI influencers that they write
about they show AI apps and they then
they ask money later like when a V video
goes vir all I can do it do it again and
send me $4,000 something I'm like okay I
did that for example but it works like
Tik Tok is a very big platform for user
uh um acquisition yeah and organic like
the best user acquisition I think is
organic you don't need to buy ads you
probably don't have money when you start
to buy ads so use organic or write a
banger tweet right that's can make an
app take off as well well I mean yeah
fundamentally create cool stuff and have
just a little bit of a following enough
to like for for the cool thing to be
noticed and then it becomes viral if
it's cool enough yeah and you don't need
a lot of followers anymore because that
on on X and a lot of platforms because
Tik Tok X I think Instagram reals also
they have the same algorithm now it's
not about followers anymore it's about
they test your content on a small subset
like 300 people if they like it it will
gets tested to thousand people and on
and on so if the thing is good it will
rise anyway it doesn't matter if you
have million followers or a th000
followers or 100 what's your philosophy
of monetizing how to make money from the
thing you build yeah so a lot of stter
they do like free users so you could
sign up and can use the app for free
which is um it never worked for me well
because I I think free users generally
don't convert and I think if you have VC
funding it makes sense to get free users
because you can spend your funding on
ads and you can get like millions of
people com in predictably how much they
convert and give them like a free trial
whatever and then they sign up but you
need to have that flow worked out so
well for you to to make it work that you
need like it's very difficult I think
it's best to start and just um start
asking people for money in the beginning
so show your app like what are you doing
on your landing page like make a demo
Whatever video and then if you want to
use it pay me money pay $10 $20 $30 I
would ask more than $10 per month like
Netflix is like $10 per month but
Netflix is a giant company that can you
know they can afford to make it so cheap
relatively cheap if you're individual
like an indie hacker like you are making
your own app you need to make like at
least
$30 or more on a user to make it uh
worthy for you you need to make money
you know and it builds a community of
people that actually really care about
the product also yeah making a community
like making a Discord is very normal now
every AI has a Discord and you have the
developers and the users together in
like a Discord they talk about they ask
for features they build together it's
very normal now and um and you need to
imagine like if you're if you're
starting out getting a thousand users is
quite difficult getting thousand pages
is quite difficult and if you charge
them like $30 you have 30k a month
that's a lot of money that's enough to
like live a good life yeah live a pretty
good life I mean there could be a lot of
cost associated with hosting so that's
another thing I make sure my profit
margets are very high so I try to keep
the cost very low I don't hire people um
I I try to negotiate with like AI
vendors now like can you make it cheaper
you know which is I discovered this you
can just email companies and say can you
can give me discount cuz too expensive
and they say sure 50% I'm like wow very
good and and I didn't know this you can
just ask and especially in like like now
it's kind of recession you can ask
companies like I I need a discount or I
kind of need to like you don't need to
be asshole about it say you know I kind
of need a discount or I need to go maybe
to another company so maybe like a
discount like here and there and it says
sure a lot of them will say yes like 25%
discount 50% discounts because you think
the price on the website is the price of
the API or something it's not like you
know and also you're a public facing
person oh that helps also and there's
love and Good Vibes that you put out
into the world like you're actually
legitimately trying to build cool stuff
so a lot of companies probably want to
associate with you because you're trying
to do yeah it's like secret heck but I
think even without good person it
depends how much discount they will give
you know they'll maybe give more but you
know that's why you should shit post on
Twitter so you get you know discounts
maybe yeah yeah um but and also the when
it's
crowdsourced I mean paying does prevent
spam or help prevent spam also yeah yeah
it gives you high quality users and free
users are s but they're horrible like
it's just like millions of people
especially if AI startups you get a lot
of abuse so you get millions of people
from anywhere just abusing your app just
just hacking it and whatever like
there's something on the Internet you
mentioned like forand discovered Hood
Maps yeah but I love fortune they I
don't love fortune but you know I mean
like they're so crazy especially back
then like that's it's kind of funny what
they do you know I actually uh what is
it this new documentary on Netflix
antisocial Network or something like
that that was really was fascinating
just fortun just the you know the spirit
of the thing Fortune Mis understand
Fortune it's so much about freedom and
also like the humor involved in fucking
with the system and fucking with man
it's just anti-stem for fun the the dark
aspect of it is you're having fun you're
doing anti-stem stuff but like the Nazis
always show up and it's somehow bad shit
started happening it starts drifting
somehow yeah like school shootings and
stuff so it's a very difficult topic but
I I do know it's especially early on I
think 2010 I would go to for for fun and
they would post like crazy offensive
stuff and this was just to scare off
people so we' show to other people say
hey do you know this internet website
for just check it out yeah and it' be
dude what the fuck I'm like no no you
don't understand that's to scare you
away but actually when you go through a
scroll there's like deep conversations
yes and there would already be this was
like a Normy filter like to stop yeah so
kind of cool but yeah goes dark it goes
dark and if you have those people show
up they'll for the fun of it do a bunch
of racist things and all that kind of
stuff you're saying but everything's I
think it was never man I'm not a
fortunate but like I it was always about
provoking it's just provocateur you know
but the the provoking in the case of
hood Maps or something like this can can
damage
the uh good thing like you know a a
little poison in a town is always good
it's like the the Tom weights thing but
you don't want too much otherwise it it
destroys the town it destroys the thing
they're kind of like pen testers you
know like penetration testers hackers
yeah they just test your app for you and
then you add some stuff like I add like
a I add like a NSFW W list they would
say like bad words so when they would
write like a bad word they would get
forwarded to YouTube which was like a
video
was like a a very relaxing video that's
like kind of ASMR with like glowing
jelly streaming like this to relax them
you know or cheese melting on the toes
to chill them out I like it like but
actually a lot of stuff I didn't realize
how much originated in forchan in terms
of memes Rick Roll I didn't understand I
didn't know that Rick Roll originated in
forchan like there's so many memes like
most of the memes that you think the
word role I think comes from forun like
not the word role but like in this case
in a mem used like you would get like
roll doubles cuz every it was like post
IDs on fortun so they were R they were
kind of like random so if I get doubles
like this happens or something so You'
get like two two anyway it's like a
betting Market kind of on these doubles
on these post IDs this so much funny
stuff yeah I mean that's internet that's
purest but yeah again the dark stuff
kind of seeps in yeah and you you it's
nice to keep the dark stuff to like some
low amount it's nice to have a bit of
noise of the darkness but not too much
yeah and but again like you have to pay
attention to that with um I mean I guess
spam in general you have to fight that
with NAD list how do you fight spam man
I use gp4 now it's amazing so so I have
like um user input I have reviews people
can review cities and they don't need to
actually sign up it's Anonymous reviews
and they write like whole books about
like cities and what's good and bad so
uh I run it through gp4 now and I ask
like is this a you know is this a good
review like is it offensive is it racist
or some stuff and and it sends me a
message on telegram when it rejects
reviews and I check it and it's man it's
so on point a yes and it's so accurate
it understands double meanings um I have
gb4 running on the on the on the chat
Community it's a chat community of
10,000 people and they're chatting and
they start fighting with each other um
and I used to have uh human moderators
was very good but they would start
fighting the human moderator like this
guy's biased or something I have GPT 4
and it's it's it's really really really
really good it understands humor it
understands like like you could say
something bad but it's kind of like a
joke and it's kind of not like offensive
so much so it shouldn't be deleted right
understands that you know it's I would
love to have a gbt 4 based filter of
like of different kinds of for like X
yeah I fought this week like I tweeted
like a fact check like you can click
fact check and then gp4 look gp4 not
always right about stuff right but it
can give you a general fact check on a
tweet like usually what I do now when I
write something like Difficult about
economics or something or AI I put in
gp4 I say can you fact check it because
I might have said something stupid and
the stupid stuff always gets taken out
by the reply is like oh you said this
wrong and and then the whole tweet kind
of doesn't make sense anymore so I asked
gbt for to fact check a lot of stuff so
fact check is a tough one yeah but it
would be interesting to sort of
um rate the thing based on how well
thought out it is and how well argued it
is yeah that that seems more doable that
seems like more doable like it seems
like a GPT thing because that that's
less about the truth and it's more about
the rigor of the thing exactly and you
can ask that you can ask in the prompt
like I don't know like for example do
you think create like a ranking score of
X Twitter replies where I should this
post be if we rank on like I don't know
Integrity reality like fundamental
deepness or something inness um and it
would give you that with a pretty good
score probably I mean Elon can do this
with groc right he can start doing using
that to to check replies cuz the reply
section is like chaos you know and
actually the ranking of the replies is
not doesn't make any sense doesn't make
sense no and I I would like to sort in
different kinds of ways yeah and you get
too many replies now if you have a lot
of followers I get too many replies I
don't see everything and I I a lot of
stuff I just miss and I don't I want to
see the good stuff and also the
notifications or whatever it's just
complete chaos yeah it'd be nice to be
able to filter that in interesting ways
sort in interesting
ways cuz like I feel like I miss a lot
and I what's surfaced for me are just
like a random comment by a person with
no followers that's positive or negative
it's like okay if it's a very good
comment it should happen but it should
probably look a little bit more like do
these people have followers because
they're probably more engaged in the
platform right oh no if it's I don't
even care about how many followers if
you're ranking by the quality of the
comment great yeah but not just like
randomly like chronological just a sea
of comments yeah yeah yeah it does makes
sense yeah uh X could be very improved
of that I think one thing you you spouse
a lot which I love is the automation
step so like once you have a Thing Once
you have an idea and you build it and it
actually starts making money and it's
making people happy there's a community
of people using
it you want to take the autom step of
automating the things you have to do as
little work as possible for it to keep
running indefinitely can you like
explain your philosophy there what do
you mean by automate yeah so the general
theory of stter would be that when when
it starts like you start making money
you start hiring people to do stuff
right do stuff that you like marketing
for example do stuff that you would do
in the beginning yourself um and
whatever Community Management and
organizing meetups for nist for example
that would be a job for example and I
thought like uh I don't the money for
that and I I don't really want to run
like a big company with a lot of people
because there's a lot of work managing
these people so I've always tried to
like automate these things as much as
possible and um and this can literally
be like for this it's literally like a
it's not a different other stars was
like a web page where you can organize
your own Meetup set a set a schedule a
date whatever you can see how many
Nomads will be there at that date so you
know there will be actually enough
Nomads to meet up right and then um when
it's done it sends a tweet out on the
nist account there's a Meetup here it
sends a direct message to everybody in
the city who are there who are going to
be there and then people show up on a
bar and there's a Meetup and that's
fully automated and for me it's like
it's not it's so obvious to make this
automatic why would you why would you
have somebody organize this like um it
makes more sense to automate it and this
with most of my things like I figure out
like how to do it with code and I think
especially now with AI like you can
automate so much more stuff than before
because AI understands things so well
like before I would use if statements
right now you ask GPT you put something
in GPT for and in the API and it sends
back like this is good this is bad yeah
so you basically can now even uh
automate sort of subjective type of
things this is the difference now and
that's very recent right but it's still
difficult to I mean that step of
automation is difficult
to figure out how to is you're basically
delegating everything to code and it's
not trivial to take that step for a lot
of people
So when you say automate are you are you
talking about like Crown jobs Yes Man a
lot of crown jobs a lot of crown jobs
it's like uh I literally I log into the
server and I do like pseudo Chron tab d
e and then I go into the editor and I
write like hourly and then I write
PHP uh you know do this thing. PHP and
that's a script and that script does a
thing and it does it then hourly that's
it and that's how all my websites work
do you have a thing where it like emails
emils you or something like this or
email somebody managing the thing if
something goes wrong I have these web
pages I make they're called like health
checks so like Health check. PHP and
then it has like emojis like a has like
a green check mark if it's good and a
red one if it's bad and then it does
like database curious for example like
what's the internet speed in for example
um Amsterdam MH okay it's a number it's
like 27 point megabit so it's accurate
number okay check good and it goes to
the next and it goes on all the data
points did people sign up in the last 24
hours it's important because maybe the
sign up broke okay check somebody sign
up then I have um uptime robot.com which
is like for uptime but it can also check
keywords it checks for an emoji which is
like the Red X which is if something is
bad and so it opens that health check
page every minute to check if something
is bad then if it's bad it sends a
message to me on telegram saying hey
what's up uh it doesn't say hey what's
up it sends me like alert like this
thing is down and then I check so within
a minute of something breaking I know it
and then I can open my laptop and fix it
yeah but the good thing is like the last
few years things don't break anymore and
like definitely 10 years ago when I
started everything was breaking all the
time and now it's like almost it's last
week was like 100. z% up time and these
health checks are part of the uptime
percentage so it's like everything works
yeah actually making me realize I should
uh I should have a page for myself like
one page that has all the health checks
just so I can go to didn't see all the
green check marks just it feels good to
look as you know it just be like okay
yeah all right we're okay everything's
okay yeah and like you can see like when
was the last time something wasn't okay
and it'll say like never or like meaning
like you've you've you've you've checked
since you've last cared to check it was
all been okay for sure it used to send
me the the good health checks like yeah
you know this all works it all works but
it's been so often and I'm like this
feels so good but then I'm like okay OB
is not going to we need to hide the good
ones and show only the bad ones and now
that's the case I need to integrate
everything into one place I automate
like everything yeah have also just a
large uh set of cron jobs a lot of the
publication this podcast is has done all
everything is just on automatically it's
all clipped up all the all all this kind
of stuff yeah but it would be nice to
automate even more like a translation
all this kind of stuff would be nice to
automate yeah every JavaScript every PHP
error gets sent to my telegram as well
so every user whatever user it is
doesn't have to be page user if they run
into an error um the JavaScript sends
the JavaScript error to the server and
then it sends to my telegram from all my
websites so you get like a message so I
get like a uncut variable error whatever
blah blah blah and then I'm like okay
interesting and then I go check it out
and that's like a way to get to zero
errors because you get flooded with
errors in the beginning and now it's
like nothing
almost so that's really cool but mat
that's really cool but this is the same
stuff people they they pay like very big
size companies like New Relic for right
like to manage the stuff um so you can
do that too you can use off the-shelf I
like to build myself it's easier yeah
it's nice it's nice to do that kind of
automation I'm starting to think about
like what are the things in my life I'm
doing myself that could be
automated uh in the ask your gbt you
know like give your daily your day and
then ask it what part you to automate
well one of the things I I would love to
automate more is my consumption and
social media yeah both the the output
and the input man that's very I think
there's some startups that do that like
they they summarize the cool shit
happening on Twitter you know like with
AI I think the guy called s wyx or
something he does like a newsletter it's
completely AI generated we have the cool
the cool new stuff in AI yeah I mean I
would love to do that but also like
across Instagram Facebook LinkedIn all
this kind of stuff just like okay can I
can you summarize the internet for me
for today summarize internet.com yeah
cuz I I feel like it pulls in way too
much uh time but also like I don't like
the effect it has some days on my psyche
because like haters or or just general
content like no no just general like for
example like Tik Tok is a good example
of that for me I sometimes just feel
Dumber after I use Tik Tok I just feel
like I don't use it anymore empty
somehow and I'm like
uninspired yeah it's funny in the moment
I'm like ah look at that cat doing a
funny thing and then you're like oh look
at that person dancing in a funny way to
that music is and then you're like 10
minutes later you're like I feel way
dumber and I don't really want to do
much for the rest of the day my
girlfriend sat she saw me like watching
some dumb video and she's like dude your
face looks so dumb as well your whole
face starts going like oh interesting
you know
so I mean with social media uh with uh
with X sometimes for me too is I think
I'm probably naturally gravitating
towards the drama yeah aren't we all
yeah so there following AI people
especially AI people that only post
technical content has been really good
cuz then I just look at them and I and
then I go down rabbit holes of like
learning new papers that have been
published or uh good repos or or um just
any kind of cool demonstration of stuff
and the the kind of things that they
retweet and that's the rabbit hole I go
and I'm learning and I'm inspired all
that kind of stuff
it's been tough it's been tough to
control it's difficult you need to like
manage your your your platforms you know
I have a mute word list as well so I
mute like politics stuff because I don't
really want it on my feet and I think
I've muted so much that now my feet is
good you know I see like interesting
stuff and but the fact that you need to
modify you need to like mod your app
your social media platform just to
function and not be toxic for you for
your mental health right that's like a
problem like it should be doing that for
you it's some level of automation
I that that would be interesting I wish
I could access X and Instagram through
API easier you need to spend $42,000 a
month which my friends do yeah you can
do no but still even if you do that that
you're not getting I mean there's
limitations that don't make it easy to
do like yeah automate because they the
thing that they're trying to limit like
abuse or for you to steal all the data
from the app to then train an llm or
something like this but if I just want
to like figure out ways to automate my
inter action with the X system or with
with Instagram they they don't make that
easy but I would love to sort of
automate that and explore different ways
to how to leverage llms to control the
content I consume and and maybe publish
that maybe they themselves can see how
that could be used to improve their
system so but there's not
enough uh access you can screen cap your
phone right can be an app that watches
your screen with you you could yeah but
I don't really know like what it would
do like maybe it can hide stuff before
you see it you know like I I have Chrome
extensions I I write a lot of Chrome
extensions that hide parts of different
pages and so on like for example for my
own on my main computer I hide all views
and likes and all that on on YouTube
content that I create so that you it
doesn't yeah so you don't pay attention
to it um I also hide Parts there I have
a mode for X where I hide most of
everything so like there's no it's same
with YouTube the same I have this
extension like uh well I wrote my own
because it's easier because it keeps
changing it's like it's it's not easy to
keep it dynamically changing but they're
really good at like getting you to be
distracted and like starting related
accounts related post I'm like I don't
want related and like 10 minutes later
you're like or something that's trending
I have a weird amount of friends
addicted to YouTube and I'm not addicted
I think because my attention span is too
short for YouTube but uh but I I have
this extension to like YouTube on hook
which like it hides all the related
stuff I can just see the video mhm and
it's amazing and uh but sometimes I need
to like like I I need to search a video
how to how to do something and then I go
to YouTube and I had these YouTube
shorts these YouTube shorts are like
they're like algorithmically designed to
just make you tap them and like I tap
and and then I'm like five minutes later
with his face like and you're you're
just stuck and he's like what happened I
was gonna open I was going to play like
the coffee mix you know like the music
mix for drinking coffee together like in
the morning like jazz I didn't want to
go to shorts
so it's it's very uh it's very
difficult I love how we're actually
highlighting all kinds of interesting
problems that all could be solved with a
start up okay so what what about the
exit when and how to exit man you
shouldn't ask me because I never sold my
company and you've never all the
successful stuff you've done you've
never sold it yeah it's kind of sad
right like I I've been in so I've been
in in a lot of acquisition like deals
and stuff and I learn a lot about
Finance people as as well there like
manipulation and do diligence and then
changing the valuation like people
change the valuation after uh so they
they a lot of people string you on to
acquire you and then it takes like six
months it's like classic it takes six to
12 months they want to see everything
they want to see the the your stripe and
your code and whatever and then um in
the end they'll they'll change the price
to lower because you're already so
invested so it's like a negotiation
tactic right I'm like no then I don't
want to sell right and the problem with
my companies is like they make you know
90% profit margin so the multiple they
companies get sold with multiples kind
of multiples of profit or revenue and
often the multiples like three times
three times or four times or five times
revenue or profit so in my case they're
all automated so I might as as well wait
three years and I get the same money as
when I sell and then I can still sell
the same company you know what I mean I
can still sell for three five times so
financially it doesn't really make sense
to sell yeah unless the price high
enough like if the gets to like six or
seven or eight I don't want to wait six
years for the money you know but if you
give me three like three years nothing
like I can wait so I mean the really
valuable stuff about the companies you
created is not just the interface and
the and the crowdsource content but the
people themselves like the user base
yeah but nor list it's a community yeah
so I could see that being extremely
valuable I'm surprised but normally this
is like it's like my baby it's like my
first product I took off and I don't
really know if I want to sell it it's
like something you would nice when you
you know when you're old that you're
still working in this you know it's like
a it has like a mission which is like um
people should travel anywhere and they
can work from anywhere and they can meet
different cultures and that's a good way
to make the world get better if you
learn if you go to China and live in
China you'll learn that they're nice
people and a lot of stuff you hear about
China's propaganda a lot of stuff is
true as well but it's more you know you
learn a lot from traveling and I think
that's why it's like a cool project to
like not sell uh AI projects I have less
emotional feeling with AI projects like
guy mhm which I could sell yeah yeah the
thing you also mentioned is you have to
price in the fact that you're going to
miss yeah the company you cre and
meaning it gives you right there's a
very famous like depression after
started fin a Solar Company like they're
like this was my this was me like who am
I and they immediately start building
another one you know they never can stop
so I think it's it's good to keep
working you know until you die just keep
working on cool stuff and you shouldn't
retire you know I think retirement is
bad probably so you usually build the
stuff solo and mostly work
solo what's the thinking behind that I
think I'm not so good working with other
people not like I'm crazy but like I I
don't trust other people to clarify you
don't trust other people to do a great
job yeah and I don't want to have like
this consensus meeting where we all like
you know you have like a meeting with
three people and then you kind of get
this Compromise result which is very
European like it's very in Holland we
call po where you put people in the room
and you only let them out when they
agree on the compromise right in
politics and I don't think it I think it
it breeds like averageness you know you
get an average idea average company
average
culture um you need to have like a
leader or you need to be solo and just
do it you know do it yourself I think
and I trust some people like now I like
with my best friend Andre I'm making a
new AI startup um but it's because we we
know each other very long and he's one
of the few people I would build
something with and uh but almost never
yeah so what does it take to be
successful when you have more than one
like how do you build together with
Andre how you build together with other
people so he codes uh I shit post on
Twitter literally like I promoted on
Twitter I I we said like product
strategy like I said this should be
better this should be better but I think
you need to have one person coding it he
codes in Ruby so I cannot do Ruby I'm in
PHP so you literally so you have you
ever coded with another person for
prolonged periods of time never in my
life
so uh what what do you think is behind
that I don't know it was always just me
sitting on my laptop like like goting no
like you've never had another developer
who like rolls in and like I've had once
where F I like there's AI developer
Philip I hired him to do the because I I
can't write Python and AI stuff is
Python and I needed to get models to
work on replicate and stuff and I needed
to improve photo ey and he helped me a
lot for like 10 months he worked and uh
man I was trying Pyon working with numpy
and package manager and it was too
difficult for me to figure this shit out
and I didn't have time like I think 10
years ago I would have time to like sit
you know go do all nighters to figure
this stuff out with python I don't have
the and I don't have the it's not my
thing it's not your thing it's another
programming language I get it AI new
thing got it but like you've never had a
developer roll in look at your PHP J
query code and be and yes like you know
like in conversation or in impr they
talk about yes and like basically all
right I had for one week understand and
then it ended because he wanted to
rewrite everything in the no that's the
wrong guy I know he wanted to rewrite in
what he wanted to rewrite to he said to
JY we cannot do this I'm like okay he's
like we need to rewrite everything think
in view VJs I'm like are you sure come
just like kind you know like keep jaker
he's like no man like and uh we need to
change a lot of stuff and I'm like okay
and I was kind of like feeling it like
this you know we're going to clean up
shit but then after weeks this it's not
gonna it's gonna take way too much time
I think I like working with people where
like when I approach
them I pretend in my head that they're
the smartest person who has ever existed
wow so I look at their code or I look at
the stuff they've created and try to see
The Genius of their way like you really
have to understand people like really
notice them like really and then from
that place have a conversation about
what is the better approach yeah but
those are the top tier developers yeah
and they those are the ones that are
Tech ambiguous so they can work with
they can learn any teex Tech and they
can and that's like really few like it's
like top 5% cuz if you try hire deps
like no offense to devs but most devs
are not man most people in general jobs
are not so good at their job like even
doctors and stuff when you realize this
people are very average at the job
especially with death with coding I
think so sorry I think that's a really
important skill for for developer to
roll in and like understand the
musicality the the style of and like
empathy it's like code empathy right
code empathy yeah it's a new word but
that's it you need to understand like go
over all the code get a holistic view of
it and man you can suggest we we change
stuff for sure but um and look jur is
crazy it's crazy I'm using J Cur we can
change that it's not crazy at all jQuery
is also like beautiful and powerful and
PHP is beautiful and Powerful especially
as you said recently in the in the in
the as the versions evolved it's much
more serious programming language now
it's super
like PHP is really fast now it's cat
JavaScript much Ruby really fast now so
if speed is something you care about
it's super fast um and like there's
gigantic communities of people using
those programming languages and there's
Frameworks if you like the framework so
there whatever it doesn't really matter
what you use but like also you if I was
like a developer working with you like
you are extremely successful you've
shipped a lot so like if I roll in I'm
going to be be like I don't assume you
know nothing assume Peter's a genius
like the smartest developer ever and
like learn learn from it and yes and
like notice Parts in the code where like
okay okay okay I got it like here's how
he's thinking and now if I want to add
another uh like a little feature
definitely needs to have
Emoji yeah in front of it and then like
just follow the same style and add it
and my goal is to make you happy to make
make you smile like to make you like ha
fuck I I get it and now you're going to
start respecting me and like trusting me
and like you start working together in
this way I I don't know I I don't know
how hard is to find developers no I
think that exist I think you need to I
need to hire more people need to try
more people but that cost a lot of my
energy and time but it's 100% possible
but do I want it I don't know things
kind of run fine for now and I mean like
okay you can say like okay nor looks
kind of clunky like people say the
design is kind of clunk okay I'll
improve the design it's like next to my
to-do list for example you know like I
can I'll get there eventually but it's
true I mean you're also extremely good
at at what you do like I'm just looking
at the interfaces of like Photo AI like
you would Jake by the way jQuery right
like how amazing is jQuery but like you
can these Cowboys are getting these are
there's these
Cowboys this is a lot it's a lot but I'm
glad they're all wearing shirts anyway
the interface here is just really really
nice like I could tell you know what
you're doing and with Nomad list
extremely nice the interface thank you
man and that's all you yeah that's
everything is me so all of this in every
little feature all say it looks kind of
ADHD or add you know like it's so much
because it has so many things and design
these days is minimalist right right
right I hear you but this is uh a lot of
information and it's useful information
is delivered in a clean way while still
stylish and fun to look at so like
minimalist design is about like when you
want to convey no information whatsoever
and look cool it's very cool it's
pretentious right pretentious or not
that the function is like is useless
this is about a lot of information
delivered to you in a clean and when
it's clean you can't be too sexy so it's
sexy enough yeah this is I think how my
brain looks you know like there's a lot
of shit going on it's like drawing based
music it's like
very yeah but it's still pretty the
spacing of everything is nice the font a
really nice like very readable very
small I like it you know but I made it
so I don't trust my own judgments no
this is really nice thank you the Emojis
are somehow like it's a style it's a
thing I need to pick the Emoji it takes
a while to pick them you know there's
some something about Emoji is a really
nice memorable like placeholder for the
idea yeah like if it was just text it
would actually be overwhelming if you
was just text the Emoji really helps
it's a brilliant addition like some some
people might look at it why do you have
emojis everywhere it's actually really
for me it's really tell me to to remove
the Emojis people don't know what
they're talking about and then
the I'm sure people will tell you a lot
of things this is really nice and then
using color is nice small font but not
too small and obviously you have to show
maps which is really tricky
yeah yeah this is this is no this is
really really really nice and all of I
mean like okay like how this looks when
you uh hover over it yeah as transitions
no I understand that but like I'm sure
there's like how long does it take you
to figure out how you want it to look do
you ever go out down Rabbit Hole where
you spend like two weeks no it's all
iterative it's like 10 years of you know
add a SE transition here or or do this
or well was say like see these are all
these are rounded now yeah if you wanted
to like H round is probably the better
way but if you wanted to be rectangular
like sharp Corners what would you do you
just so I go to the index. CSS and I do
command F and I search border radius
12px and then I replace with border
radius zero and then I do command enter
and it's G deploys it it pushes to the
GI Hub and then sends a webbook and then
deploys to my server and it's live in 5
seconds oh you often deploy to
production you you don't have like a
testing ground no so
I so I I'm like famous for this Cu uh
I'm too lazy to set up like a staging
server on my laptop every time so I
nowadays I just deploy to production
yeah and um it's man I'm going to canel
for this you know but it it works very
well for me CU I have a lot of I have
like PHP lint and J lint so it tells me
when has error so I don't deploy but my
literally I I I have like 37,000 git
commits in the last 12 months or
something so I make like small fix and
then command enter M uh and sends to
GitHub GitHub sends a web to my server
web server pulls it deploys the
production and it's there what's the
latency of that from you pressing one
second can be one two seconds to make a
change and then you're getting really
good at like not making mistakes
basically man 100% you're right like
people are like how can you do this why
you get good at not taking the server
down you know like because you need to
code more carefully but it's look it's
idiotic in any big company but for me it
works because it makes me so fast like
somebody um will report a bug on Twitter
and I kind of did do like a stopwatch
like how fast can I fix this bug and
then two minutes later for example it's
fixed yeah and it's fun cuz it's cuz
it's annoying for me to work with
companies where report a bug and it
takes like 6 months yeah it's like
horrible and it makes people really
happy when you can really quickly solve
their problems so but it's it's crazy
I'm I admit I don't think it's crazy I I
mean there's I'm sure there's a middle
ground but I think that whole thing
where there's a a phase of like testing
and there's the staging and there's a
develop and then there's like multiple
tables and databases that you use for
the state like it's fing it's a mess and
there's different teams involved it's
it's not good I'm like a good funny
extreme on the other size you know but
just a little bit safer but not too much
it would be great yeah yeah I'm sure
that's actually like how X now how they
doing rapid Improvement they do because
there's more bugs and people complain
about like oh look he bought this
Twitter now it's full of bugs dude he's
shipping stuff like things are happening
now and it's a dynamic app now yeah the
bugs is actually a sign of a good thing
happening the bugs of the feature
because it shows that the team is
actually building shit 100% well one of
the problems is like I see with YouTube
there's so much potential to build
features but I just see how long it
takes so I've gotten a chance to uh
interact with with many other teams but
one of the teams is uh MLA multilanguage
audio I don't know if you know this but
in YouTube you can have audio tracks in
different languages for overdubbing and
that there's a team and not many people
are using it but like every single
feature they have to meet and agree and
like there's allocate resources like
Engineers have to work on it but I'm
sure it's a pain in the ass for the
engineers to get approval to like
because that it has to not break the
rest of the site whatever they do but
like if you don't have enough
dictatorial like top down like we need
this now it's going to take forever to
do anything multilanguage audio but
multilanguage audio is a good example of
a thing that seems Niche right now but
it quite possibly could change the
entire world when you have when I upload
this this conversation right here if
instantaneously it dubs it into 40
languages yeah man and everybody consume
every single video can be watched and
listened to in those different it
changes everything and YouTube is
extremely well positioned to be the
leader in this they got the they got the
compute they got the uh the user base
they got like they have the experience
of how to do this so like multilanguage
audio should be high priority feature
right yeah that's high priority like and
it's a way you know Google is obsessed
with AI right now they want to show off
that they could be dominant in AI That's
a way for Google to say like we used AI
like this is a way to to to Break Down
The Walls that language creates the
preferred outcome for them for them is
probably their career and not the the
overall result of the the cool product
you know I think they they're not like
selfish or whatever they they want to do
good there's something about the machine
organization organizational stuff that I
have this when I report bogs and like
big companies I work with I get I talk
to a lot of different people DM and
they're all really trying hard to do
something they're all really nice and
I'm the one being kind of asshole cuz
I'm like guys I'm talking to 20 people
about this for six months and nothing's
happening and say man I know but I'm
trying my best and yeah so it's systemic
yeah so what it requires again I don't
know if there must be a nicer word but
like a dictatorial type of top down the
co rolls in uh and just says like for
YouTube it's like MLA get this done now
this is the highest priority I think big
companies especially in America a lot of
it is legal right you need to pass
everything through legal yeah and you
can't like man the things I do I could
never do that in a big Corporation
because it's everything has to be
probably get deployed has to go to Legal
well again dict tutorial you basically
say Steve Jobs did this quite a lot I've
seen a lot of leaders do this ignore the
lawyers ignore coms ignore PR ignore
everybody give power to the engineers
like listen to the people on the ground
get this shit done and get it done by
Friday yeah that's it and the law can
change like for example let's say you
you launch this AI dubbing and it
there's some law legal problems with
lawsuits okay so the Law changes there
will be appeals there will be some
Supreme Court thing whatever and the Law
changes so just by shipping it you
change society you change the legal
framework and by not shipping being
scared of the legal framework all the
time like you're not changing things
just out of curiosity what uh what IDE
do you use let's talk about like your
whole
setup given how ultr productive you are
and that you often programing your
underwear slouching in the couch is
there does it matter to you in general
is there like a specific ID you use vs
code yeah vs code before I use Sublime
Text I don't think it matters a lot I
think I'm I'm very skeptical of like
tools when people think it they say it
matters right I don't think it matters I
think uh whatever tool you know very
well you can go very very fast in like
you know the shortcuts for example IDE
you know you know like um I love Sublime
Text because I could use like multic
cursor you know you search something and
I could like make Mass replaces in a
file with the cursor thing and uh VOD
doesn't really have that as well it's
actually interesting Sublime is the
first editor where I've learned that and
I think they just make that super easy
so like what would that be called
multi-edit multi multi cursor edit thing
whatever I'm sure like almost every
editor can do that it's just probably
hard to set up yeah's not so good at it
I think or at least I try it but I would
use say to like uh process data like um
data sets for example from World Bank I
would just multic cursor Mass change
everything um but yeah vs code I man I
was bullied into using vs code because
Twitter would always see my screenshots
of sublime text and say why are you
still using Sublime Text like Boomer you
need to use vs codes and I'm like okay
I'll try it I I got a new Macbook and
then I I never install like I never copi
the old MacBook I just make it fresh you
know like a clean like format C you know
Windows like clean start and I'm like
okay I'll try vs code and it's stuck you
know but I don't really care like it's
not so important for me wow you know the
format see reference huh dude it was so
good you would install Windows and then
after three or six months it would start
breaking and everything was like get
slow then you would restart go to Doss
format C you would delete your hard
drive and then install the Windows 95
again was so good times and you would
design everything like now I'm going to
install it properly now I'm going to
design my desktop properly you know like
yeah I don't know if it's peer pressure
but like I use zMAX for many many years
and I know you know I love lisp so a lot
of the
customization is done in lisp it's a
programming language it partially was
peer pressure but part of was realizing
like you need to keep learning stuff
like the same issue with jQuery like I
still think I need to learn node.js for
example yeah even though that's not my
main thing or even close to the main
thing but I feel like you need to keep
learning this
stuff and even if you don't choose to
use it long term you need to give it a
chance so you your understanding of the
world expands yeah you want to
understand the new technological
Concepts and see if they can benefit you
you know it would be stupid not to even
try it's more about the concepts I would
say than the actual tools like expanding
and that can be a challenging thing so
going to VSS code and like really
learning it like all the shortcuts all
the extensions and actually installing
different stuff and playing with it that
was a interesting challenge it was
uncomfortable at first yeah for me too
yeah yeah but you just dive in it's like
neur Flex like you keep your brain fresh
you know like this kind of stuff I got
to do that more like have you given
react a chance no but I I want to I want
to learn I want to I I understand the
basics right
um I don't really know where to start
but would you like I guess you got to
use your own model which is like build
the thing using it no man you're so I
kind of did that like I kind like the
the the stuff I do in Jer is essentially
a lot of it is like I start rebuilding
whatever Tech is already out there not
based on that but just an accident like
I keep goinging long enough that I built
the same I start getting the same
problems everybody else had and you
start building the same Frameworks kind
of so I essentially I use my own kind of
framework of so you basically build a
framework from scratch that's your own
that you understand it kind of yeah with
ax calls but essentially it's same same
thing look I don't have the time I don't
and this is I think saying you don't
have the time is like always a lie
because you just don't prioritize it
enough my priority is still like the the
running the businesses and improving
that and and AI I think learning AI is
much more Val out and learning uh a
front end framework yeah like it's just
more impact I guess you should be just
learning every single day a thing yeah
you can learn a little bit every day
like a little bit of react or I think
now like next is very big so learn a
little bit of next you know but I I call
them the military industrial complex so
if I but you need to know you need to
know it anyway so you got to learn how
to use the weapons of war and then and
then you can be a peace neck yeah yeah I
mean but you got to learn in in in the
same exact ways we were talking about
which is learning by trying to build
something with it and actually deploy it
the Frameworks are so complicated and it
changes so fast so it's like where do I
start you know and I guess it's the same
thing when you're starting out making
websites like how where do you start as
gp4 I guess but it yeah it's just so
Dynamic it changes so fast that I don't
know if it would be a good idea for me
to learn it you know um maybe some
combination of like few next with PHP
laravel laravel is like a framework for
PHP I think that would be uh it could
benefit me you know maybe Tailwind for
CS like a styling engine that that stuff
could probably save me time yeah but
like you you won't know until you really
give it a try and it feels like you have
to build like if maybe I'm talking to
myself but like I I should
probably recode like my personal one
page in laral or yeah and even though it
might not have almost any Dynamic
elements maybe have one Dynamic element
but it has to go end to end in that
framework or like end to end build it in
node.js some of it is I don't figuring
out how to you even deploy the thing
have no idea all I know is right now I
would send it to GitHub and it sends it
to my server I don't know how to get
JavaScript running I have no clue yeah
so I guess I need like a a pass like a
like versal right or uh you know Heroku
kind of those kind of platforms I
actually kind of just my gave myself the
idea of like I kind of just want to
build a single web page like one web
page that has like one Dynamic element
and just do it in every single like in a
lot of Frameworks like just ah on the
same page same same page kind page
that's a cool prodct like learn all
these Frameworks and you can see the
differences yeah that's interesting how
long it takes to do it yeah stopwatch I
have to figure out actually something
sufficiently complicated because it
should probably do it should probably do
some kind of
thing where it accesses the database and
dynamically is changing stuff some AI
stuff some llm stuff yeah maybe some it
doesn't have to be
aii call Api call to something to to
replicate for example and then you have
yeah that would be a very cool project
yeah yeah and like time it and also
report on my happiness yeah I'm going to
totally do this cuz nobody benchmarks
this nobody's Benchmark happy developer
happiness with Frameworks yeah nobody's
benchmarked the shipping time just take
like a month do this how many Frameworks
are there there's how many how many
there there's like five main ways of
doing it so there's like this is no
there's back end front end and this
stuff confused me too like react now
apparently has become back end yeah or
something used to be only front end and
you're forced to do now backend also I
don't know and then but there's not
really you're not really forced to do
anything so like B according to the
Internet so like there's no um it's
actually not trivial to find the canical
way of doing things so like the standard
vanilla like you you go to the ice cream
shop there's like a million flavors I
want vanilla if if I've never had ice
cream in my life can we just like learn
about ice cream yeah I want vanilla
nobody actually sometimes they'll
literally name it vanilla but like I
want to know what's the basic way but
not like dumb but like the standard
canonical want to know the dominant way
like 60% of developers do it like this
it's hard to figure that out you know
that's the problem yeah maybe LMS can
help maybe you should explicitly ask
what is the dominant they usually know
like the dominant you know they they
they give answers that are like the most
probable kind of yeah so that makes
sense to ask them and not I think
honestly maybe it would help is if if
you want to learn or I would want to
learn like a framework hire somebody
that already does it and just sit with
them and make something together like
I've never done that but I thought about
it that would be a very fast way to you
know take their knowledge
Tred these kinds of things what happens
is depends what kind of if they're like
a worldclass developer yes often times
they themselves are used to that thing
and they have not themselves explored in
other options so they have this dogmatic
like talking down to you like this is
the right way to do it it's like no no
no we're just like exploring together
okay show me the cool thing you've
tried which is like it has to have U
open-mindedness to like you know node.js
is not the right way to do web
development it's like one way and
there's nothing wrong with the the old
lamp PHP jQuery vanilla JavaScript way
it just has its pros and cons and like
you need to know what those people exist
you could find those people probably
yeah like if you want to learn AI
imagine you have karpati sitting next to
you teach you L like he does his YouTube
videos is amazing he can teach it to
like a 5-year-old about how how to make
llm it's amazing like imagine this guy
sitting next to you and just teaching
you like let's make LM together like
holy shit it would be amazing yeah I
mean well
Kath has its own style and his like I'm
not sure he he's for everybody but for
example 5-year-old it depends on the
5-year-old yeah but he's like super
technical but he's amazing because he's
super technical and he's the only one
who can explain stuff in a simple way
which shows his complete genius yes
because if you can explain without
jargon you're like wow and build it from
scratch yeah it's like top tier you know
like what a guy but he might be anti
framework cuz he buil from Scrat exactly
yeah actually probably is yeah uh he's
like you but for AI yeah so maybe
learning framework is a is a very bad
idea for us you know maybe we should
stay in PHP and like script Kitty and
the but you have to Maybe by learning
the framework you learn what you want to
yourself build from scratch yeah maybe
you learn Concepts but you don't
actually have to start using it for your
life right yeah yeah
and you're still a Mac guy was a Mac guy
yeah yeah I switched to Mac in 2015
because uh it was CU When I wanted to
start traveling and my brother was like
dude get a Macbook is like the standard
now I'm like wow I need to switch from
Windows and I had like three screens you
know like Windows had this whole setup
for music production I had to sell
everything um and then I had a Macbook
and I remember opening up this MacBook
box like ah and it was so beautiful it
was like this aluminum and then I opened
it I removed the you know the screen
protector thing mhm it's so beautiful
and I didn't touch it for three days I
was just like looking at it really and I
was still on the Windows computer and
then I went traveling with that so I and
all my great things started when I
switched to MEC which sounds very
dogmatic right but what great things are
you talking about all the business
started working out like I started
traveling I started building startups I
started making money it all started when
I switched to Mech listen I I kind
of you're making me want to switch to
Mac so I use either use Linux inside
windows with w SL or just UB ontu Linux
but windows for most stuff like editing
or any like uh
any yeah yeah well you could use I guess
you could do Mac stuff there I wonder if
I should switch what do you miss about
Windows what was the pros and cons I
think the finder is horrible MEC like
it's like it's it's the what is horrible
the finder oh you don't know the so this
the Windows Explorer
yeah is amazing finder is strange man
there like strange things this's this
bug where if you if you send like test
your photo on WhatsApp or telegram it
just selects the whole folder and you
almost accidentally can click enter and
you send all your photos all your files
to this chat group have it to my
girlfriend she starts sending me photo
photo photo photo photo so F finder is
very unusable but it has Linux like the
whole thing is like it's Unix based
right so you use the command line like
yeah all the time like all the time and
the cool thing is you can run I think
it's like Unix like Debian or whatever
you can run most Linux stuff on MEC OS
which makes it very very good for
development like I have my engine X
server you know if I set if I'm not lazy
and set up my staging on my laptop it's
just the engine X server the same as I
have on my Cloud Server right the same
where the websites run and I can use
almost everything the same config files
configuration files and it just works
and that makes Mac a very good platform
for Linux stuff I
think yeah yeah real Ubuntu is like
better of course but yeah I'm in this
weird situation where
I'm somewhat of a power user in Windows
and let's say Android and all the much
smarter friends I have all using Mac and
iPhone and it's like but you don't want
to go through the peer pressure you know
it's not peer pressure it's
like like one of the reasons I want to
have kids is that there's a lot of like
I I would love to have kids as a base as
a baseline but you know there's like a
concern maybe there's going to be a
tradeoff for all this kind of stuff but
you see like these extremely successful
smart people who are friends of mine who
have kids and are really happy they have
kids so that's that's not peer pressure
that's just like a strong signal works
for people it works for people and the
same thing with Mac it's like
yeah like the the fun like I don't see
fundamentally I don't like closed
systems so like fundamentally I like
Windows more because there there's much
more freedom same with Android there's
much more freedom it's much more
customizable but like all the the cool
kids the smart kids are using Mac and
iPhone it's like all right I need to
really I need to give it a real chance
especially for development since more
and more stuff is done in the cloud
anyway yeah well anyway uh but it's
funny to hear you say all the good stuff
started happening maybe I'll be like
that guy too when I switch to Mac all
the good stuff started happening I think
it's just about the hardware it's not so
much about the software the hardware so
well builds right the keyboard and yeah
but look at the keyboard I use so that
is pretty cool
that's one word for it uh what's your
favorite place to work uh on the couch
does the couch matter is the couch at
home or is it any couch no any like
Hotel couch also like in the room right
in yeah but I used to work like very
ergonomically with like a standing desk
yeah and everything like perfect like
eye height screen blah blah blah and I
felt like man this has to do with
lifting too I started getting RSI like
uh repetitive strain injury like
tingling stuff and it would go all the
way on my back and I was sitting in a
co-working space like 6:00 a.m. sun
comes up and I'm working and I'm coding
and I hear like a sound or something so
I do like I look left and my neck get
stuck like and I'm like wow fuck and
um I'm like what's am I dying you know
and I thought I'm probably dying so I
don't want to die in a cing space I'm
going to go home and die in like you
know peace and honor yeah so I close my
laptop and I put it in my backpack and I
walked to the to the street and got on
my motorbike went home um and I lie down
on like a a pillow like with my legs up
and stuff uh to get rid of this like
because it was my whole back and it was
because I was working like this all the
time yeah so um I started getting like a
a laptop stand everything ergonomically
correct but then I started lifting and
since then like it seems like uh
everything gets straightened out your
posture kind of you're more straight and
I never have RS RSI anymore rep injury I
never have tingling anymore uh no pain
and stuff so then I started working on
the sofa and it's great like it it feels
um you're close to the I I sit like I
sit like this yeah legs together and
then a pillow and then a laptop and then
I work are you like leaning back I'm
kind of
like together like legs and then where's
the mouse using using the No No so every
St bed on the Mac OS on the MacBook I
used to have the Logitech MX Mouse the
perfect economic Mouse doing like this
little with thing one screen one screen
and I used to have three screens so I
come from the I know where people come
from I I had I had all the stuff but
then I realized that having it all
condensed in one laptop it's a 16-inch
Macbook so it's quite big but having it
all there is amazing because you're so
close to the tools you're so close to
what's happening you know it's like
working on the car or something it's
like so um like man if you have Tre skin
you look here look there you get also
neck injury actually so it's well I
don't know this this sounds like you're
part of a cult and you're just trying to
convince me but uh I mean but it's good
to hear that you can be ultra productive
on a single screen that's I me that's
crazy command tap you alt up like when
is alt up Mac command you switch very
fast so you have like one the entire
screen is taken out by vs code say you
look at the code and then yeah and then
like if you deploy like a website you
what switch screens mon to Chrome I used
to have this swipe screen you know you
could do like um different screen spaces
yeah I was like it's too difficult let's
just put it on one screen on the MacBook
and then and he can be productive that
way yeah very productive yeah more
productive than before interesting
because I have I have three screens and
two of them are vertical like the size
code right yeah for code you can see a
lot no man I love it like I'm I love
seeing it with friends like they have
amazing like Battle Stations right it's
called It's amazing I want it but I
don't want it right like do you like the
constraints there's that's it there's
some aspect of the constraints which
like once get good at it you can focus
your mind and you can man I'm suspicious
of like more you know yeah you really
need all the stuff like it might Slow Me
Down actually it's a good way to put it
I'm suspicious of more me too I'm
suspicious of more in all in all ways in
all because you can defend more right
you can defend yeah I'm a developer I
make money I need to I need to get more
screens right I need to be more
efficient and then you read stuff about
like mythical man month where like
hiring more people slows down a software
project project that's famous I think
you can use that metaphor maybe for you
know tools as well then I see friends
just with gear acquisition syndrome
buying so much stuff but they're not
that productive they have the best be
most beautiful Battle Stations desktops
everything they're not that productive
and it's also like kind of fun like it's
all from my laptop in a backpack right
it's kind of noat minimalist take me
through like the perfect ultr productive
day in your
life like say like where you get a lot
of shit done yeah are you uh and it's
all focused on getting shit done what
what when are you waking up is it a
regular time super early super late so I
go to sleep like 2: am. usually
something like that and uh before 4:
a.m. uh but my girlfriend would go sleep
midnight so we did a compromise like 2:
a.m. you know MH so I wake up around 10
11 then more like 10: um shower make
coffee I make coffee like drip coffee
like the V60 you know the filter and I
boil water and I put the coffee in um
and then chill a little with my
girlfriend and then open laptop start
coding check what's going on like bugs
or whatever how long how long are you
like how stretches of time are you able
to just sit behind the computer coding
so I used to need like really long
stretches where I would do like all
nighters and stuff to get shit done but
I've gotten trained to like have more
interruptions where I can like cuz you
have to this life like there's a lot of
distractions like like your girlfriend
asked off people come over whatever yeah
um so I'm very fast now I can lock in
and lock out quite fast and I heard
people developers or entrepreneurs with
kids have the same thing like before
they're like ah I cannot work but they
get used to it and they get really
productive in like short time because
they only have like 20 minutes and then
shit goes crazy again so another
constraint right yeah it's funny so
think that works for me um yeah and then
you know cook food and stuff like have
lunch steak and chicken and eat a bunch
of times a day so you say coffee what
are you doing yeah so a few hours later
cook foods we get like locally soures
like meat and stuff and vegetables and
cook that uh and then second coffee and
then coat some more maybe go outside for
lunch like you can you can mix fun stuff
you know how many hours are you say in a
perfectly productive day are you doing
programming like if you were like to
kill it are you doing like all day
basically you mean like the special days
where like girlfriend leaves to like
Paris or something and you're alone for
a week at home which is amazing you can
just coat it's like and you stay up all
night and eat chocolate and yeah
chocolate yeah you know okay okay let's
remove girlfriend from picture social
life from picture it's just you man that
shit goes crazy like cuz when shit goes
now she goes crazy okay okay so sh you
let's let's rewind are you still waking
up there's coffee there's no girlfriend
to talk to there's now we wake
up like 1: p.m. at 2
p.m. cuz you went to bed at 6 a.m. yeah
cuz I was coding I was finding some new
AI shit and I was studying it and it was
amazing and I cannot sleep because it's
too important we need to stay awake we
need to see all of this we need to make
something now and but that's the times I
do make like new stuff more so I think I
have a friend he actually books a hotel
for like a week to like leave his and he
has a kid too and his girlfriend and his
kid stay in the house and he goes to
another hotel sounds a little suspicious
right going to the hotel but all he does
is like writing or coding he's a writer
and he needs like this alone time this
silence and I think for this Flow State
it's true you know I'm better
maintaining stuff um when there's a lot
of disruptions than like creating new
stuff I need this it's common it's flow
it's this uninterrupted period of time
um so yeah I wake up like 1 2 p.m. um
you know still coffee shower we still
shower you know uh and then this code
like nonstop maybe my friend comes over
uh comes over some distraction yeah he
also Andre codes too so he comes over we
code together we listen you know it
starts going back to like the Bali days
you know like yeah coor days like you're
not really working with him but you're
just both working because it's nice to
have like the vibe where you both sit
together on the couch and coding on
something and you actually it's mostly
silent or there music you know and
sometimes you ask something and but
generally like you're really locked in
and what uh what music are you listening
to I think like like um techno like
YouTube techno um there's a there's a
channel called h o r with a o Loud Like
H O like double dot it's it's Berlin
techno whatever it looks like it's they
film it in like a toilet with like white
tiles and stuff and very cool and they
always have like very good like kind of
industrial like indust so fast kind of
aggressive you know
like that's not distracting to your
brain that's amazing like I think
distracting man Jazz like I listen
coffee Jazz with my girlfriend when I
wake up and it's kind of like this piano
starts getting annoying it's
like it's too many tones it's like too
many things going on this industrial
techno is like you know this African
like rain dances
like it's this transcendental trans
that's interesting cuz I I I actually
mostly now listen to uh Brown noise
noise yeah wow like pretty loud wow and
one of the things you learn is your
brain gets used to whatever so I'm sure
to techno if I actually give it a real
chance yeah my brain would get used to
it but like with with noise what happens
is something happens to your brain I
think there's a science to it but I
don't really care you just have to be a
a scientist of one like study yourself
your own brain for me it like it does
something I discovered it right away
when I tried it for the first
time after about like a couple minutes
your
everything every distraction just like
disappears and it goes
like you can like
hold focus on things like really well
it's weird like you can like really
focus on a thing it doesn't really
matter what that is I think that's what
people achieve with like meditation you
can like like focus on your breath for
example it's normal Brown It's not like
binar no it's just normal
Brown yeah white noise I think it's the
same it's like pink Noise White Noise uh
Brown noise I think is when it's like
basier like yeah it's more diffused more
dampened yeah dampened yeah I can see
that no sharp yeah sharp brightness yeah
bright yeah I can see that and you use a
headphone right yeah headphones yeah
actually like walk around in life often
with brown noise dude that's like
psychopath shit but it's cool you know
yeah yeah yeah when I murder people it
helps it it drowns out their screams
Jesus Christ sorry I said too much no
I'm going to try Brown noise with the
murder or for the coding yeah for the
coding yeah okay good uh try it try it
but you have to like with everything
else you give it a real chance yeah I
find I also like I said do uh techno
type stuff electronic music on top of
the brown
noise uh but then control the speed cuz
the faster goes and more anxiety so if I
really need to get shit done especially
with programming I'll have a beat yeah
and it's great it's cool I say it's cool
to play those little tricks with your
mind to study yourself yeah I usually
don't like to have people around because
when people even if they're working I
don't know I like people too much
they're like interesting no that's my
yeah in coworkers space I would just
start too much yeah yeah so there's a
source of distraction yeah we would do
in the cob space we would do like a a
money like pot like a mug so if you
would we would work for 45 minutes and
then if you would say one like per word
you would get a fine which is like $1 so
you'd put $1 to say hey what's up so
three $3 you put in the mug um and then
10 15 minutes free time like we can like
party whatever and then 45 minutes again
I'm working and that worked but you need
to shut people up where they you know I
think there's um
there's an
intimacy in being silent together that I
might maybe I'm uncomfortable with like
but you if you need to make yourself
vulnerable and actually do it like with
with close friends to just sit there and
silence for long periods of time and
like doing a thing dude I watched this
um this video of this podcast it was
like this Buddhism podcast with people
meditating and they were interviewing
each other or whatever and like a
podcast and suddenly after a question
it's like yeah
yeah and they were just silent for like
three minutes and then they said that
was amazing yeah that was amazing I was
like Wow pretty cool you know elon's
like
that and I I really like that when
you'll ask a
question like uh I don't know what's a
perfectly productive day for you like I
I just asked and you just sit there for
like 30 seconds thinking yeah he
thinks yeah I don't know that's so cool
I wish I was
was I wish I could think more about but
I want to like I want to show you my
heart you know I want to show you go
straight from my heart to my mouth to
like saying the real thing and the more
I think the more I start like filtering
myself right and I want to just throw it
out there immediately I I do that more
with Team I think he has a lot of
practice in that I I do that as well in
the team setting when you're thinking
brainstorming and you allow yourself to
just like think in silence yeah just
like because even in meetings people
want to talk
yeah it's like no you think before you
speak and just like it's okay to be
silent together yeah and if you allow
yourself the room to do that you can
actually come up with really good ideas
yeah so okay this perfect
day how much caffeine are you consuming
in this day man too much right cuz uh
normally like two two cups of coffee but
on this perfect day like we go to like
four maybe so we're starting to hit like
the anxiety levels so four cups is a lot
for you well I think my coffees are
quite strong when I make them it's like
20 gram of uh coffee powder in the V60
so like my friends call him like nuclear
coffee cuz it's quite heavy it's quite
strong um but it's nice to hit that
anxiety level where you're like almost
panic attack but you're not there yet so
but that's like man it's like super
locked in just
like it's amazing but I mean that's
there's a space for that you know in my
life but uh it's uh I think it's great
for making new stuff it's amazing start
starting from scratch creating a new
thing yes I think girlfriends should let
their guys go away for like two weeks
mhm every few no every year at least you
know maybe every quarter I don't know
and just sit and make some shit without
you know they're amazing but like no
disturbances just be alone and then you
know people can make something very very
amazing just wearing cowboy hats in the
mountains like we showed exactly we can
do that there's a movie about that with
the laptops they didn't do much
programming though yeah you can do a
little bit of that okay and then a
little bit of shipping you know do
both it's a different broke they need to
allow us to go you know you need like a
man cave right yeah to ship yeah to ship
get shit done yeah it's a balance okay
cool what about sleep naps and all that
you're not sleeping much I don't do naps
in a day I think it's power naps are
good but I don't really I'm never tired
anymore in the day uh man also because
of gym I'm not tired I I'm tired when I
want to when you know when it's night I
need to sleep me I love apps I don't
care I don't know I don't know why brain
shuts off turns on I don't know if it's
healthy or not it just works yeah I
think with anything mental physical you
have to be a student of your own body
and like know know what the limits are
like that you have to be skeptical
taking advice from the internet in
general cuz a lot of advice is just like
a good Baseline for the general
population but personalized yeah you
have to become a student of your own
like of your own body of your own self
of how you work yeah that's I've I've
done a lot of like for me fasting was an
interesting one because I used to you
know eat a bunch of meals a day
especially when I was lifting heavy like
as everybody says to you have to eat uh
kind of a lot you know multiple meals a
day but I realize I can get much
stronger feel much better if I eat once
or twice a day man me too yeah it's
crazy I never underst do this small meal
thing yeah didn't work for me let me
just ask you it'd be interesting if you
can comment on some of the other
products you've created
we talked about Nomad list interior AI
photo AI therapist AI what's remote okay
it's a job board for remote jobs um
because back then like 10 years ago
there was uh job boards but there was
not really specifically promote job job
boards so I made one B I made like first
on Nomad Le I made like Nomad jobs like
a page and a lot of companies started
hiring and they pay for job post so I
spin it off to remote and now it's like
the number one or number two biggest
remote job boards and uh and it's also
fully automated it and people just post
a job and people apply it has like
profiles as well like it's kind of like
LinkedIn for remotes work just focus on
remote only yeah it's this it's
essentially like a simple job board I
discovered job boards are way more
complicated than you think but um yeah
it's a jobboard for remote
jobs but the nice thing is you can
charge a lot of money for job posst it's
man it's good money B2B you can charge
like you start of$ 299 but at the peak
during when the FED started printing
money like 2021 I was making like 140k a
month with remot k with just jaob posts
and I started like adding crazy upsells
like rainbow colored uh jaw post you can
add your background name it's just
upsells man and you charge $5 for an
upsell it was crazy and uh all these
companies just UPS so up so yeah we want
everything jobst would cost
$3,400
$4,000 and I was like this is good good
business and then the fat stopped
printing money and it all went down and
it went down to like 10K a month from
140 yeah now it's back it's I think it's
like 40 was good times you know uh I got
to ask you about back to the digital
Nomad life yeah you uh you wrote a blog
post on the reset and in general like
just giving away everything living a
minimalist life yeah what did it take to
do that like to get rid of everything 10
years ago was like this trend in the
blog back then blogs were so popular was
like a blogosphere and it was like the
100 things challenge what is that the
100 things I mean it's ridiculous but
like you you write down every object you
have in your house and you count it you
make like a spreadsheet and you're like
okay I have 500 things you need to get
it down to 100 why you know this was
just a trend so I did it I started like
selling stuff started throwing away
stuff and I did like MDMA and easy like
2012 kind of and uh after that trip I
felt so different and I felt like I had
to started throwing shit away like I
swear yeah and I started throwing shit
away and I felt that was like it was
almost like the drug sending me to a
path of like you need to throw your shit
away you need to start you know go on a
journey you need to get out of here and
um and that's what the MDMA did I think
yeah how hard is it to get down to 100
items well you need to like sell your PC
and stuff you need s you need to go on
eBay and then man going eBay selling or
your stuff is verying because you
discover Society you mat you meet the
craziest people you meet every range
from Rich the poor everybody comes to
your house to buy stuff it's so funny so
interesting I recommend everybody do
this just to meet people people that
want your shit yeah it was so like I I
didn't know was I was living in
Amsterdam and I didn't know I have my
own you know subculture whatever and I
discovered the Dutch people like as they
are from eBay you know so I sold
everything what's what's like the
weirdest thing you had to sell and you
had to find a buyer for not the weirds
but like what what's memorable so back
then I was I was making music and I we
would make music videos with like a
Canon 5D camera back then everybody's
making films and music that and uh and
we bought it with my friends and stuff
and
it was kind of like I had to sell this
thing too because it was like it was
very expensive like 6K or something yeah
and but it meant that selling this meant
that we wouldn't make music videos
together anymore I would leave Holland
this kind of like stuff we were working
on would end and I was kind of saying
this music video stuff we're not getting
big we're not getting famous in this or
successful we need to stop doing this
this music production also it's not
really working and it was kind of like
felt very bad you know for my friends
cuz we would work together on this and
um to sell this like camera that we make
stuff with and it was a hard goodbye was
just a camera but it was like it felt
like uh sorry guys it doesn't work and I
need to go you know who uh who bought it
do you remember was some guy who
couldn't possibly
understand the journey motion of it yeah
yeah he just showed up here here's the
money thanks yeah but it was like a it
was like cutting your life like this
shit ends now now we GNA do new stuff
and I think it's beautiful I did that
twice in my life give away everything
everything everything like down to just
pants underwear
backpack I think uh I think it's
important to do it shows you what's
important yeah I think that's what I
learned from it like you you learn that
you can live with very little objects
very little stuff and um but there's a
there's a counter to it like you you
lean more on this on the stuff on the
services right like for example you
don't need a car you use Uber right or
you don't need kitchen stuff because you
go to restaurants you know when you're
traveling so you lean more on other
people's services but you spend money on
that as well so that's good yeah but
just letting go of material possessions
which it gives a kind of freedom to how
you move about the world yeah it gives
you complete freedom to go into another
city to yeah with your backpack with a
backpack there's a kind of freedom to it
there's something about material
possessions and having a place and all
that that ties you down a little bit
Yeah like spiritually it's good to take
a leap out into the world especially
when you're younger to like man I
recommend if you're 18 you get out of
high school do this go travel and uh uh
you know build some internet stuff
whatever if your bring your laptop and
uh it's it's amazing experience I five
years ago it's still going to University
but now I'm thinking like no maybe don't
maybe skip University just go first like
travel around a little bit figure some
stuff out you can go back to University
when you're 25 you can like okay now I
learned I being successful in business
you have money at least now you can
choose what you really want to study you
know because people at 18 they go study
what is probably good for the job market
right so it probably makes more sense
like if you want that go travel build
some businesses and go back to
University if you want so one of the
biggest uses of a university is the
networking you you uh you gain friends
you gain like you meet people it's a
forcing function to meet people but if
you can meet people out into the World
by traveling man and you meet so many
different cultures I mean the problem
for me is like if I traveled at that
young age I'm attracted to people at the
outskirts of the world like for me like
where no mean not geographically oh like
the the subcultures the sub yeah like
the weirdos the darkness yeah me too but
but that might not be the best
networking at 18 years
old no but it man if you if you're smart
about it you can stay safe and I met so
many weirdos from traveling you meet
that's how travel works if you really
let lose you meet the craziest people
yeah and it's the most interesting
people
and it's just I cannot recommend it
enough well see the thing is when you're
18 I feel like depending on your
personality you have to learn both how
to be a weirdo and how to be a normie
like you still have to learn how to fit
into society like for a person like me
for example who's always an outcast like
there's always a danger for going full
Outcast yeah and that's a harder life if
you like if you go to like go full
artist and full like Darkness it's just
a heart of life you can come back you
can come back to normally that's a skill
that's like I think you have to learn
how to how to fit
into uh like polite Society but I was
very strange Outcast as well and I'm I'm
more adaptable to normally now you know
learned it after 30s you know you're
like yeah but you mean it's a skill you
have to learn yeah I feel man I feel
also the you start as Outcast but the
more you work on yourself the less like
shit you have you kind of start becoming
more normally because you become more
chill with yourself and more happy and
it kind of makes you uninteresting right
a little bit yes yes like the most the
crazy people are always the most
interesting if you've solved your
internal struggles and your your therapy
and stuff and you kind of become kind of
you know it's not so interesting anymore
maybe you don't have to be broken to be
interesting I guess is what I'm saying
yeah what kind of things were left when
you minimalized so the backpack yeah uh
MacBook uh toothbrush uh some clothes
underwear socks um you don't need a lot
of clothes in Asia cuz it's hot so you
just wear swimpants swim shorts he w
walk around flipflops uh so very basic
t-shirt and uh I would go to the lroom
mat and wash my stuff and I think it was
like 50 F or something yeah yeah it's
nice there's uh as I mentioned to you
there's the the show alone yeah they
really test you cuz they you only get 10
items and you have to survive out in the
wilderness and an axe like everybody
brings an
axe some
people uh also have a
saw wow but usually a does the job you
basically have to in order to build a
shelter you have to cut down cut the
trees and make and like learning
Minecraft you know everything I learn
about life I learn Minecraft
bro yeah yeah you can it's a it's it's
nice to create those constraints for
yourself to understand what matters to
you and also how to be in this world and
one one of the ways to do that just to
live a minimalist life but like some
people like I've met people that really
enjoy material possessions and it brings
him happiness and that's that's a
beautiful thing yeah like for me it
doesn't but people are different it
gives me happiness for like two weeks
yeah I'm very quickly adapting to like a
baseline hedonist hedonistic adaptation
very fast yeah but man if you look at
the studies most people like like
getting a new car six months you know
getting a new house six months you just
feel the same you're like wow should I
buy all the stuff that studying
hedonistic adaptation made me think a
lot about minimalism like and so you
don't even need to go through the whole
journey of getting it just just focus on
the the thing that's more permanent yeah
like building shit yeah like people
around you like people you love nice
food nice experiences meaningful work
those things exercise you know those
things make you happy I think make me
happy for sure you wrote a blog post why
I'm unreachable and maybe you should be
too what's your strategy in
communicating with people yeah so when I
wrote that I was getting so many M as
you probably have you have a million
times more but um and people were
getting angry that I wasn't responding
and I was like okay I'll just close down
these DMS completely M then people got
angry that I Clos my DMs down that I'm
not like man of the people you know it's
like you changed man yeah you Chang you
guys you know like this and I'm like
I'll explain why I just don't have the
time in a day to you know answer every
question and also people send you like
crazy shit man like stalkers and like
people write like their whole life story
for you and then ask you advice like man
I have no idea I'm not a therapist I
don't know I don't know this stuff but
also beautiful stuff no absolutely sure
like life story I've posted a coffee
form like if you wanted to have a coffee
with me and I've gotten an extremely
large number of submissions and when I
look at them there's just like beautiful
people in there like beautiful human
beings really powerful stories and like
breaks my heart that I won't get to meet
those people you know like and so this
part of it is just like there's only so
much bandwidth to truly see other humans
and help them or like understand them or
hear them or yeah see them yeah I have
this problem that I try I want to try
help people and like also like oh let's
make startups and whatever and it's I've
learned over the years that generally
for me and it sounds maybe bad right but
like I help my friend Andre for example
he was he he came up to me in a cing
space that's how I met him and he said I
want to learn a code I want to do
startups how do I do it I said okay
let's go uh install engine X let start
coding and he has this self energy that
he actually um he he doesn't need to be
pushed he just goes and he just goes and
he asks questions and he he doesn't ask
too many questions he just goes goes and
learns it and now he has a company and
makes a lot of money has his own
startups so and the people that that I
had to kind of like that asked me for
help but then I I gave help and then
they started they started debating it
you know do you have that like people
ask you advice and they go against you
say no you're wrong because I'm like
okay bro I don't want debate you ask me
for advice right and the people who need
this push generally it doesn't happen
you need to have this energy for
yourself well they're searching they're
searching they're trying to figure it
out but often times their
search if they successfully find what
they're looking for it'll be within
sounds very like spiritual Sonny but
it's it's really like figuring that shit
out on your own but they're reaching
they're trying to ask the world around
them like how do I live this life how do
I figure this out but ultimately the
answer is going to be from them working
on themselves and like literally it's
the stupid thing but like Googling and
doing like yeah I think it's
procrastination I think sending messages
to people is a lot of procrastination
like Lex how do you become successful
podcaster bro just you know start like
just go yeah and uh just go I would
never ask you how to be a successful
podcaster like I would just start it and
then I would copy your methods you know
I would say ah this guy's a black
background we probably need this as well
yeah try it yeah try it and then you
realize it's not about the black
background it's about something else so
you find your own voice like keep trying
stuffa imitation is a difficult thing
like a lot of people copy and they don't
move past it yeah you should understand
their methods and then move past it like
find yourself find your own voice you
imitate and then you put your own spin
to it you know and that's like creative
process that's like literally the whole
cre everybody always Builds on the
previous work yeah uh you shouldn't get
stuck 24 hours in a day eight hours of
sleep you like break it down into a math
equation uh 90 minutes of showering
clean up
coffee it just keeps whittling down to
zero man it's not this specific but I
had to make like a you know an average
or something firefighting I don't like
that one hours of groceries and errands
I've tried breaking down minute by
minute what I do in a day yeah
especially when my life was simpler it's
really refreshing to understand where
you waste a lot of time yeah and uh what
you enjoy doing like how many minutes it
takes to be happy doing the thing that
makes you happy and how many minutes it
takes to be productive and you realize
there's a lot of hours in the day if you
spend it right yeah a lot of is wasted
yeah for me has been the the the biggest
battle for uh for the longest time is
finding stretches a time where I can
deeply focus into really really deep
work just like zoom in and completely
focused cutting away all the
distractions yeah me too that's the
battle Yeah it's unpleasant it's
extremely unpleasant we need to fly to
an island you know make a a man cave
Island where we can just everybody can
just goat and for a week you know just
get shit done make new
projects yeah yeah but man they called
me psychopath for this because it says
like one hours of sex hugs love you know
man I had to write something you know
and they were like ah this guy
psychopath he plans his sex know in
specific hour like bro I don't but have
a counter for hugs yeah exactly like
yeah like click click click H it's it's
just a numerical representation of what
life is yeah
it's like one of those like when you
draw out how many weeks you have in a
life oh dude this is like dark yeah man
don't want to look that too much yeah
man how many times you see your parents
Jesus like man yeah it's scary man
that's right it might be only you know a
handful more times yeah man you just
look at the math of it if you see him
once a year or twice a year yeah
FaceTime today yeah
yeah I mean it that that's like dark
when
you see somebody you like like seeing
like a friend that's on the outskirts of
your friend group and you realize like
well I haven't really seen him for like
three years so like how many more times
do we have that we see each other yeah
do you believe that like friends just
slowly disappear from your life like
they kind of your friend group evolves
right so like it does it does like you
don't want to there's a problem with
Facebook you get all these old friends
from school like when you were 10 years
old back when Facebook started like you
don't really you would friend them and
then you're like why are we in touch
again just keep the memories there you
know like it's different life now yeah I
have you know I don't that might be a
guy thing or I don't know there's
certain friends I have that like we
don't interact often but we're still
friends yeah like I every time I see
him I think it's because we have a
foundation of many shared experiences
and many memories like I it's like
nothing has changed like we've been
almost like we've been talking every day
even if we haven't talked for a year
yeah so that like yeah that's deep yeah
so that so I don't have to be
interacting with them for them to be in
a friend group and then there's some
people I interact with a lot so it's it
it depends but there's just this network
of good human beings that
can I have like a real love for them and
I I can always count on them if like if
any of them called me in the middle of
the night I'll get rid of a body you
know I'm
there I like how that's a different
definition of friendship but it's true
it's true true friend you've become more
and more famous recently how's that uh
affect you it's not recently it's this
gradual thing right like it keeps keeps
going and uh and I also don't know why
it keeps going does that put pressure on
you to cuz you're pretty open on Twitter
and you're just like basically building
shit in the open yeah and just not
really caring if it's too technical if
it's any of this just being out there
does it put pressure on you as you
become more popular to be a little bit
more like collected and man I think the
opposite right like because the people I
follow are interesting because they say
whatever they think and they and they
ship or whatever it's so boring that
people start tweeting only about one
topic yeah I don't know anything about
their personal life I want to know about
their personal life like you do podcast
you ask about LIF stuff about
personality that's the most interesting
part of like business or sports like
what's the behind this for the athlete
right behind the entrepreneur that's
interesting stuff to be human yeah like
you you share that you know like I Shar
the Tweet went too far but like we were
cleaning the toilet because the toilet
was clogged you know but like it's just
real stuff because Jansen hang the
Nvidia guy he says he started cleaning
toilets you know that was cool you you
tweeted something about the the Denny's
thing I forget yeah it was recent Nvidia
was started in a Denny Diner uh table
and you made it somehow profound you're
almost yeah this one this one uh Nvidia
three $3 trillion company was started in
a Denny's an American Diner people need
a third space to work on their laptops
to build the next billion or trillion
dollar company what's the first and
second space the home office and the in
between the island I guess yeah the
island yeah you need a space to like
congregate man and I found history on
this so 400 years ago in the coffee hous
of Europe the like the Scientific
Revolution the enlightenment happened
because they would go to coffee houses
they would sit there they would drink
coffee and they would work they would
work they would write or they would and
they would do debates and they would
organize Marine routes right they would
do all the stuff in coffee houses in
Europe in France in Austria in UK in
Holland so we would always be going to
we were always going to cafes to to work
and to have serendipitous conversations
with other people and start businesses
and stuff and when I like you asked me
to come on here and we flew to America
and the first thing I realized was that
I've been to America before but but we
were in this Cafe and like there's a lot
of laptops everybody's working on
something and I made I took this photo
um and then when you're in Europe like
large parts of Europe now you can't you
cannot use a laptop anymore it's like no
laptop which I understand but that is to
you a fundamental place to create shit
is in that natural organic uh co-working
space of a coffee for a lot of people a
lot of people have very small homes and
co-working spaces are kind of boring
they're kind they're not very they're
private they're not
serendipitous kind of boring um cafes
are amazing because they random people
can come in and ask you what are you
working on or you know and not just left
those people are also having
conversations like they did 400 years
ago debates or whatever things are
happening and man I understand the the
Aesthetics of it like it's like oh
startup bro shipping his uh bullshit
startup you know
like but there's something more there
like there's people actually making
stuff making new companies that the
society benefits from like we're we're
benefiting from Nvidia I think as the US
GDP for sure is benefiting from Nvidia
European GDP could benefit if we build
more companies and I feel in Europe
there's this Vibe and this you have to
connect things but not not allowing
laptops and cafes is kind of like part
of the vibe which is like yeah we're not
really here to work we're here to like
enjoy life I agree with this Anthony
bdan like this tweet was quote tweeted
Anthony Bain photo with him with
cigarettes and a coffee in France and he
said that's this is what cafes are for I
agree but there is some element of like
entrepreneurship like you have to allow
people to dream big and work their ass
off to to towards that dream and then
feel each other's energy as they
interact with that's one of the things I
liked in Silicon Valley when I was uh
working there is like the cafes like
there's a bunch of dreamers that there
you can make fun of them for like
everybody thinks they're going to build
a trillion dollar company but like yeah
and it's a not everybody wins 99% of
people will be bullshit but they working
their ass off yeah they're doing
something and and you need to past this
startup bro like oh it's startup Lev no
it's not it's people making cool shit
yeah and this will benefit you because
this will create jobs for your com your
your country in your region and I think
in Europe um that's a big problem like
we have a very
anti- um entrepreneurial mind dream big
and build shit this is really inspiring
this is pin tweet of yours all the
projects that you've tried and the ones
that
succeeded has very few mute life it was
for Twitter to mute uh to share the mute
list your uh mute words fire calculator
no more Google maker rank how much is my
site project worth climate finder ideas
AI Airline list still runs but it's
doesn't make money Airline list like
compares the safety of Airlines CU I was
nervous to fly so I was like let's
collect all the data on crashes for all
the airplanes BC cable nice that's
awesome uh Village NORAD gear 3D and
virtual reality Dev play play my inbox
like you mentioned there's a lot of
stuff yeah man I'm trying to find some
embarrassing tweets of yours you can go
to the highlights tab it has all the
like the good shit kind of there you go
this was Dubai POV building an AI
startup wow you're a real
influencer and people copy this photo
now and they they change the screenshots
it becomes like a meme of course you
know
this is good this how Dubai looks it's
insane that's beautiful architecture
wise it's crazy the story is behind this
story behind for sure so this is about
the European economy where like European
economy landscape is ran by dinosaurs
and today I studied it so I can produce
you with my evidence 80% of top EU
companies were founded before 1950 only
36% of top us companies were founded
before 1950 yeah so the median founding
of companies in US is something like
1960 and IM Med median the top companies
right and IM median in Europe is like
1900 or something yeah so it's um here
1914 and 1963 so there a 50-year
difference it's a good um representation
of the very thing you were talking about
the diff difference in the cultures
entrepreneurial Spirit of the peoples
but Europe used to be entrepreneurial
like there was companies found in 1800
1850 1900 it flipped like around 1950
where America took the lead and uh and I
guess my point is like I hope that
Europe gets back to because I'm European
I hope that Europe gets back to being an
entrepreneurial culture where they build
big companies again because right now
the all the old dinosaur companies
control the economies they're lobbying
with the government they're Europe is
also that's like they're infiltrated
with the government where they create so
much regulation like I think it's called
regulatory capture right where it's very
hard for a newcomer to join to enter an
industry because there's too much
regulation so actually regulation is
very good for big companies because they
can follow it I can't follow it right if
I want to start a AI startup in Europe
now I cannot because there's an AI
regulation that makes it very
complicated for me I probably need to
get like notaries involved I need to get
certificates
licenses um whereas in America I can
just open my laptop I can started AI
started right now um mostly you know
what do you think about eak effective
accelerationist movement man you had
Beth jzos on I I love Beth jzos and um
he's amazing and I think iok is is very
needed to similarly create a more
positive uh outlook on the future like
because people people have been very
pessimistic um about Society about the
future of society um you know climate
change all this stuff uh eok is like is
a positive outlook in the future it's
like technology can make us you know we
need to spend more energy we should find
ways to of course get like clean energy
but we need to spend more energy to make
cooler stuff and you know go into space
and build more technology that can
improve society and we shouldn't shy
away from technology technology can be
the answer for many things yeah build
more don't spend so much time on uh
fear-mongering and cautiousness and all
this kind of stuff some is okay some was
good but most of the time should be
spent on building and creating on like
and doing so unapologetically it's a
it's a refreshing reminder what made
United States great is all the builders
like you said the entrepreneurs like we
can't forget that in in all the sort of
discussions of how things could go wrong
with technology and all this kind of
stuff yeah it goes SC look at China
China is now at the stage of like
America what like 1900 or something
they're building rapidly like insane and
obviously China has massive problems but
that comes with the whole thing that
comes America and this beginning also
massive problems right
um
but I think it's very very dangerous for
a country or region like Europe to you
you you get to this point where you're
kind of complacent you're kind of
comfort
and then you know you can either go this
or you can go this way right you're from
here you go like this and then you can
go this or this I think you should go
this way and uh OB yeah go up and and
uh I think it's the problem is the the
the Mind culture so eok I made eok which
is like the European kind of version um
I made like hoodies and stuff so a lot
of people wear like this this make your
grade again head um I made it red first
but it became too like Trump so now it's
more like you're being blue you know
make Europe great
again all right
um okay so you had a incredible
life very successful built a lot of cool
stuff so what advice would you give to
young people about how to do the same
man I would listen to like nobody just
do what you think is good and follow
your heart right like uh everybody peer
presses you into doing stuff you don't
want to do and like they tell you like
parents or family and society and tell
you but like try your own thing you know
because it probably it might work out
you can you can steer the ship you know
it probably doesn't work out immediately
you probably go into very bad times like
I did as well relatively right but in
the end if you're smart about it you can
make things work and you you can create
your own little life of things as you
did you know as I did and I think that
should be more promoted like Do Your Own
Thing there's space in economy and in
society for do your own thing you know
yeah it's like um you know like little
Villages everybody would sell I would
sell bread you would sell meat every can
do their own little thing you don't need
to you know be a Normy as you say you
you you um you can you can be what you
really want to be you know and like go
all out doing that thing yeah you got to
go all out cuz if you do if you have
assets you cannot succeed you got you
need to go lean into the to the outcast
stuff lean into the um being different
and and just doing whatever it is that
you want to do right you got a whole
asset yeah
yet this was an incredible conversation
it was an honor to finally meet you it
was honor to be to talk to you and uh
keep doing your thing keep inspiring me
and uh the world with all the cool stuff
you're building thank you Matt thanks
for listening to this conversation with
Peter levels to support this podcast
please check out our sponsors in the
description and now let me leave you
with some words from Drew hon Dropbox
co-founder by the way I love
Dropbox anyway Drew said don't worry
about failure you only have to be right
once thank you for listening and hope to
see you next time