if I hate you that's great but if I have
a story to support that hate that's even
better uh one of your favorite words
Jihad that's my favorite hobbies it
doesn't matter now who do you vote into
power they will not listen to you they
would listen to the people who paid them
to be there when the military came in
people were walking to me like pointing
their fingers like don't speak about C
you don't speak about the Army huh we
love you now but don't you you don't
would like that so I called John was
like I don't know what to do and he said
the most interesting thing ever and say
if you're afraid of something make fun
about the fact that you're afraid of
it the following is a conversation with
bosam youf a legendary Egyptian American
comedian the so-called John Stewart of
the Middle East who fearlessly sazed
those in power even when his job and
life were on the line boss is a
beautiful human being it was truly a
pleasure for me to get to know him and
to have this fun fascinating and
challenging
conversation this is Alex Freedman
podcast to support it please check out
our sponsors in the description and now
dear friends here's bosam
Yousef your wife is half Palestinian and
I've heard you say they've been trying
to kill her but she keeps using the kids
as human Shields so have you considered
negotiating a ceasefire well the thing
is every day every minute of the day in
a married life is a negotiation
everything can blow up into a fullscale
war starting from a simple sentence like
good morning what should we do with the
kids today what should we do with that
piece of furniture any sentence can lead
you to heaven or to hell in the same
time so you do negotiate with terrorists
oh yeah yeah 100% yeah and for her I am
her terrorist too so it's equal
Terrorist on both sides on a more
serious note when you found out about
the attacks of October 7th what went
through your mind if I'm allowed to use
a curse word I I was like as many as
possible I like oh part of my
stand-up comedy is I describe a
situation where I was in a restaurant
with producers and there was a bombing
two blocks away in Chelsea New York in
206 and of course this is the like damn
what's going to happen to us now and and
and there's like two different reaction
there's like the white reaction which is
like oh my God I hope nobody is heard
this is terrible I hope everybody's okay
and there's the Arab reaction what's his
name what's is his name what is the name
you know because you know what's going
to come it's kind
of I was scared what's going to really
happen in that area and it's like oh my
God it's going to be horrible and the
way that it was
reported I I didn't know how to handle
this so I basically I went into hiding
for a few days 3 4 days and I talked
about Piers Morgan uh Team talking to me
two times three times I like no I can't
how can I you defend that how can you
defend the rape the decapitated babies
and whatever and then I started kind of
looking in the news a little bit and
then I started seeing people coming on
the shows and saying things that I know
as an Arab as a Muslim as someone from
that region that it's not
true but I didn't know how to how what
to say how to say it so I said by the
third time when they asked me I said
like fine put me on and I went there it
was more of a figurativ speaking a
suicide mission
and uh because it's a l lose situation I
can I can lose stuff in Hollywood I can
I even I remember my manager like
Bess be careful I mean are you sure you
want to do it are you my managers was
like please don't do it please don't do
it and on the other side if I don't
perform well whatever well means I'm
going to be rejected by my own people so
it's a it was a lose-lose situation
because whatever I say it will never be
enough and whatever I say will not be
good enough and uh I was going into
there and I I felt that I was going into
a trance for the 33 minutes that I was
on the on that interview for the first
time you blacked out I blacked out I
blacked out and a lot of people ask me
is the earpiece was that a bit when the
earpiece kept falling it's like no it
was really falling off and it
disconnected and I had to save it
because I cannot see them all I can hear
I can just hear them and I could
expecting at any time okay B thank you I
like I I I was fighting for every second
to say words to put stuff in there yeah
for people who don't know this is your
conversation interview with Pierce
Morgan and you could see I couldn't see
I was just like the lens with the camera
and I just a real dream or nightmare
yeah hello W like hello W like hi and it
could end at any moment your career and
everything everything yeah yeah so what
was the drive that got you to actually
do it to overcome that fear multiple
things first of all I don't want to say
it's just my wife's family because my
wife's family has always been there but
this time was different the the the
bombing the attack they they usually one
of those people that they are away of
everything when whatever happened in
Gaza they are always in safe places but
this time it seems that there was no
place safe and already we heard about
like two three of the of the cousins and
the uh uncles already lost their home so
this was too much so I I I wanted to say
something for those people because I
know that you know I I made I made one
of the jokes that I made about like oh
you know it's Hassen her cousin he's a
loser he's a doctor he's a doctor and he
every time a hospital was bombed we were
worried about him so I wanted to to say
that because I felt that these are this
is a family that I have never seen in my
life I've never she she actually hardly
saw an uncle or two because you know
they cannot
leave but I I said like I need to speak
at least I do something for those
extended family that I have never known
but also
because when when when P Morgan team
called me a couple of times said okay
let's let's see what's going on in the
show and I just watch the stuff and the
lies and the one ided reporting that
made my blood boil and then I thought
like what why am I what am I afraid of
I'm afraid of if I say something I can
lose my career like wait a minute but
that was the reason why I left Egypt I
said wait I left I came to United States
I came to the land of the free where I
can say anything I want and yet I have
limitation of what to say I mean I
thought we left that behind I mean
what's happening and I understand I
understand the connection of how
sensitive it is when you you speak about
Israel and all of the readymade
accusations but as a as an Arab as a
Muslim I don't react the same when you
talk about Saudi Arabia or Iran or Egypt
or any of them it's like hey you you
want you want to diss some of these
countries I'll I'll do that with you
because I have strong opinions about
what happened and I already been
expressing them but when I talk that's
why I and I speak and and there's a lot
of Jewish people who come to my show and
they understand that they understand
that the separation
but that kind of a grouping of
blackmailing people and saying and not
saying what they have in their mind it
is that kind of like one of the things
that kind of like push push me to go on
the show the thing that was bothering
you was it what was being said or how it
was being said both because there are
lies which is usually in the media but
there was the total disregard of
humanity you talk a lot about in your
show about human suffering and I felt
that here the human suffering was not
equal I felt that's why I came up with
this like what's the exchange rate today
what's the exchange rate today there's
there's of course it's terrible to see
anybody die but when I feel that like is
it isn't our life not worth anything
yeah you had a chart um to crypto from
an invest you analyze it from an
investing perspective of course in the
dark
and you were saying that a certain year
was a good year yeah 2014 2014 was a
good year for in invest me purposes and
also to to refer to the to family member
that you called the loser you were
saying that uh you you called him had a
conversation with him and he keeps
saying that he's not using anybody for
human Shields and you called him a loser
what do you you can't even give a job a
liar he lied to us because I have to
believe but this is what the one thing
it's like it's also one of the things
like how it was said it was stuff that
I've been hearing I don't know what what
turned on on my head but it's stuff that
I've been hearing all my life from the
media Israel warns civilians before
bombing them and that's okay but that's
not okay Israel is trying to minimize
the civilians but killing them anyway
and that's okay but that's not okay so
it is kind of like the indoctrination
that we've been hearing as if it is okay
and then suddenly it's not yeah there's
a kind
of several layers of almost
sometimes hiding the obvious horror of
the
situation with kind of politeness and
all this kind of stuff just the basic
value of human life that said it's a
difficult situation it is it is what
would you do if you were Israel BB
called you aome big fan big fan of your
comedy mhm um first of all would you
hang up right away would you hear him
out no I definitely hear him out like
that like wait a minute that's Mater
that's
that's material man I like so n called
me I was sitting with my family just
like my phone like oh
nyaho yeah just shows up that way I mean
what would you do what would you do in
the situation to answer this question we
need to understand how Israel thinks
there is an incredible speech given by
gon Levy the famous Israeli repor
ands and he describes a situation where
he was in the West Bank and there was a
checkpoint
and in that checkpoint there was an
ambulance with a Palestinian patient and
it was there sitting for an hour and a
half not moving and then he went to talk
to the soldiers like guys why are you
not letting them go it's like I let them
go like and and then he told them
imagine if he was your father and the
soldier stood up like what these are
pigs these are not humans so when you
tell me what would you do if Israel
would do it really needs to we need to
ask how does Israel look at the
Palestinian and view the Palestinians
because they do look at them less than
human and there is an incredible talk uh
by mior Meyer he was a holocaust
Survivor and he said I learned in aitz
when I was there in the concentration
camp that in order for a group of
dominant group of people to dehumanize
another group they need first to
dehumanize
themselves and Israel looks at
Palestinians as lesser people as lesser
beings as some people who are
dispensable and the way that they treat
them is that they don't really care
about like that's why that the exchange
rate thing so for me if I am Israel I it
will be like what would you do if you're
the United States in the time of the
Native Americans they were killing
people with the millions when you
dehumanize a group of people you really
don't care so if I was Israel I would do
exactly what Israel is doing right now
because there's no one is holding me
accountable there's no one stopping me
and I can get whatever I want throughout
my history through violence I think a
lot of the things you just said are a
tiny bit slightly exaggerated so let me
let me try let's lete try so not
everybody in Israel of so let's let's
look
at um several groups so people in
government IDF
soldiers and citizens that are neither
of those
and not everybody of any of those uh
sees Palestinians as less than human
just some percentage so what percentage
is that in your sense it's the people
who have the power so it's mostly the
focus of your commentary when you say
people in Israel you really mean the
people in power the people have in power
but but but as much as like I of course
I mean the people in power because when
I speak about even when I speak about
America I speak about people in power
when I speak about Egypt I speak the
people of power because like I can't
really talk about the 100 million people
in Egypt or the 11 million people in
Israel of course not there are people
who go in and they demonstrate against
Netanyahu and they want him out of the
government but we have to admit that the
isra society at a whole have moved quite
bit to the right and has been has been
like many extreme and you know what
happens when you go to the right or you
go to the most extreme the other person
go to the most extreme and extremism
breeds extremism so thank you for the
clarification but like I really meant
with the people of power when people
criticize the United States States for
going in Iraq of course I'm not
criticizing citizens but you made
another point which is an interesting
point and it's very difficult to see in
the heart of people but I wonder if you
look at the average Palestinian and the
average Israeli and when they look at
the other do they have some hate in
their heart well everybody probably has
some what is that amount you know when
you look at a person that looks
different than you how much hate is
there it depends on what do the living
situation of each person so in the
Berlin Film Festival just like a few
couple of weeks ago there was an Israeli
and a Palestinian receiving an award
together and the Israeli director said
we're going to go back to Israel he's
going to go to the West Bank he will
have no rights and I will have full
living rights these people manag to work
together and be friends and they have
empathy to each other now the
average
Palestinian it's a very difficult
question because is it the Palestinian
in the diaspora or the Palestinian in
Gaza or the diaspora in the West Bank or
the one in the citizen of as a citizen
of Israel who still have less right than
a romal citizen of Israel as a
Jew and it really depends if I am there
are people in Arabs in Israel who are
having a great life and there are people
Arabs who are having a a miserable life
but definitely people that living in G
or in the West Bank is kind of like on
the lower tier of the living conditions
now let's talk about the hate what does
that Palestinian see from the
Israeli the Palestinian see oppression
limitation of movement limitation of
Freedom they have and then when there's
something happens you see the full force
coming in destroying their home taking
away members of his family there will be
absolutely no reason for him to love the
other the Israeli because he you know he
doesn't have the power but he lives
under his government all he sees is the
rocket or whatever but like he sees the
reaction and he doesn't see what
happened to those and as humans we are
selfish we see what really affects us as
humans and I cannot even imagine what it
would be like to live as a Palestinian
and I'm not even talk about Gaza because
everybody talks about Gaza but let me
give you an example and I'm not going to
talk about the 12,000 kids killed in
Gaza let's talk about just like the four
weeks in the West
Bank March 4th Amar Nar H1 sitting next
to his father shot in a while he's
sitting in a car next to his father by
the IDF solders Muhammad zad 13 years
old March 3rd shot in front of a un
School while in season with his friends
Muhammad ganim age 15 March 2nd he shot
while standing in front of a St front
during a night trade February 23rd s Jal
he he was killed by a drone fire
February 22nd F San killed while
standing in front of the top of a Red
Cross
building uh Nel Nel zad February 14th
Valentine's Day killed a shot in the
head while leaving school February 11th
Muhammad katur US citizens killed while
being in a park car and mu Shams
February 9th killed right in front of
his home because a military
came reversing back to him and then
somebody opened the door shot him and
leave this is a daily life of people in
the West Bank what is the the
justification that IDF
provides
terrorism terrorism or I don't know I
mean you cannot really say like human
Shields but they would say like they
were throwing rocks there was a guy who
went on Chris Rock and he said like his
son a US citizen would kill and like
they were throwing rocks so we killed
him even when they were throwing rocks
you kill him but the thing is you see
this is how easy for them to get rid of
Palestines I mean I love like I I was I
had to say I prepared a little bit for
the podcast because you are in Tech so
and I I am ignorant in tech there is a
movie called The LAB it is uh directed
by an Israeli director called utam
Feldman and he talks about
how the the military uh uh industry in
Israel is very
Advanced and what is really mindboggling
is in that movie he shows how the
military tests its weapons in the field
in urban areas on
Palestinians it it it is it is
heartbreaking you know as a doctor
there's five stages of Trials there is
like uh there's Discovery preclinical
clinical and then
uh market and then postmarket evaluation
by the FDA the FDA value approval and
then FDA post Market five just to take a
pill and you go in and and he interviews
people as like where did you test this
they test it in the field so when when
you just like when human life is so is
so cheap and it is so
indispensable it made me it gave me a
vis reaction because you know we as hum
this has been actually the the the state
of humanity Humanity have lived and
survived and th by actually killing each
other but there was kind of like we were
remotely we were removed from it people
in Greece didn't know what the Alexander
the Great was doing he was killing and
paging like we call him the great
because but he was killing he was he was
conquering he was invading Julius Cesar
all of the greats he would doing but
killing was difficult killing had to
have some sort you have to be with your
enemy then you go back catapults then
cannons then a little bit back from and
then you're kind of like starting
remotely now you're killing people
behind the screen with a button with a
push of a button you know a lot of
people say terrorism they killed you
with a knife killed one person with a
knife shot you that's terrorism but if
you fly A $64 million F-16 and you drop
up an a84 bomb that CA $16,000 that's
not terrorism because it's remote you're
behind the screen so what happened what
Israel is doing it is removing itself
like America too drones and then when
you push someone to be in to they always
about bombing them to the stone
ages what happens when the screens and
the all of the obstacles that you have
been put between you and those people
that you have treated them this way when
this is a breach and you come face to
face you will come face to face with
what you have created yeah there's a lot
of interesting things you just said so
one is the methodology of killing if you
want to look at some horrific large
scale killing people of talk about the
Holocaust but that's visceral you can
look at hollmore by Stalin where the
murder is through starvation by by by
Churchill in India in Churchill in India
uh and the Great Leap Forward by Ma y so
starvation is a thing we don't often
think of it as murder because it's quiet
it's slow and the interesting thing
about starvation is that the people
don't complain as they're dying because
they're exhausted MH that's one and the
other is the value of human life it does
seem that every culture has a unequal
valuation of human life so those two
things combined create a
complicated um military landscape of the
world yes but the thing is is that how
we look at technology as the Savior as
talk about how AI disrupt will disrupt
will disrupt will disrupt and now if you
go you talk about like going to the West
Bank the people in the West Bank walk
and they don't see humans they see
people shouting them from Towers or
behind the screens or doing and they
have like Biometrics that is developed
by basil system like that's done by HP
or or Google and Amazon who are like
part of project Nimbus and and you see
IND
division developing all of this like
metric and surveillance and all of that
stuff and then you have like something
like the gospel that like people have
actually said that that the gospel can
actually create a Target list using Ai
and give you a green yellow or a red to
go go ahead and now ai is not just
disrupting the market it's disrupting
our humanity and it is we became so
comfortable killing people from afar
killing people with a push of the button
and now it is it is like it's like
dating apps you know when you when you
swipe left and right you it's like oh
right it becomes so like cheap it's not
like meeting someone it's like oh it's
like a lot of fish in the sea same with
AI boom 500 people killed boom they
killed it's so easy it's so easy it's so
easy and then it's so far removed from
you so when you put these people in this
condition you have literally put them in
a different Universe than
yours you are behind in your air
conditioned screens like pushing them
blowing up a un a university it's
amazing but then you meet the the what
you have done that you meet the
Frankenstein that you have created and
then people are like oh look what they
do to us you just gave me this image of
a uh a dating app from hell where
leaders are just sitting there and kind
of swiping left invade
destroy just Bor puppet
government yeah and then turn off the
phone go to sleep uh so I got you know I
traveled to the West Bank and I
mentioned to you Offline that I really
loved the people there just um you I've
met a bunch of people like that in in
Eastern Europe where I grew
up uh yeah like the flamboyant the big
personalities all of that U I also met
uh a person who's in charge of a refugee
camp who was shoping IDF
solder and um I'm not sure the words he
said are important as the consequences
of the thing that you mentioned which is
the Deep hate in his eyes mhm that was
didn't feel reparable at all it was pain
it was like a foundation of pain and on
top of that a hatred and it was like wow
this is what you kill you kill one
person that's is what you
create because we have kind of like a
front row seat to what's happening we we
think we're in it but we can't really
grasp it I mean people like oh we just
going to go in get Hamas out and we're
going to get them back in m and what
about the people get back in how do you
think they would look at
you what have you
created what have you
done my show in Egypt was all about
propaganda it's all about the use of
words words are very important the
decapitated babies were not
chosen randomly because you see it it
plants certain image in your brain
imagine if you're going in what a baby
can do it can smile cry and poop that's
it is absolutely no threat so when you
tell people 40 decapitated babies they
are so animalistic they didn't see the
babies women raped of course he's anamal
to do that and they would go through
that and they would what was very
frustrating about the conversation is
the Gish Galloping the Gish Galloping
throwing you see the dist ractions you
see what happens like like what's the
proportionate response can Israel defend
itself do you condemn Hamas does Israel
has the right to exist decapitated
babies raped women why don't the Arab
countries take them why don't the musl
Muslims kill Muslims look what happened
in Yemen in Syria in Iraq like see see
how they kind of distract you they throw
little things at you so you don't know
what to do oh the honor the unn
anti-semitic October 7th October 7th
October 7th and then suddenly you are
distracted and pulled into discussing
all of these little things and you
discussing what's happening right now it
is basically stalling giving them time
to do what they do so there's uh there's
some degree to the propaganda the so the
beheaded babies and all this kind of
stuff
that is so over the top that it shuts
down actual conversation about actual
wrongs war crimes on both sides M so
it's overstating it to where everyone on
social media and everywhere in the press
and everywhere is arguing almost become
desensitized to actual horrors of death
which are more mundane they're not so
dramatic as beheaded babies because
people people a baby is shot but
decapitated babies there's like a knife
blade that goes into the skin the
trachea the flesh the spine decapitated
like how like you can just like he's
dead no you go in this is the hate so
much hate and you know that's why you
have made me
laugh at the darkest you're such a
beautiful person your dark humor is just
wonderful but but you see this happened
to Jews before remember blood liel where
did the blood liel come from it come
from these rumors that Jews suck baby's
blood this is what they did to them
that's what's in the cup
exactly that's a very delicious baby
delicious baby but but this is what you
do you you tell people something and it
happened with the Native Americans when
they were here when when they went and
they wipe a whole tribe so and and and
and and Jewish people one of the like
the minorities that were persecuted and
had this used against them for a very
long time and it is terrible and it's
terrifying that's been used again so I I
just did a very lengthy debate on Israel
and
Palestine and the really painful thing
from that there's two historians it was
it was deep it was thorough it was
fascinating
but in constantly asking about sources
of Hope or Solutions there was none
there was a there was a sense of like a
really dark sense of it's hopeless from
both sides it's
hopeless uh so you know I Look to
You for for
source for a source of Hope do you have
is is there any hope here Solutions
shortterm long-term Obama have kind of
summarized this beautifully in his book
He said the reason why the Israeli
Palestinian conflict is so chronic is
one side have so much power and the
other side have absolutely no power and
that's what one he said he said like you
have Israel that fa basically don't
listen to us because they are supported
by people who are bigger than the
president bigger than Administration
they know that they can I mean like you
OB like Netanyahu was caught on tape
many times saying like he's basically
like belittling Americans like I we we
control 80% of the population we don't
care they this has kind of like non
chalen kind of like uh we we have
them and there's nothing really that
compels Israel to give up anything
because at the end of the day what is
compromise compromise is like I give
something you give something Israel is
not giving anything and they project
that on you so for example how many
times have we heard like oh Palestinians
were giving like four five 6 seven 15
chances and they said no to them and yet
when you read the history that's not the
case at all like for
example in 20 the whole idea about like
Arafat walked away from Oso that didn't
happen and there is an Incredible video
by you know uh what's his name Joe SC
scoro with Misha and they were hosting
her father uh brazinski he was the uh
National Security adviser and Jo carabo
said like well you know like Arafat left
the oo C and the Palestinians and then
bis are like this is like embarrassingly
shallow
it's like listen what happened was there
was a lot of catches on the oso Court it
was very unfair to the Palestinian so AR
said like I agree but I need to take it
to the Arab capitals and and and they
went to ins and they went to Sharm they
came to Egypt and he and H Barak went to
there and then bar left because there
was election and he lost theel Shon came
and it was Destro this is one of the
reason why people it is it's kind of
like
facts don't matter as much as what is
the narrative that is being controlled
but what what were the biggest barriers
to peace there do do you think it's
fundamentally leaders don't want a two
St solution or was there nuanced small
differences that if solved could have
led to us to two State solution I mean
there was a maybe there was a certain
point when the Israeli leaders were
more open to compromise but I can't say
that because each time Israel gives back
land it it has to be after some use of
force the the 1973 War the Ina the first
and second the the the the casualties in
Kaza they never give up land willingly
and because of Peace because if I have
that much military I can do whatever I
want why would I give up anything I have
that much power why would America or
China give everything if they're so
powerful and especially if they are have
this kind of open check from the United
States so it is it is really
about what can push Israel to give up
something because you are so much
stronger than me what could compel you
to give up
something and this is why the whole
thing about like trying to equalize
Palestinians and the Israeli state and
government it doesn't make any sense so
what is the source of hope you know John
Stewart who will'll talk about it from
many angles uh somebody you admire a
friend uh he proposed a two-state
solution look look look to the comedians
for Hope yes well everybody's talking
about the two-state contion but Israel
has said many times on nyaho and Ben
like there there's going to be no State
solutions they in the past is like even
even neali Benet he came in on the on on
hard talk us like yeah maybe in the past
we wanted two State Solutions but like
look every time we give them land they
kill us so no State solution and they
openly saying it that's perhaps rhetoric
rhetoric that is supported by action
because look at what they're doing in
the the West Bank that you said they are
cutting it illegal settlement me peac
mealing it so how is if you have an
intention at all to give them anything
why would you keep do keep doing this
and you've called it a bunch of little
Gaza yes it's a nice little picture of
what's Happening peace mealing itum
because it is what happened in the past
4 months the Palestinians have been
micro doing on it for a very long time
little by little little by little and we
would shout every time when it gets too
much and then we shut down and then
little by little but this time it was
hard it was hard to see the
blatant oppression and the word
said maybe the Hamas Ministry of the
health are giving us the bad numbers
maybe it's just human and I I I laugh
there's 13,000 babies killed does that
mean that there
13,000 military Target hiding in their
diapers because it is so it doesn't make
any sense to kill that maybe just like
oh oops is out of our head it's hard to
know what to do with those numbers I
mean I just one baby is enough but you
know what happens when you hear so many
numbers numbers become numbers and you
become so desensitized
and this is why there's a difference
between
saying 13,000 Palestinian kid did it's
like milain an Israeli baby 10 month old
she was killed in her crib and this is
what we hear from CNN we never hear a
story about a Palestinian kid that's why
thank you for giving me the space for
saying the names of the Palestinian CH
children that were killed just for four
weeks do like it's it's
because humans needs context they need
depth they need like a a 3D look at what
they can look at but if you just get
numbers oh they don't mean anything is
there some degree to where both
leaderships Hamas PA Palestinian
Authority Israel all want
war like Perpetual War to to remain in
power there is that's that's an
interesting uh
question but I mean let's admit
something the Arab regimes in the in the
area have actually used the problem of
Palestine in order to stay in power in
order to take get excuses like have this
enemy and Israel the the Israeli
government has used that too and maybe
the Palestinians
but but my problem with when going into
discussion this is that the the two
sides are not equal they're not equal in
power they're not equal in influence and
they're not equal in international
supports especially with the United
States so Palestinians can the people
who have made changes in history were
the people with power the people who
would have the ability to change things
and the Palestinians cannot really
change and what what can they change
well is that true though with uh how
much support the Palestinian people have
so just like you said there's a lot of
Arab states that are uh that will voice
their Pro Palestinian position in order
to distract from their the own
corruption and abuses of power in their
own countries but you know I don't think
if you look globally there's a complete
asymmetry of power and public opinion
here maybe in the press in the west but
if you look globally but do they have
the same kind of weapons that the Israel
have so literally power no there's a
major asymmetry of literal power some
money to their leaders does that make
any difference I mean and also when you
say Palestinian Authority which
authority are you talking about Hamas or
the Palestinian Authority who has been
kind of a domesticated kind of like a
puppy for the Palestinian who basically
have been an informant for the OWN on on
their own people and this is the the
thing also that kind of like really
pissed me off when I was hearing the
thing about about they think like Hamas
Hamas Hamas Hamas like we have Netanyahu
on tape confessing that he supported
Hamas gave him money in order to cause
factions in the in in between the
Palestinians so it's just like it
doesn't make you just told me this m you
just told me this you just told me
support H like but ham like what I mean
to which degree does n yahu
represent the Israeli people is is a is
a real question to which point does
Trump or Biden represent the American
people and to which degree does Hamas
represent the Palestinian people does
none of these represent it but who have
the power in order to make the decisions
it really comes down to that well who
does have the power are are you you're
giving a lot of power to Israel
yeah but the the Arab League what should
Hames do what do you think we should
Hames do continue doing what a charter
says which is trying to destroy Israel
and the role of the Palestinian people
is to overthrow Hamas and get a more
moderate leadership probably and the
role of the Israeli people is to vote
out this right-wing
government and elect a more moderate
leader so that there's a chance at peace
with two moderate leaders so before h
even got to control 2006 Gaza there was
AEL Chiron in 2000 MH and we all know
what happened and I Shon kind of like
had made came up with this amazing
policy of like breaking people's uh kids
bones in the in so he baraki was also
like I mean which one is moderate me I
think is Hamas is a product of what
happened I mean we can if if there was
no aperti in in in South Africa there
will be no NFC there will be no nson
Mandela if there was no Nazis in in in
Paris there will be no French Resistance
and I'm not saying that and and again
I'm not I I would don't want to be in a
put in a position to defend Hamas or
anybody because you know what that
entails
but there are those are like Hamas again
not defending them they went into
October 7th what was their what what
they why why did they did that like
release our hostages the people in
prison because if you're talking about
people who were kidnapped Israel kidnaps
people every single day and when they
had that the first Exchange in November
4th Israel Le 400 people 3/4 of them
were women and children why are those
people in prison there's one in four
kids that are in prison that stay in
solitary confinement which is by
international law a form of torture and
you're putting kids through that is it
possible so first of all ceasefire yes
and longer term is it possible for Arab
states and the United States to get
together and with
power through diplomacy en force a
solution it's a very very ideal solution
but you know and I know that the Arab
states don't really have the power all
of the powers are in the hands of
America they have the power see I would
I think they have the power I don't
maybe they don't want to use it they
don't well that's maybe because there's
a benefit like the dark the dark sense I
have is that a lot of people win from
the suffering that Palestinians are
going through because they can point to
that and distract from definitely def
corruption in their own States and then
obviously Iran can benefit also from the
same kind of dynamic uh distracting
from the uh the authoritarian nature of
their regime definitely but what is the
core of the problem here is it the Arab
states using the suffering or the
actually the the the suffering itself
and the suffering comes from people
being displaced their homes were taken
away there are 7 million Palestinians in
diaspora 7 Millions 7 million went out
there and now they're living in Canada
and America and Europe they had homes
there they cannot go back
to 1.7 million people of the people in
Gaza don't belong and Gaza they were
pushed from other places the the peace
meal thing of people are being you
know in in
Germany I'm I'm going to shift gear a
little bit it's going to be a little bit
of fun there is a there's a book that I
bought the rights to and I want to turn
it into a movie and i b i optioned the
right for two month for for two years in
March of last year before October 7th
after October 7th I bought the permanent
right mhm that book is
called the Muslim and the Jew and it is
written by an author called Ron and
Stein I read an article about this book
in
2016 and I chased that book for rights
for seven years I didn't have that much
money but I wanted that book and that
book was translated into English called
an and Dr helmy and that book tells the
incredible story under Nazi
Germany where
Arabs went and droves to Berlin in 1920s
after the first world war in the vi
Republic and they became doctors and
engineers and journalists for two
reasons number one it was dir cheap very
cheap because of the inflation and two a
lot of the Arab nationalists didn't want
to send their kids to to England or
France because they were the
occupiers and Dr helmy was the hero of
that he's an Egyptian doctor and that's
why I kind of like I personally kind of
connected with him and he went to scho
uh medical
school didn't find a place to live so he
lived in the Jewish ghetto like many
Arabs he didn't find a school to work at
a hospital to work in so he worked in a
Jewish
hospital so these are there was a lot of
ARS who lived with the the G and
actually the the first director of the
Berlin mosque with a Jewish con convert
who converted to Islam and he was a gay
activist I'm telling you this is like a
crazy story and this all this is not a
fiction story this not this is actually
like a nonfiction it's written actually
based on the statement the documents of
the Nazis
Ando Dr
heny he was in this hospital and the
Nazis came in and they killed and
tortured and beat up the Jewish doctor
and he made they made him the head of
his Department then he was now he's
surrounded by Nazi doctor they didn't
touch him because he was an Arab there
was kind of like a thing between Germany
and the Arabs because they wanted to
appease to them mhm in order to have
kind of
a a grassroot base in the Arab word
where he want to go next mhm and this is
why 1934 1935 the racial laws of
norenberg they had a name change first
they were called anti-semitic then they
changed into anti-jewish because also
Arabs were semetic so they wanted to
appease the Arabs now what happened to
Dr heli when that happened to him he
would go back to the
ghetto and he would see the apartments
next to him the Jewish apartment become
more and more and more flooded with
people because they were moving Jews and
pushing them and putting them
together pushing them to the side and
each H each plat each flat each
apartment instead of one family it would
have three four six seven families and
he was there b it home and he looked he
was he was there this is where the
people he grew up with he he he lived
with and now he's seeing that kind of
discrimination just because he was an
Arab and then he he started to kind of
like atone for like because he felt
responsible because he wasn't treated
the same way and he started to go and
treat Jewish people in their homes
because they couldn't go to hospitals
and then one family gave them his
daughter it's like this is Anna save her
he took her pretend ended to cheese his
niece put a hijab around her taught her
Arabic called her Nadia my not my
daughter's name by the way and they and
and he hid her in plain sights for seven
years in front of the Nazis as his nurse
it's an incredible story and then not
just that he went to prison and then he
went out and he formed with the Arab
people that was in prison with him a
network that saves 300
Jews you see that kind of story this is
the Jews that were living in the Arab
Ward I'm not saying that the Jews living
in the Arab Ward was living like an in
life of course as a kind of minority
they did not have like the full power of
their full you know advantages of the ru
that's that's normal but we had
this kind of a a
relationship
before Israel
was erected in
1948 and then of course everybody looked
at Jews at the time as fifth column and
of course the nationalistic regimes use
that and this is why what Biden
said was very dangerous when he said if
there's no Israel no Jew in the world
will feel safe you are the leader of the
Free World you are the president of the
United States do you mean that you're
telling me that the Jews in your country
in the United States of America are not
safe that is wrong on two levels number
one America historically and right now
is more safe to Jews in America in the
world than more than anybody they are
safer than the Jews in Israel they never
had PS or or the Holocaust like Europe
they live here a good life not perfect
life but they are better second of all
if you are the president and you're
telling that a group of people will not
feel safe unless there is a different
one you are already feeding into their
fifth column they're like you're Russian
you come from there and there is a group
of laws in the Russian Constitution that
says that Russia will protect its
citizens everywhere in the world what
happens if the president says like oh
you're Russians you're protected by own
country you don't belong here this is
terrible yeah you're right that's
actually an indirect threat yes uh you
know even saying musl
cannot feel safe in America or something
like this that means like a that's a
threat but what what would a Jewish
person in Beverly Hills or in in in in
Brooklyn feel if he hears that you are
already telling people you need to have
be loyal to Israel I mean Israel is a
foreign country I am sorry but Israel is
a foreign country Israel is a client
country that we sponsor and it is should
actually be responsible and held
accountable for what they do you
mentioned 1948 the nakba but before that
4139 41 to 45 the Holocaust what do you
do what do you do with the Holocaust
like what uh how do you incorporate into
the calculus oh yeah of what's oh it's
terrible of morality that that leads up
to the displacement of
700,000 uh Palestinians from the land
how do you work that out is terrible but
like I mean what the the the systemic
annihilation of Jewish people under the
Nazi that is like like a carefully
engineered thought for planned it was
terrible it was like kind of like the
human Ingenuity put into like something
that is very
evil but also it is not just not just
that happened we need we need to
remember that OT Frank the father of
annafran has his Visa Refugee Visa
rejected by the United States there's a
lot of people that were rejected by the
United States rejected by other European
countries and then they were pushed into
Palestine so you have to put yourself
between like and the Arabs okay we're
sitting here okay come and then all
right you don't have a a home or a
country anymore that that that that that
kills you I mean you see if I'm not an
Arab and you give me that kind of piece
of like terrible human trasy like oh my
God that is terrible but then I'm an
Arab is like yes I'm so sorry but what
do I have to do with that what why is
that my fault the the persecution of the
Jewish people have started since the the
eth and 9th century because they they
were like they were first
anti-christians they were like with
criminal immigrants they were like
conspirators this this this is this is
this is the the anti like people kind of
like as if Europe kind of like throw
anti-Semitism on us you understand that
like Henry Ford Henry Ford is one of the
biggest anti he was he was the the
inspiration for Adolf Hitler
this is how anti-semitic Henry Ford was
and you kind of like gloss over that and
then suddenly we as Arabs have to pay
the price
why several questions I want to ask
there so but one just zooming out why do
you think hatred of
Jews has been such
a viral kind of idea throughout human
history oh it's very easy
it all started from Christ they killed
Christ they killed Christ they killed
Christ they're the killer of Christ
that's a very sexy story and that was so
yeah that was and that stayed for years
that stayed for centuries I'm sorry
centuries they're the killer of Christ
and then the C the Catholic church
church did not allow usury but they
would work in usury so they become rich
now the people that we hate that we
accuse them of feeling Christ are
becoming rich so that's Envy now and
that's that and and and that's hatred I
I mean when you talk about ghettos
ghettos were not just a secluded Parts
in cities sometimes those ghettos were
outside the cities Jews were not even
allowed to work a lot of professions
they were not allowed to get into the
syndicates of
certain uh professions so they had to go
work usually and they got rich so people
hated them more the first the first
crusade didn't kill a single musl Muslim
all they killed were Jews and when they
finally arrived to Jerusalem all they
killed were Jews they they almost
annihilated the Jews so it was all this
and of course you have the Dark Ages who
do you need as an enemy the Jews right
they they're the killer of Christ
there's nothing bigger than
this and then you you fast forward I
mean one of the things that I that I
found out that was very very very very
crazy when Henry Ford imported
the the protocols of the Elders of Zion
by the way in the Arab word Protocols of
the Elders of Zion is so popular and for
obvious reasons and for the people who
don't know it it's kind of like a bunch
of like stories and basically it's like
the the the the the Jews saying like
we're going to control the world and
we're going to do this and we're going
to do that and whatever what people
don't know that they that is a work of
plagiarism it was plagiarized
from a satirical play called
conversation in Hell between mcki and
and moniku and it is just it it is and
it is kind of like based on one chapter
or one scene or something it it's crazy
but it's crazy how sticky it is like yes
weird yes because if I if I hate you
that's great but if I have a story to
support that hate Ah that's even better
but it's like one of the one of the best
stories one of the stickiest stories
about hate it's probably the the most
effective cuz like there you know a lot
of peoples hate other groups of peoples
but that that's just like the sexiest
story of them all because humans need to
concentrate their hate their
insecurities and their shortcomings into
one thing that they can practice that
that hate on if it's a it's a it's a
person great if it's a group even better
but how do you into this C
incorporate that the that group is
pretty small there's 16 million Jews
worldwide mm and you mention how is that
the responsibility of the Arab peoples
you know everybody should be to blame
for not taking in Jews after the the
Holocaust but you know the reality of
the situation if we look at the
religious SCE of this there's 16 let's
say million Jews and there's I don't
know how many Muslims but
1.8 billion yeah yeah how do
you that difference that uh 100x
difference do you incorporate that into
the sense that Jews in Israel might feel
for you know the existential dread that
we might this this small group might be
destroyed Jews in Israel have every
right to feel afraid because of
everything that they see and everything
they've been told everything but I I I
would say that the calculus or the
numbers doesn't like of course like
being
small it is of course a factor but it is
never an excuse in order to take
something that's not yours it's saying
like hey you have 300 million Americans
and we have 52 502 say give one state
for them there's too many of them to too
many of you just give them something you
know it's like the fact that I have
something and you don't and I have there
are too many of me and there is little
of you and then you come in and and it's
not really Israel against the Arab word
or the Muslim because we have to say we
up big time but it is the the the
the the the Palestinians that are in and
they are being subjected to that so it's
not really like the 1.8 billion and the
16 million Jews and the 1.8 billion if
you look at them some of them like don't
care some of them live into regimes that
being oppressed and those regimes are
supported by the United States in order
it's easier for me as a as a as an
Empire to to take what I want from this
country if I control the dictator and I
tell them that his power is linked to my
ability to to my my desire to keep him
in power so that's why you have a total
disconnect between people in power in in
the Arab and the Muslim countries and
the people themselves can you speak to
1948 you know cuz you mentioned taking
land that's not
yours um maybe parallels with Native
Americans mhm
yeah there was a
war the the Jewish minority fought that
war against several Arab states and won
that
war how do we incorporate that into the
cathis yeah well that's a also a
misconception uh like a
misinterpretation of the event because
it seems that it was uh like the small
the it's kind of like a David and
Goliath kind of
story but and I was all like how did we
how did we not do that but in in reality
with
numbers uh I I can't pull it up right
now but if you look at the numbers the
number of Tanks the planes the the
trained officer because those many of
those Jewish uh Fighters came from World
War II they were season Fighters and
they actually had more planes more tanks
more artillery more pieces of weapon
more of the all of other combined
because they the the the people that
really like fought was
Egypt and you have to 1948 some many of
those Arab countries didn't even have
their independence so they would kind of
like send like a Cavalry or like a
people in horses but in fact the whole
idea was like we won against Seven
Nations the numbers were totally in
Israel favor they were better equipped
they were better trained they were they
had like more tanks and and and
artillery and and and and and
airplanes and they plan planned better
so they yes they deserve the win because
they planned and we did it so to you
there was an asymmetry military power
even then but what do you do with the
fact that the war was one so like if you
look at the history of the world
MH there
is wars fought over land I agree with
you this has been the history of
humanity Humanity was not living
peacefully it's all about like people
taking people and E killing people
taking their land but there's two
difference here most
usually the Conquering power like for
example England they had England and
they conquer you India and after the
occupation finished they go back to
England uh France Greece Persia Egypt
they would like go in expand and Shrink
expand and Shrink it's always been there
what is different here is exactly what
happened in Australia and the United
States a group of people came in not
just to conquer and take the land but
they completely changed to replace them
and get them out or kill them it was
very easy with the Indians because they
had small parks there was no social
media they did it over 400 years they
had time the problem is what is
happening right now I agree with you it
might not bad be that new but we are
there and we're watching it happen and
so now we have to confront the realities
of war and Empire and conquering because
you know what's the problem we told
ourselves we can be better yeah at after
1948 there was the universal Declaration
of Human Rights it means that we are
going to be better humans we're not
going to kill and take land we're not
going to displace people we're not going
to take people for what they there's now
laws there's international law there's
International court of justice and now
Israel is giving the middle finger to
all of them so isn't in some fundamental
way this whole thing that we're talking
about is us as a civilization on social
media in in uh In Articles and books and
uh in newspapers we're just trying to
figure out who are we as a people I I
think the the shock came from the fact
that we thought that we as Humanity have
evolved and now we
are what have actually changed is that
we became more advanced in effectively
eradicating a group of people because of
the technolog that we have and the fact
that we can do that under the eyes and
ears of all the world and we are
watching it on our phone we have a
window we have a window to the war you
know 1945 people didn't know what was
happening in Japan what well we heard
about it in the radio like oh today our
forces came in and they launched we
don't know we heard it we maybe we saw
pictures after that and it's quite
edited but now we see it we're into it
and it is it is so much for our for for
our psyche and we can get it and it's
like and then the Arabs are say like
guys you told us we came to the West
because we were told that we were equal
you know the universal Declaration of
right one of the co-authors his name is
Stefan Hassel he's a Jew he is a
survivor of the
hola and you know what happened to him
he died by the way a couple of years ago
but he before he died he was cancelled
by so many people and he was called
anti-semitic because he joined the BDS
movement and he spoke of of Palestine
that is the author of The Universal
Declaration of Human Rights that we
value so much and we think that that
would Define our Humanity but then we go
in and we
are shocked it's like maybe we were sold
something maybe that was false
advertisement you shared a tweet by an
account called awesome
[Music]
Jew uh it reads Islam Nai comedian bosam
YF comedian and quotes by the way yeah
yeah yeah of course because I'm not
funny so Islam Nazi comedian bosam YF is
now denying the octob I love that you
retweeted like this like twice yeah I
guess suppose because it's advertising
some upcoming
dates he's now denying October 7th
Massacre the Muslim radical bosam YF is
notorious for his radical radical said
twice for his radical hatred of Jews in
Israel in a recent clip he claims that
the atrocities committed on October 7th
are fabricated we looking for all
information regarding
any of his upcoming shows as well as the
venues which host the scumbag where Jews
feel safe around this
Nazi Nazi yeah I've never this is my
first time interviewing a Nazi so this
is honor it's my first time I actually
get called a Nazi first time first time
I have been called so many things in
Egypt so in Egypt I was
called um a CIA operative amused byy a
secret Muslim Brotherhood a secret
a secret Jew secret Jew uh there was
also an article that was published about
me in the state FR media saying in
details how bassim has been uh recruited
by CIA agents using John Stewart in
order to use satire to bring down the
country I was a Freemason an Infidel um
uh a member of the uh the the the the
Knights of the temple something like
that and there's actually people the the
Muslim Brotherhood on their show they
would say like he is actually an Israeli
and they have forged an Egyptian ID for
him to come so it's kind of like when I
get like I I said I had I left all of
that behind and I come here it's like
boom anti-semitic Nazi damn I mean I
really covered everything I don't know
what else I mean I think I have it's
kind of like I'm collecting phds I'm
just like getting like all of these
credits how do you deal with that how do
you deal with the attacks I mean this
goes back to the decision to uh
do the interview with Pierce Morgan like
how how do you like psychologically
throw all of it these kind of
attacks at the beginning it's fun but
when they evolve into something else so
for example I was like laughing off all
of the stuff about calling me this
calling me that but then when people
would come and and thread the theater
because it's not the people who are
making those accusations that would come
to you it's the people that will hear
and see those accusations and act on it
and there's always the fear of like I
mean we have we have in the airboard a
lot of things that somebody would hear
something about someone else and go kill
him and whatever like anybody else so
there's this but somehow I want to make
fun of
it and and it is to be cold and N an
Islam Nai it must been the funniest
thing ever because it doesn't Islam Nazi
wow how did you how did you and a
radical Muslim me a lot of islamist hate
me they call me a secular
Infidel so it's kind of like who am I
maybe I have an identity crisis and I
need the people to tell me who I
am let's go to the beginning let's go to
your childhood you grew up in Egypt K
Egypt well let's figure out how you came
to be who you are how do you become an
Islam Nazi yeah exactly it's a long
journey I do like the swasa tattoo on
your ass which I didn't
how did you see my you know what you did
I know what you did it was very
inappropriate you're also obviously a
sexual harasser of
me is this is like a me to this this
like 2020 someone will come up it's like
okay clip it this is your me too
moment um all right so Cairo what's a
what's a what's a meem defining memory
positive or negative from your childhood
my me memory in general was was cool it
was cool I went to a Catholic uh uh
school until the for for primary school
elementary and by the time I'm
done uh there was kind of like a start
of a decline into the public education
and my parents they're like middle class
working officials you my dad was a judge
my mom was a business professors and she
and they were like one of the people was
like they didn't have that much of
luxury my dad like drove like a regular
like car a Fiat
which is like the equivalent for the in
in Russia thank you for speaking to the
audience and um well so would that be a
good car or bad car it's kind of like
kind of like the minimum and my dad was
not a command of of of showing off he
whatever money they would do they would
put it for us education give everything
to their kids this is kind of like a
very very typical mentality uh and I'm
sure it's in many cultures but like we
grew up with this like everything that
we have is like for kids so they will
put us into education so uh Middle
School uh that was the beig 1986 was the
beginning of the explosion of like
international schools private schools
and these schools were relatively
expensive of course now with today's
currency it's ridiculous but at that
time it's was very expensive so I went
to that
school and from there was this moment
was like you feel less right away I mean
of course there's the regular bullying
and stuff but it's it's not that it's
kind of like you always feel less you
don't have that much of like purchasing
power that can allow you to go to the
same outings or travel with them and
even like how you dress it will be
modest compared to them so I was always
an outsider I
was uh and I compensated with that by
two things being good at school and
being good at sports so I was not like
the typical nerd was just like I was
like I was playing football basketball
CR field and I was like one of the
people would like to have me on their
team so I wasn't like kind of like ah
he's in there get him away but I never
had a girlfriend I never had any kind of
I was not like I was not boyfriend
material MH so that's kind of like it it
leaves remnants in you that you're not
good enough but psychologically you were
always like when you were by yourself
you felt like an outsider yes all the
time and that's why kind of like I'm
more of a loner I don't have a lot of
what do you call friends I have
acquaintances people people that I do
stuff with but I don't I've like the
people that I tell them everything when
I went to medical school now medical
school is a different Animal Medical
School is where all of the people from
the public schools go public schools are
very like they are not they they don't
have like they they don't have English
uh language as like a strong partner but
they are brilliant people so because
they would mostly they study in Arabic
but they are brilliant and they are very
very very smart very sharp but then I go
there now I am the boy
from the private school that comes into
medical school now I'm an outsider again
and I go into uh I I go into
residency and I pick up salsa so now I'm
a salsa teacher while being a cardi
thoric uh surgery resident and I'm an
outsider for the third time because in
salsa I'm kind of like the respectful
doctor and in Resident I'm the guy who
is just dancing so and everything of
course as a medical resident you will
mess up a lot yeah so they would always
like oh because you're a dancer oh
because you don't care about medicine
you just like want to go there and dance
with
women which is true
but but and so all of my life I felt
that I'm an outsider I'm not part of the
team I'm not part of the core
group
so and and I have a story that you would
love I right before my residency I was
so much into Sala so I
I had all of the m and then you saved
that and I was working in summers and I
was doing extra jobs and I took that
money and I went to Miami in order to to
learn R de kazino which is the Kuban
kind of like Circle salsa kind of thing
and I and I went there in the summer of
2001 yeah and my return ticket was
2011 Universe has a sense of humor I got
to tell you that no my n 912 I was
supposed to be on a plane coming back to
Egypt what happens thank God I ran out
of money 10 days before that just like
all right I changed my ticket and I came
back 911 I'm kind of like my mom wake up
wake up what what like and I see like
the two 4 was like my's like oh you're
here you're here you're here thank that
and I was like I was like I should I
could have been in guantan MO right now
F flying at 912 and but by the way I was
in Miami they were they when they went
to the the flying school in Miami so I
mean I I I I had like 911 written all
over my face you'd be all over the news
all over and my's like what he went
there to dance salsa I didn't know that
salsa is like a name for
terrorist why salsa why why why did that
attract you and what like can you
explain what salsa is so I I mentioned
to you Offline that I've been doing a
little bit of Tango try learn it yeah
like you know samb Sala Pata Maring it's
kind of like Latin dances uh and uh it's
like um you know I I don't know how you
describe Sal couple Dance One Latin beat
and uh I I did it
because I I once I and I talk about that
about my in my Arabic stand-up comedy
not the English I talk about like how I
was you
know I didn't have like really like a
great like social life and I my friends
went there one day and I go go into a
place which it was called eletto
negro no no it was called Big Fat Black
Pussycat and then I think they they they
thought it will be like racist or
something to change it to elto negro
anyway
so great great I know great decision I
know so I went there I like damn music
and women M and my doctor a doctor
dancing salsa that is electric magnet
yeah 100% we know we do you know we do
everything for for that all of even
power even money all the wars we've been
talking about
women the day the approval from the
other sex we are we are babies we would
we are terrible people yeah so of course
like I mean that was like that was like
great but then I as as a nerd I went in
so hard and now I became a salsa teacher
yeah and I earned more money from salsa
more than I did as a doctor's res I
didn't know this part of you that's
hilarious I know I was I was making I
was making killing amount of money like
huge amount of money and I I was just
like you know I I would go finish my my
my shift and I go to the salsa class and
sometimes I would have like 70 people in
My Salsa class oh wow I had like the
biggest salsa class in Egypt in the the
beginning of 2000 and it was fantastic
and it was an outlet because you go
there and there's the shift and people
dying damn and they go
salsa Escape you must have been good I I
was okay I was cool I was fun there were
people better than me but I I I I have a
a thing about teaching I like teaching
people so you mentioned heart surgery so
what what motivated you to become a
doctor it was a a choice of exclusion I
mean there's nothing else you can do
with these high grades other than doctor
engineering I hate math so go be
off this the Middle East what do you
expect it's either a like I in my joke
in my show I said like there's it can be
one of three things in the Middle East a
doctor an engineer or a disappointment
it is that that is the choices that you
have so years after a
Bo yeah I am you're damn good at it
though that's a hard path though yeah
right and it's uh it's a fascinating one
for can I tell you something that
actually I was thinking about why did I
actually going to medicine and why did I
always choose the hardest thing although
I didn't love
it and I have to tell you I had an
epiphany only two weeks
ago and I don't know if that's actually
related or not you know remember when I
told you I went to this school and I
didn't have that much money and I didn't
have the luxury of time or money to be
with those people and do what they do so
by the time I finished school and
everybody was going to University all
everybody in my school went to the Au
the American University in K of course
probably like American Education party
time like I mean of course they're
brilliant and everything but they have
yeah they they have a different you know
social life and part of me now I I kind
of
like I realized that just like very very
recently maybe I went to the hardest
school ever so I don't have space to use
other than St
because if I have that much space what
I'm going to do with it I don't have
that much freedom I don't have that much
money I'm not I can't compete with those
people going out so maybe I need a solid
excuse that I'm in a place where I don't
have that much of a spare time is it
also possible I like how this is a
therapy session where we're
psychoanalyzing is it also possible that
you always just pick the hardest thing
you could possibly
do maybe but maybe that's the Piers
Morgan thing too like what
maybe but like when I left Egypt and I
came here I still had the choice to go
back to Medicine sure but I hated it I
hated medicine traumatized me the amount
of like you give up you know my my
brother in Egypt he had a daughter she's
a brilliant basketball player she is in
the national team amazing I I used to
play basketball also in the Egyptian
League but I never I was kind of like my
favorite position in the court was the
bench and I was not as good as her but
she and then and then he he it was time
for her to go into into college yeah and
he he didn't talk to me for 6 weeks I
said tell what what's happening to Farid
where College like I didn't want to tell
you she went into medicine I said what
medicine why did he do because he knows
how I hated it I was traumatized like
she's and and I said like dude she's a
basketball player make her go like to an
easy school like n so that's kind of
it's fine he still did it he still did
it I still did it but I don't know is it
because of the difficulty or
because because of what I told you maybe
I needed something maybe because I was
not very confident in my social life so
I needed a distraction not to be to have
that much of a social life oh wow okay
you understand I see yeah uhhuh it's
it's kind of loud because I will always
have an excuse I'm studying I have
something I have exams and I don't know
I kind of like self- sabotaged my own
thing because I couldn't compete with
with those people on on the outing and
the money and whatever so I need an
excuse to be like oh he's a doctor he's
studying at least in your own mind you
can compete yeah yeah I I I always felt
as less because I mean I I didn't have
any girlfriends in in in school I I had
very late in life I everything to me
came to life so I always felt even stand
up comedy it came very late to me in
life so I always feel that I'm not good
enough I feel that I didn't spend the
time of to build the foundation that
other comedians do so I always feel that
I am too lucky I always feel that this
is a fleeting thing and when I went had
the the the height and the fall the fall
all of in Egypt when I would like the
top of of everything I was like so so
famous and then everything was taken
away from me that's like ah you see I
told you that happens when you don't
build Foundation you fall so I always
feel that I that I am not good enough or
if I am in a position where people think
I am deep inside I am not do you know
that I have a speech imped that I was
not meant to be a TV presenter I have an
in Arabic it's very obvious I cannot
troll my RS mhm I cannot say I cannot
roll it so in Arabic like Spanish it's
very obvious M so when I did my first
video on the internet that made me
famous and then I got my television deal
back there there in Egypt my partner at
the time he took the video and he went
to a producer I said like are you giving
me a guy with a lisp he couldn't he
should that's why when I came on
television I was the first ever guy with
a lisp I had two things going for me the
lisp and the big nose and I was always
bullied for two for these two all the
time so I always felt less see but
that's a foundation of like creating a
great person yeah because if you're
pretty you don't need to do
much I probably wouldn't recommend it
but it is it is true that so if you are
pretty do some
disfigurement find the flaws
and and uh be extremely self-critical
about
them so you saw John Stewart on TV for
the first time in in uh 2003 I believe
how did that change your life I was in a
gym and I was running on the treadmill
and at that time CNN was coming up for
on like on
cable uh and uh I was watching and
there's this studio I don't know what it
is so I
put the the earphones on and I started
watching and I was so taken by this that
I stopped the treadmill and I just like
St stood for the 20 minutes like this on
the treadmill and then I and I just like
standing there I didn't know what we was
he was saying I didn't understand what
is Democrats what is Republicans what is
what the those names that he's saying
what is Fox News I don't understand but
I was
fascinated there was something you know
when you don't understand the music but
you get the Rhythm mhm it was that I
wonder what that is that you saw it's
like the timing of the humor I mean
there is John Stewart is one of a kind
like his
biting criticism of power I would say
and also ability to highlight the
absurdity of it all but you understand I
didn't understand any of that but I
didn't understand any of the references
but it is the the Rhythm the Rhythm you
know sometimes when you even see like a
comedy that is that's a language you
don't understand but there's a
rhythm boom boom there's something
there's something in the music there's
something so there's something with the
videos and the pictures and he and the
face and people reacting yeah what is
this what is this yeah what is this and
we we had the uh the global edition so I
went to the YouTube and I just like
started to kind of like watch every
single episode that I can I said like do
you think we can have this in Egypt I
said nah never and then
2011 like I had a a friend of mine who
was also a YouTube Partner it was
something new at the time he said like
let's do something on internet let's do
something I said I want to do John
Stewart it's like do Ray William Johnson
John Stewart will not work I like I want
to those so that was in there yeah it
was in there and and and I and I and I
did it and it it can you talk about 2011
I mean uh what what is the Arab Spring
what is it uh people here in America you
know
depend depends on which side something
happen or what depend
depends which side of of the equation
you are because for a lot of people it's
a conspiracy it's American made it is a
Muslim Brotherhood it's the islamist it
is Israel it is everything else other
than people oh but it's a pure
Revolution it's a
pure I I I I I think we put too much
weight on conspiracies I think it is
normal human behavior that then become
get maybe used or abused or taken
advantage of by other powers and then
the conspiracy
M starts but at the
time uh the Arab Spring didn't start in
Egypt it starts in Tunisia bazis um a
fruit vendor blew like burned himself up
uh like the American soldiers who did
that a few days ago and uh that kind of
sparked protest in Tunisia and Benin Ali
was a dictator in Tunisia for about like
20 years and they removed him so
suddenly it was kind of like a domino
effect so and then Egypt started and and
it just took 18 days and you know people
hindsight this 2020 say said like you
know just bubak became like a burden on
the military because the military are
the real rulers of the country you you
might have a president that kind of like
have certain powers but at the end of
the day when the military sees that a
certain president is like too much of a
burden too much of like a you know so
they cut him off and muar is the leader
of Egypt at the time he was there for 30
years 30 years by the way speaking of
which CU it was a joke in you Mark Twain
speech I got te te ey just watching that
that was great you're like great
like what you did with Mark Twain awards
for John Stewart it's great I mean your
comedy is great in general and I wanted
to go to your show I I definitely will
uh but that's a that's like a little
stroll in the complete tangent of just
the masterful introduction and
celebration of John Stewart anyway
Mubarak yeah so I and and it's a joke
that I say also like V had like was a
president for 30 years like oh my God
you had a president for 30 years like is
the Middle East it's a very short first
term it's like it's like we're still
warming up baby warming up I thought
like we need to plan ahead we need to
plan our our our our vacations our
careers our jail time it's just like we
need
to great so uh true so we had kind of
like the shortest nicest Revolution 18
days and we thought oh 18 days we can
change the country in 18 days so but of
course we were naive and we had this
kind of hope so Mubarak was removed
there was an interm uh period by the
military took it for one year then they
did elections Muslim brother came to
power they stayed for for one one one
year and then the military removed them
and in these three years my show started
it started by kind of like a YouTube
video it became famous overnight
overnight five five to six videos boom
went
out and at that time I was waiting to
get my clearance to go to Cleveland I I
I I I already accepted in a fellowship
as a pediatric heart surgery in in a
hospital in
Cleveland and and I said all right I'm
just going to do a couple of videos
maybe I'm going to put it in the
internet and maybe after a year or two
after I come back from the fellowship
somebody will come hey why don't you
write a show that looks like John
Stewart that P My Mind took five weeks I
had my first contract of of television
and
overnight the exposure and over a the
next two three years I had 30 to 40
million people watch 30 to 40 million
people watching every episode a lot of
it's like wow that's too much that is
terrifying yeah because it means that
there are 30 million people who have an
opinion about you yeah you said there's
a lot of aspects of that sudden Fame
that were just horrible it's toxic it's
toxic it's unnatural it's unnatural when
people started to recognize me in the
street and take pictures I was awkward
like why do you want to have a picture
with me why why is it because I didn't
feel that I'm worthy enough to be like a
reward for someone to have a picture and
I didn't understand it I was actually I
was kind of an ass sometimes because
people thought it was arrogance no it
was confusion and I remember like my
director and my producers and people are
they always saw me in a very bad mood
it's like why are you why are you not
enjoying this it's like because this is
not natural this is not natural this
adoration this love and this have to end
somehow and it did and in because at at
a certain point you are a human you and
people kind of the Adoration and the fun
and the love comes because they see you
saying stuff because you do your job
basically political satire is basically
us making fun of politicians in the
media and a lot of people have a lot
really strong opinions about politicians
in the media so we came that we
articulate that and we give it to them
and we make them laugh so for them we
made a great job so why don't you do
more but you are limited and at a
certain time you can't and a certain
time you're afraid because we're humans
because you're afraid about like if I
continue speaking up not like something
will happen to me I'm kind of like maybe
have some protection because I'm have
I'm F people see me but are the people
around you mhm and we I've seen that so
that's why at a certain point like
that's it I can't I mean there's a lot
of things to say there but one of the
difficult things of Fame in your
situation is you're not just having fun
you're criticizing power yeah and and
and and and it is loved by the people
but it comes with a price because at a
certain if the power is too strong and
you're not into a situation or or or a
or a system that allows that that gives
you that kind of safety so what
happened what happened I was so when so
the height of our my fame when the
Muslim brothers were uh Brotherhood was
in power and at that time they had their
media and I had one show I had like one
hour Peri week and they had five
channels 24/7 and they were like you
know I'm B John Stewart said it
beautifully one it's like we say
and you say and we just say
better than you this is exactly what
John St like we're just better we're
just better at saying back yeah so
so basically I had one hour and they
have like the five thing that they were
like you know they're calling me all
kind of names not just me like all their
enemies you know and then I just had one
hour and I would kind of like annihilate
them in one hour a week so
at a certain point they would they would
even like kind of be side with the Army
against the the the the kind of the the
liberal seculars whatever you call it
and at a certain point the Army kind of
like flipped everybody what do you mean
like kind of like they they made they
they they they yeah they removed the
Muslim Brotherhood they came to power
and we I I can I have to say I admit it
I supported that in the beginning
because I I had daily threats I had I
was actually interrogated and arrested
on in the Muslim Brotherhood I was in in
an interrogation for 6 hours and they
were asking about the my jokes and I use
that in my stand-up comedy describing
exactly what happened in the six hours
and it is so funny okay well
it's
hilarious but what slow down you were
interrogated by thehood the general
prosecutor the general prosecutor and it
was based because of complaints by the
the the officials in the government
because in order the general prosecutor
to do it it has to have a high up
mandate to bring that person into
questioning oh so they went through kind
of official channels oh yeah yeah
absolutely so it's all yeah it was
official it was legal legal very legal
so I went there and and and I and I
asked and and it's kind of like a bunch
of like insulting Islam insulting
president spreading false rumors and I
went there and I and it was funny
because I I go into the building where
there's police officers and their judges
and all of them are big fans of the show
and some of them were taking pictures of
me and then I'm sitting there and it was
the most ridiculous interview ever
because he was asking me about my jokes
it's like what did you mean by this joke
and it's like
nothing it was there for six hours he's
just reading he reading my jokes and
he's reading the jokes and the junior
judges sitting there like cracking up I
like I remember that it's like
guys guys that's dark is it's kind of
like and I'm laughing but in the same
time it's like the whole situation is
ridiculous but then at the end I I was
released on so I went back to my show
and I make fun of that and you have to
be honest the Muslim Brotherhood were in
power but Egypt were like right out of
the Revolution for there was kind of
like an
equal spread of power between the people
there was not like someone who come in
and just like the Muslim brother didn't
have that power yet but they were kind
of people saw that they were moving
towards that and then the tension Rose
and then there was like a kind of a a
confrontation between them and the Army
and then a lot of people were killed in
the street it was terrible m Massacre
and and then suddenly I am blamed for
all of that it's like you made fun of us
so now it made it easier for people to
kill us like dude come on you doing that
to me too I just did it better than you
and the fact that you sided with the
same people that flipped against you
that's not my fault did you criticize
the Army at all did yeah so uh after
that show I did like one episode against
the Army and I was canceled the next day
and then I went to another channel did
16 episodes in a different season and it
was I was walking on exell
and then it that was canceled again and
then my the production company that was
doing my show that we SE severed a ties
because there we didn't have the show
they had their their offices raided that
have people like having death threats so
at I woke up one day 11th of November
2014 and my lawyer said like leave the
country right now there is this legal
case that we that that they kind of like
they're coming for you but I said like
you cannot it was an arbitration case
and I lost against my my the channel
that basically canceled me and I said
like I don't but there's no jail time in
arbitration it's like yeah tell that to
the judges
leave so I I jumped on a plane the
verdict was 1200 noon 11 November 5
afternoon I was on a plane left Egypt
and I never came back since
then was there a worry of
non-legal things like
assassination I can tell you something I
was so stressed because of the show
because of everything I sometimes I
would wake up in the morning and I hope
that like bullet will come and finish
everything because I was so stressed
it's like I would love because I'm too
much of a chicken to kill myself so I
would like rather to have someone else
do it for me so uh I I I I I was I was
so under so much pressure and I remember
the day that like my show was canceled
indefinitely the second time under the
Army and I was
like I don't have to worry about what
kind of script I have to write next week
because this is you know remember when
you asked me about like that tweet about
like the all of say those accusation
doesn't bother me Infidel spy uh secret
Jew Zionist slamon Nai that's
what is really what really leaves a mark
is the criticism to your craft and your
work so you're not funny goes deeper
yeah certain things get to you better
than others especially if you have like
a secret suspicion that you are like
maybe not funny maybe I'm not because I
was put into that it's like because that
to your insecurities like I know but you
shouldn't say it out loud you shouldn't
say the truth out loud you shouldn't say
it
out but what about the weight of the
responsibility of uh speaking truth to
power so like walking on eggshells like
what did that feel like
well after the Muslim Brotherhood were
removed you have to understand like when
the military coup happened it was a very
popular coup like people love the AR the
AR the in Egypt the Army is more sacred
than the religion people love the AR but
the Army can go no wrong so me going
against the Army was I mean the Muslim
Brotherhood was not very popular they
were popular for their own basis but
people accepted the fact that like we
make fun of them but CeCe at that time
he was a God and I used to go to this
high class Club called gazer club and
this is basically kind of like the kind
of upper middle class upper class kind
of people MH and I during the that year
of the Muslim Brotherhood I was the most
popular ever people come yay when the
military came in people were walking to
me like pointing their fingers like
don't speak about C don't speak about
the Army huh we love you now but don't
you they would like that so I called
John Stewart was like I don't know what
to
do I don't know what to do
and and at that time all of the channels
were like closed down all of the the
independ I was the only one left because
it was difficult for them to get rid of
me very quickly because I was too
popular it was kind of like peace peace
mealing kind of like
going and I remember like I don't know
what to do he said like you don't have
to do anything just your safety comes
first and he said but I can't I mean
I've been doing that for 2 years and I
cannot just like say bye-bye guys I have
a responsibility I have a team I have
people working for
me and I also I cannot just like
disappear and he said the most
interesting thing ever and say if you're
afraid of something make fun about the
fact that you're afraid of it instead of
talking about that something brilliant
yeah so there was like a whole episode
that we did not even mention CCE we did
not even mention it but the videos did
all the thing and the whole episode was
me trying to avoid talking about him MH
and that that that how the comedy was
created the fact that I don't want to be
here and then I so he said like if you
will be surprised how people can relate
to that because there was a lot of kind
of like oh we love him but we feel we
cannot speak so just by doing the simple
thing about be mirroring the
society that goes a long
way and I kind of try to do what I can
under the I mean they they came up
with a machine that treats AIDS and
hepatitis C virus and basically every
single and I went to town with that
because people think it doesn't really
have to go in to go to the bigger po
like you're an no you talk about
their
propaganda you talk about what they want
people to perceive them
at and it's a failure and for that that
kind of hit them even more because what
do authoritarian figures do they work on
two things
fear and propaganda and from that it
gets the respect so when you go into
their propaganda and expose them they
have nothing else that's brilliant so
like you are walking on X shells but
you're doing it masterfully that you're
revealing sort of the the flaws in the
propaganda the absurdity of the
propaganda in so doing are criticizing
them and this is why comedy is very
specific because people say you were not
as hard on him as you were in a Muslim
brother yes because under Muslim
Brotherhood we were like just like
saying to each other yeah but now
the the the ceiling was like here so
it's kind of like how can you do
something from here yeah exactly that's
the art form yeah in the in the Soviet
Union under Stalin the a lot of the
criticism came from like children
stories and uh and children's cartoons
double meaning double in window stuff
that means other stuff that is the
that's the
Brilliance but everyone knows everyone
knows because you are like putting a
mirror like you're mirroring the society
it's fascinating actually and that's why
I was canceled
twice and that is a scary one the Army
you see that in Ukraine everybody
supports the Army that's why uh zalinsky
getting riding getting rid of the head
of the army was a big big deal it's a
really dangerous thing cuz everyone
support and everyone's afraid to say
anything negative about the Army
especially during war uh in that case
and in this case maybe there's Civil War
that kind of thing but think about it
actually an army during peace is much
more
dangerous because think about it I don't
really have an enemy to fight but I have
all of this power all of this tank why
is this actor have more money than me
yeah I'm protecting him why does this
businessman think that he can get onto
his private uh plane and go to Paris and
why I'm here sitting like not having all
of this
so and there there's a lot of time on
your hand because
your job is to go fight when you don't
go fight and we when you have the lack
of that's why that's one of the thing I
love the United States about is the fact
that the Army cannot really get power
but the kind of like the Army is the
power is actually in the military
industrial complex which is a different
issue yeah it's kind of like a different
kind of issue but if you have all of
that power like what why am I sitting
around just like playing guard for you
guys that's why iron that's terrifying
cuz you have this military that it just
becomes a police force that turns
against its own people
yeah so
you're you're you're a famous guy
talking in the middle of all that
yeah and and I when I left I went
through a very dark side dark dark dark
because all of the insecurities all of
the stuff that have been like working on
my head now came to life and now I'm in
America and I'm a nobody yeah I'm a
nobody and now it's like I have to do
something have to earn some money so I
started to do standup comedy 5 years ago
and I sucked because I it was my second
language and I was new and now I would
go to these comedy clubs with like kids
and 21 22 people and then I'm there with
the family to support that I'm going
there to doing it for $15 $20 and and I
was bad I was bad you're you're bombing
bombing big time eating eating
Big Time dying up there big time and I
would go back home and I would cry and
then and then what made it worse is
sometimes like a fan like not a fan a
bunch of fans from Egypt oh B you they
come
and disappointment on there that kind of
like face of adoration that
goes and I could see it in their face I
think he's going to drive an Uber in a
couple of
weeks that that kind of pressure and I
would go and I would and and I and and
then oh you left you you you you gave up
you were a sellout you're a coward why
don't you speak from abroad you're
you're safe now like I I don't I already
spoke I don't want to be because I don't
want to be an activist I was doing that
for comedy when it was good for
everybody but now they want me to go go
into YouTube and just like throw rocks
from outside and like you know I
understand I have family there and and
and it was this kind of like thing like
that I am
being like attacked for not doing what I
should do in their face and attacked for
not being funny and not doing good being
and now I'm feel like maybe it was wrong
and I was I didn't know I I really it
was so traumatic that I don't know
actually how I went through these years
and I blocked so many details from my
brain because I have been using this
technique for a while now that I have
been erasing a lot of my there is a lot
of memory
gaps in my brain and I'm trying to
suppress it because it was very very
very traumatic and a lot of people told
me you have to go to therapy but I I
don't I can't I don't know I I I'm I'm
worried to open the floodgates and I'm
think as if as I'm functional and I'm
not killing anybody I'm
okay it's like I think Elon tweeted uh
never want to therapy it's going to be
on my
headstone
yeah
[Laughter]
tell you best butts okay I mean that is
like terrifyingly difficult to like
after being a a surgeon after being a
superstar Super Famous going to eat
at local tiny clubs in the United States
I mean eating period yeah like
bombing is really really really
difficult really difficult for 20 year
olds imagine when you were 45
46 and and then people like is this his
midlife crisis what is
this I I I I I went through a lot of
pain and a lot of like the doubts and it
was terrible what I mean how did you
survive I know you blocked most of it
but what what gave you like strength
through all that because I didn't have
any other choice because I started that
and the only reason that I could is to
continue I I I I I don't know what else
to do I don't want go back to Medicine I
don't want to do go I don't I don't want
to do that and I don't I don't know I
was and bit by bit bit by bit I started
to kind of like be better be better be
better and I was at a certain time a
year ago a year ago this is where I
started to kind of like hone the craft
and kind of sell more tickets and
sometimes even sell out some shows and
sometimes sell a theater so like it was
going and the money was flowing and it
was
good and then I was like
why didn't I I want it faster I want it
more I want it now I want it I want
Netflix deal or whatever and then the PE
Morgan thing happened and then I blew up
and then suddenly I'm selling out
everywhere and it's like ah if those
people came if that that the war
happened two years ago I will not be
ready so now they come to the show and
by the way my show had nothing to do
with the October 7th my show is my thing
that I've been crafting and working on
you know how difficult is to do the
first hour that the the hour that I've
been working on for 5 years and it's all
my personal story all about like what
happened to me in Egypt me as an
immigrant coming here to the United
States finding Trump as a president
finding myself in the middle of a guns
rally finding myself in the middle of a
bombing kind of like talking about how I
got my citizenship it's all like funny
stories about like my origin story so
they come in and they expect October 7th
and all is my personal story but it's
good and it kills and they love it it's
like if that if that kind of like blow
up in America happened to me two 3 years
ago I would not have people would come
and be
I gotta say the timing of October 7th is
very suspicious oh my God please don't
say that I don't know I'm just asking
questions I'm telling you one of the
funniest thing a guy he I was in Dubai
and like a TV anchor came to me bassim
youf he flourishes during revolutions
and War it's like wait wait wait what
what
dude you're you're making me sound like
a bad woman a very bad
woman yeah you Hamas and BB together
orchestrated all oh my God that's the
the that's the
trilogy you guys should go on the road
together I'm telling you that phone call
is coming yeah but Hames has to
open and they would really bomb right
that would really
bomb Oh I love dark humor you do a show
like you were saying in
English and in Arabic MH so and the
story is very different totally
different two different stories I would
love to just just the language
difference because the music of the
language is also different so like what
what's how can you convert it into words
but what's what's the difference in the
in the music of the languages I'll tell
you because I thought about that a
lot all right all right okay so when I
was doing the English first yeah I was I
actually had good jokes but I was
missing the delivery because the Cadence
and the music and the rhythm is
different the way that an English
speaking American uh a member of
audience will receive it it will be
different than how I receive it the
energy everything is
different so when I kind of like got
it I didn't know how to switch back to
Arabic oh wow yeah fascinating because
here's the thing with English standup
comedy English you have a huge Library
you have like a legacy you have like
years and years and years and years of
people doing comedy but in Arabic it's a
very new very new to us and most of the
Arabic stand-up comedy especially in
Egypt is very um tamed
mhm this is kind of like imagine the
stand-up comedy seen in America 1960s
before Lenny Bruce oh so no swearing
conservative swearing nothing
conservative everything like yeah it's
kind of like very so I didn't know what
to do with Arabic so I broke the bars I
became Danny Bruce I became Geor KH so I
went in and I went and I and I changed
the whole thing seven words you're not
allowed to say what for me there 15
words
but a lot a lot Arabic is a very rich
language yeah
so when I did here's the difference
between the Arabic and the English
show the English show surprise surprise
is a unifying language even for a group
of Arabs so if I give the same exact
show to the same 1,000 me audience
members in the same theater and they're
the same people same
makeup of like Lebanese Egyptian Syrian
Saudis English will be a unifying
language Arabic is a dividing language
because you have 22 dialects and the
dialects are vastly different and like
maybe Egyptians understand a little bit
of Lebanese but not that much but the
referen is Algerian Moroccan Tunisian
totally different animal that's like a
totally different Lang Saudi emirati
Kuwaiti totally different people
understand the Egyptian dialect because
it's the dialect of most of the artwork
and the movies but the reference and the
everyday Street Talk might not be
understood by them so now I have to go
in and talk to all of these dialects
together so I formed my big big part of
my show is like what are you guys
expecting of
this this is what this is we going to
when to go do profanity and you're going
to like
it this is the problem with that the
show as a dialect and I I construct all
of these sentences formed of so
different different words for example an
iron in any in any in in any Arabic
dialect is an iron in Saudi Arabia it
means ass that's one example yeah that's
one example you know so imagine if you
can actually construct sentences having
all of these things in one so I would I
would construct like a whole section of
my show about that so it's really very
much about like self-reflective on
language and the limits of language
that's allowed and the limits of
language and I tell them part of the
show is like I know what's a problem
with me doing Arabic it's like if this
was an English show and I was telling
you and you'll be H but
if I do one swear wordss all of you will
scr yeah it's like why is it because we
are ashamed of our own so it's kind of
like it is it's not just like about
swearing it's about like there's a lot
of
philosophical Pathways in this yeah
there's profanity and we we when people
have fun whatever but like it is about
like what does how do we treat our
language and I tell them we speak Arabic
as Arabs but it's not the same Arabic
it's crazy right and you're doing the
show in America also which is another
level of OB oh yeah actually the Arab
diaspora in America is some of the best
audiences I
have they are like wonderful and they
come from they just and I did and I do
and I did it also in the Middle East and
maybe I'll do like an Arab tour in the
Middle East in the fall which countries
would you go to and not I wor did Jordan
Lebanon I'm doing uh UAE I'm doing
Kuwait Egypt Bahrain Egypt I don't think
so I don't think so is it personal is it
worry about your
safety well I have the American
citizenship right now so I am relatively
safe there's a block sure honestly
there's a block there's a person there
is there is um there's so much that
happened and I don't and I never I I
never bad mouth Egypt it is my country
it is some like it has all of my
marriage 40 years of my life I lived
there but when you get hurt so much
instead of trying to kind of I don't
want to take revenge I don't want to
like that I just want to avoid because
Egypt gave me so much Fame and so much
love and so much hate and so much
Rejection it is a very it was a very
tulous relationship very very difficult
and it's uh and a lot of people tell me
well don't you miss Egypt and I tell
them every time the Egypt that time is
is not there anymore it's not bad or
good it's not worse or better it's just
I'm different and the places are
different and the people are different
and the circumstances are different
whatever image you have of the of what
you love is not there anymore that's why
a lot of immigrants especially Arab
immigrants they they live here but
they're there and then when they go back
for a vacation they get disappointed
because they didn't find what they want
and then they come back here and they're
disappointed because this is what they
want to come back but it's not there
anymore yeah their view of that place is
from a different time I have that
you know my parents but everybody that
left the Soviet
Union I mean it's such a complicated
relationship with that it's sometimes
borders on hate
disappointment in the uh in the case of
the Soviet Union perhaps similar to
Egypt is the promises sold when you were
younger and the the promises broken by
the possibility of what it was supposed
to be with the Soviet Union I'm sure
with Egypt is the same Iran is the same
so they have a very complicated
relationship with that yeah that's why
like for example people from Iran you I
remember I remember quite well the World
Cup that was made in done in in the
United States and the Iranian team were
play in America and there were people
people in the audience or wearing Iran
they hate the regime but they have this
kind of connection with the country yeah
and this is this is the whole thing you
can actually love the country and you
not have to agree with the
regime would would uh would you ever
perform in the West Bank no Gaza because
if I go there I have to go to the
Israeli checkpoints and I don't want to
go through the isra I don't want to have
an Israeli soldier telling me what to do
yeah there's a demeaning aspect to that
whole even even in subtle ways yeah yeah
yeah I mean I have so many Palestinian
friends with an American passport US
Passport living here they are born here
and they they talk about the humiliation
and the intimidation and the harassment
that they go in it's like I
do you want me to try yeah that little
bit of a
humiliation little
bit oh sometimes it's major but I
noticed that you know even the little
bit is uh has a after a lifetime of that
it can turn to uh it can turn to hate
towards the other yeah and resentment
resentment and then how do you do
anything with that resentment I have a
friend of mine he is from Palestine from
blest back he's American here is born
here and uh we talk about you know we
have of course all of this discussion
what what happened and he tells me you
know in October 11th in the West Bank in
and there was a village called K
KRA and on that Village like the the
settlers went in around the village and
they send a message on Facebook as like
you rats going get out of your sewers
and we're going to be waiting for you
intimidation through technology and then
they went er uh the it is KRA have like
another settlement next to it called ish
kodesh ish kodesh they have people there
who were training something called
mishar Yesa which is basically the
Guardians of Yesa and it's like a
paramilitary group that trains other
settlers on military combat give them
weapons and do like military drills and
they went there like militarized and
went there and and it was actually
co-founded by a Jew from Brooklyn
not even and and and and like an Israeli
and he is like one of the Disciples of
May Kahana I'm sure that you know Mah is
who was the Jewish defense lead the
people who assassinated Alex AA here in
the United States and and they were they
were there with their weapons outside
intimidating people now this story
carries everything that is wrong with
the situation you have people from
Brooklyn from outside just because
they're Jewish they can't come and they
can claim the land from the people there
anybody from po just because he's Jewish
you can come and take the land from
other people they're using technology to
intimidate Palestinians they have
unchecked military power these are not
IDF soldiers these are settlers and they
have free reign in order to intimidate
and to kill the people and you
understand this is the daily life of
Palestinians not in Gaza in the West
Bank what do you do from your what do we
do what do people
do
to nudge this towards
uh peace towards flourishing here's the
thing I want to talk to the people of
Israel what is Israel doing right now is
not
just unfair to the Palestinians it's
unfair to the Jewish people in Israel no
it is unfair to the Jewish people around
the world because the way that Israel
links itself to the Jew to
Judaism at a certain point you know
remember like Isis and Ka And when
everybody hated Muslims you know
sometime human humans are simple they
cannot have the nuances to
separate so anybody who with a Muslim
name with a Muslim face with a beard who
looks Muslim he would do it because of
that actions of those atrocities you
have the power as a person to separate
yourself from an abusive power a
horrible power and be yourself I am
really worried because the rise of
anti-Semitism and the rise of hate
against Jews is not because of the Jews
it's because of the actions of a
government
Jews do not have to be on the side of
aparti Rony castels he is a Jewish South
African and he fought shoulder Tosh
shoulder next to Nelson badel he was
part of the African National Conference
ANC and he had an article say like I
know what aparte is and I saw Israel and
this is what they
have and the thing is Israel the Israeli
government should
listen to other people you cannot call
anybody who who criticize you either an
anti-semite or if they're already Jewish
you call them like self-hating Jew you
cannot do that you cannot continue doing
that because we did that when I would go
in and criticize the islamist like oh
you're self hating Muslim you're not
really Muslim you're an Infidel you're
secret you're a secular whatever we have
the power in order
to
reform the course by holding people in
power accountable and the thing is it is
very stupid to actually call this
anti-Semitism like I my my idol is John
Stewart I voted for Bernie
Sanders the Sarah taxer the one who did
this amazing documentary about me
tickling Giants she's a Jew she is
married to an Israeli Jew we have a good
Rao because we know what the right is
they don't have to associate themselves
with the action of the Israeli
government uh one of your favorite words
Jihad that's my favorite hobbies it's
his favorite hobby it's my it's my show
it's like what's your favorite I talk
about like how when a white shooter does
something think he talks about all of
his family and his Hobbies like what if
we did this like for Arab for for Arab
terrorists what are his Hobbies
Jihad you see you should be a comedian
yeah wow you're making me feel good okay
Sam
Harris uh has has done several episodes
on Jihad and uh people should go listen
to it even if you disagree with it but
the basic idea that he's proposing is
that this idea of
jihad in the negative connotation of it
uh of martyrdom is a thing that gets is
counterproductive is destructive to the
possible future flourishing of
Palestinian people what what do you
think of that there just the idea of I
totally agree but like people don't wake
up in the morning and say like I want to
declare
Jihad think about it why would anybody
choose to end his life by taking other
people with him and end that life his
life must be miserable he must be pushed
into that nobody chooses death over life
willingly one of the first suicide
bombers in the Palestinian resistance
were
Christians we don't talk about that I
think he would say that the presence of
a story that you can tell yourself when
you're in a really shitty place that you
can go to a much better place by sacri I
ing your own life just the fact that
that the presence of that story is there
is is is harmful of course but these but
here here here's my problem with Sam
Harris and usually people would they
have free range talking about the
Islamic faith and nitpicking the stuff
that makes it put in a in a in a in a
bad light I can go and nitpick every
single
religion there are Jews there like benir
who openly say spitting on Christians is
not a hate speech all right they are I
mean I I you can bring me like all kind
of videos of Islamic jihadist saying
horrible things on on YouTube and I can
bring you Jews who live there they I
like we're going to have the whole world
enslaved for us and everybody would love
to be slaved for the
Jews you know I can use the talmudic
argument that if you tie a man to a tree
and he dies of thirst and hunger you
didn't kill that man and this is kind of
the same arguments like we're not
killing Palestinians it's just like
killing they Dying by themselves you
know so it it is the nitpicking of of of
a certain narrative religious narrative
that is separate from the political
context and what what's happening right
now it's very very unfair because I can
read if you want to have a deep dive
into religious text nobody will be happy
and I can bring stuff from that almud
and the and the Torah and stuff that is
horrible but like you know this is a way
again
of like distraction I dare you to talk
about Buddhism and jism though well
you
know the people who killed the Muslims
in Myanmar were there Wen they Buddhist
yeah well J let's go Jaden okay I'll
find the religion I have to get back to
you I'll have to find yeah the the the
the flying monster the the the Church of
theing moner
spaghetti as a person who tries not to
eat carbs I'm deeply offended by that I
mean there's Scientologist all they do
is actually buy real
estate I think there's a books written
about the fact that they do other
stuffff as
well so even there I Mormons sometimes
there some of the nicest people I've
ever met but I'm sure there's also
Darkness there
too oh boy religion uh there's soaking
in in
Mormons there's what soaking what's
soaking okay so I don't know how much so
soaking basically like you if if you get
into the woman and you don't move
that's not adultery that's not like oh
interesting so you go and you just say
there's a loophole there a loophole this
the thing religion religion has a
loophole yeah yes and with Muslims we do
that the whole time we we pick and
choose our our sins the stuff that we
enjoy it's just we you 72 virgins
waiting for all of us maybe if I
converted you as a Jew I'll get you 80 I
don't know you know like you can
negotiate but I also have questions
about whether a very good deal I'll give
you and maybe I'll throw there a Camry I
have to be CER it's pretty good what
year I don't know 1998 best year ever
well they last a long time so I'm not
sure I want 70 I 72 I I'll throw five in
the mix and see how we feel yeah can we
if you want to upgrade yeah can we can
we do a trial
period but in general if you just zoom
out uh do you think
religion is in what way is it good for
the world in what way is it harm for if
there was no religion humans would have
invented religion because think about
think think like the early Humanity like
you're like a cave man or whatever and
then like you see your family members
killed and then you say like what I'm
going to be like the the the or the
gazelle that just like ends and perish I
need to have I I am more important I
think I think with the development of
Consciousness
humans like thought that they are much
more precious and important than the
other animals because they have now
intelligence so
my life will not end like that they will
my death will be even more important
there's consequences for that there's
consequence for what I do and then the
the early man was like there in the
desert and all of these like natural
phenomen they didn't know what to do
they were afraid MH so they need to have
Refuge they need to have something to
take care of they need to have a reason
for everything because if there's no
reason it's chaos M it's chaos it's
terrifying it's terrifying it's Terri
there's nothing thing is there there has
to be a reason there has to be a reason
there has to be a purpose has to be like
a cause something it's it's just I'm not
just going to be like die like like a
coach being stepped on and that's kind
of like part of it is ego the whole
world rotates around you in a way it's
the ego so the religion actually got a
lot of it from Humanity itself like me
us like us being humans and there's and
and and many religion is a collection of
of of stories and those stories based on
things that humans did themselves and
they attributed it to gods and there's
an aspect of religion where you humble
yourself before a thing that is much
greater than you so that has a I would
say a very positive effect of humbling
it will be great if it stopped there but
here's the thing if you humble in order
that your ego kicks in and feel that you
are better than someone else who's not
humbled in the front of the same God go
there that means that I will have all
that train that I can use that because
now what what does mean being humble I'm
Divine yeah but I'm so I'm way more
humble than you H but you're not so you
you see how they kind of like the
oxymore I'm humble and I'm surrendering
but in the same time I am better than
you and I'm more entitled isn't it crazy
yeah it's beautiful it's crazy I mean
look at look look at like like the
Muslim Christians and Jews and every
like it's like all right Muslims we
surrender I I'm talking about the
extreme ones I mean like people like
people like I surrender to God good
keep it that way yeah like if you go
there I surrender to God that means that
I am closer to God than you then you
should die okay Christians Christ is
love and he loves me and we going to be
together but you don't get into his
kingdom and you you see it is the same
thing yeah yeah it's just if you stop
stop there stop stop where you are
humble and you feel that you're a piece
of and you are worthless human
being and you are there stop there but
you says like oh that makes me a better
person than you and it makes me more
with God than you so that would give me
the entitlement to kick your ass yeah we
always ruin a good thing don't
we that you go uh you've been
outspoken you know with Piers Morgan but
just on this topic uh and you uh talked
about uh the Superman story mhm which I
would love it if you were in a Superman
movie uh but have you lost job
opportunities uh because of this because
I I there was other a couple of things
that were going on but they stopped
again I don't know if October 7th or
tell the Superman story just so yeah
what role were you uh okay when did you
audition for yes okay
okay so in June I was traveling to Dubai
and right an hour before I I get into
the car and go there my man said like
best I'm going to send you a script read
it it's the for super Superman it's like
oh Superman you know I I I'm not really
good in auditions I'm not as SE actress
so I like okay I'm just going to do it
send the tape I do the they ascend it I
go to the airport and and I read and I
can I think I can talk about it now
because they said they changed the
script so basically what I found it
interesting in that new script is that
there is like a a dictator in a country
that invades another country and
Superman interferes politically that's
the first time we ever see Superman
interferes politically Yeah so basically
was like Russia and Ukraine but because
of me it was like it had it couldn't be
Russia and Ukraine so it had to be
something kind of like with a flavor so
I read the role as if as a mixture of
trump and
Mubarak I I I I I I I did this mix like
you know uh I like the kind of the midd
but also like kind of like the the the
the the essence of trump into it I went
to the airport it's like an hour it's
like James gun saw it he loves you like
what I never had an audition that fast I
mean I I I had a few roles but not that
fast not like that and then I said like
well the the strike starts like tomorrow
and we need to be on the phone but after
the strike we cannot talk the S after
strike like we're the writers and the
actor strike so like but I'm going to be
on a plane right now it's like okay once
you land have a zoom call with James gun
I have a call with James gun he's I am a
huge fan of him the guy took like
something like Guardian of the Galaxy
nobody knew about it made amazing
Trilogy and he is like a really cool guy
I like I like what he did and it was
like really nice and and he started to
talk to me about the movie and you know
like I talk to people uh before casting
them so I know that everybody's on set
have a good chemistry it was amazing so
in your mind if you're an actor what
does that mean you got the part and he
told me you got the
part month goes by strike goes by
October 7th happens I do Piers Morgan
one and two and then I go to my
Australian tour my manager called me B
him the Circ was over it's like you
don't have the part
anymore I was sad very sad but for 3
days and said like I need to stand up
with it I'm actually doing very well
alhamdulillah and then when I
went to Chris
KO I after I finished the show he told
me did you lose any opportunities mhm
and that was off record after after the
show was like we concluded and I said I
talked about Superman and I found myself
when I was talking I was angry I was
bitter and I went home it's like why was
I angry why was I bitter it wasn't meant
to me and I'm I'm living a good life now
I I I don't need so when I was asked
again the next day in two different
interviews the BBC and the other and
another one was salong with my
friend I said the story in a different
way I said I don't have any anger as a
matter of fact maybe if I was Wonder
Brothers I didn't talk about Jim G I
thought it was the studio if I was
Wonder Brothers and I'm a Muslim I
wouldn't have a like a Zionist or a pro
Israeli in my movie but I want to tell
them that like when I criticize Israel I
am not a threat to you as a Jew and we
can actually have more in common so I
was more of a kind of empathic so when I
said that the internet went crazy and
you know jimes gun have Hatters because
you know the the Snider verse and all of
the that it's just it's a word that I
don't understand
and James
gun like had all of these attacks on
him and I was pissed of how it was
handled I wasn't angry at James gun but
I thought it was handled so my publicist
just like B him stay calm don't speak
it's better like to to like not talk
about it I said okay so as a there's
nothing wrong about me but I see the
heat is rising against Jameson and that
is a guy that I had a personal
connection with even through Zoom MH and
I didn't like what was and then he
called me and he explained to me I said
Bim you know I actually use like have
camera test before people before finally
I didn't know that and I and then we
changed the script and it was the strike
so I didn't call and I also I thought to
myself I'm small I'm a small actor I'm
not that important for him to call me to
say we're going to change the
script so I think still think that like
the timing sucks and everything but then
I went and I did a video explaining
exactly what I'm telling you because I
didn't want to be famous for the wrong
reasons yeah because that would be
unfair because that that was already
people were and I was having like
interviews can you come about this some
like that's that's it I'm not going to
talk about because this is another issue
and I did I didn't and I when I talked
to James on the phone I felt how sincere
he was so I I I didn't want someone to
because of me will have that kind of
attack because I know what it means to
be on the other side of that kind of
attack it's terrible and it ruins your
life and it ruins your day and nobody
deserves to be doing that and I don't
want to be the reason for someone else
to go through that pain and you also
said that you don't want to be a victim
I I don't want to be I'm doing a great
I'm doing great I'm selling out
everywhere I'm having a wonderful loyal
audience is coming to me why I would be
angry about the role of it's Superman
yes it's great to be in the superhero
movies but so what you know but you know
there's um there's a wisdom in that even
if you weren't doing great that's a
choice a lot of people
can come to which is like do I play
victim here or not it's great it's great
it they want more attention they want to
be more into the thing they want more
and more and there is so much to go
around to be enough for all of us but it
is great it is ego ego ego ego I need to
be in the center I need to be victimized
I need to I need to be people feel sorry
for me and love me it and it is not the
right way it is not because it is fake
it is fake it is made up and I did not
victimize myself when I left for Egypt I
mean in the time that I was now I speak
about it now but in that dark times I
was detained in airports I didn't have
my American passport yet I I was still
traveling with my Egyptian passport and
I was detained in an Arab airport I was
going to be delivered to the Egyptians I
had shows when I was still starting I
had hecklers being sent to me by the
Egyptian embassy and Egyptian Council in
in New York and in London to curse me
and to take videos of that and then
ended to statr media in Egypt and I
didn't speak about that because I felt
that like if I speak about that I feel
about like what was going on to me I
would be victimizing myself it's like if
I'm going to be good I'm going to be
good because of what I do not because of
what people's perception of what I'm
going through yeah and that becomes a
slippery slope and somehow victimizing
yourself goes to more victimizing yeah
and then you cannot leave that habit you
can only exist and Thrive if people feel
sorry for you yeah I mean Israel and
Palestine currently
both have that
Temptation I would always push back when
you do the comparison because one of
them is not really in the same kind of
power I mean yeah for
sure very easy to say why Palestinian
will victimize them but Israel with all
of that military might man it's too much
what Israel is doing is the dev
victimizing the Jewish
experience and I don't think a lot of
and I don't think it is fair for a lot
of Jews I don't think that they should
use the Holocaust and the persecution
that happened to Jewish people all
through history in order to push an
equally oppressive agenda that is not
fair and it's not good for the Jewish
people living and it is basically a
disrespect to the memory of the
Holocaust I told you I want to make a
movie about the Holocaust I I do because
what happened was that kind of
engineered torture should never happen
again and it should not be happening now
so to you what Israel is doing is
leading to more anti-Semitism in the
world 100% And I think and I know can I
be a conspiracy theorist for a second
please the Earth is flat we all know
this a part of me thinking maybe they
are doing that intentionally because if
there's a rise of anti-Semitism in Jews
there were always like points like see
they hate us so we can do whatever we
want because if if because because you
see if we let let go of our might and
our strength we're going to go back to
the concentration camps because you see
how the word hates you and and again
when you say they are people in power
yeah oh yeah absolutely listen it's
always the people in power I believe
that humans are easily corruptible and
easily repairable but the corrupt
corrupt part is much
easier but you you people could change
but Power people and power are very
dangerous very very dangerous especially
if you have religion which is Power by
itself military might political support
and money dude that's the that's a very
very very dangerous recipe that you know
all that said I I do believe in the
power of the little guy the individual
to overthrow the government you know I
don't know if you heard but the Arab
Spring uh you know happens but but but
okay here
we we here just among friends we are
Americans right we're Americans yeah
allegedly we're Americans
and how funny is that like just giv our
two backgrounds we're americ we're
Americans we're Americans it's
like we're
americ there's one thing about like the
power of the little guy that I am very
sad about because you see I'm I love
America by the way I I consider it my
new home and I want my kids to grow up
here I have I'm very grateful for the
opportunity that I have in the United
States and I criticize the United States
politics and I criticize it out of love
the same way that I was criticizing
what's happening with Egypt out of
love what is worrying for me is how the
power of the little man is
diminishing it doesn't matter now who do
you vote into power they will not listen
to you they would listen to the people
who paid them to be there and it is very
concerning because I can see the
American democracies turning not even
slowly very rapidly into an oligarchy
if I'm I'm sure that all of the millions
of people who are voting they don't vote
for the NRA they don't for vote for APAC
they don't vote for the pharmaceutical
companies they don't F vote for the
military industry complex and yet the
people in power they come in they take
your vote and my vote and they are loyal
to those people not to us and it is very
very very concerning very concerning
and it is this is the danger of American
on the American policies American
politics and American democracies it is
dangerous because basically the vote
becomes just like a
ceremony that that the the someone with
the more uh like funding will get to
power and then he's not loyal to you
still the fire I mean we are in Texas um
everybody everybody's armed to the teeth
here yeah but like what are these arms
going to do in front of
Tanks well you said the the the American
Military is unique in this way I know
but for now for now the tanks are first
of all I believe Russia has more tanks
than the United States tanks I don't
know you know I'm not an expert in
military uh strategic deployment of arms
but uh the United States uses different
kinds of weapons it's uh they have
drones and they have the lasers and they
have they're sitting comfortably behind
the screens it's kind of like it turns
like a big Xbox game yeah
and they they they sell a lot of those
things to everybody it's crazy because
the the defense budget is 68% of
American Military it's like almost $850
billion each year MH and most of that
weapons we don't even need it yeah we
just do it because of the contracts
there was like an incredible 60 minutes
I'm sure that you saw it the one about
like the gouging of the prices of the
the department of it was one of the most
fascinating things that I've ever seen
they say like a valve a safety a safety
oil valve that used to be sold for
$329 now it is sold for
$9,000 why because there's only
five uh weapon companies and they can
control the prices and in 2006 the whole
apach Fleet over the American Army in
Iraq was grounded because there is one
valve that they were like gouging the
price and didn't want to give them the
Stinger missile mhm that just like the
missile the the the the one that you
carry and and it's like the
anti-aircraft it used to be sold for
$25,000 now it's sold for
$400,000 and nobody is doing doing that
you know why because the dod has fired
130,000 people including engineers and
negotiators so now in order to cut
expenses now we're paying more money and
the thing is we do not have a say in
this we do not have a say in how my tax
money and your tax money is being spent
because I'm sure you don't want your
money to be sent to Israel like that I'm
sure even if you're Jews I'm sure I'm
sure that like I don't want my money to
be given to some Muslim countries who
kill other Muslims I'm sure but it is it
is not here's the thing what kind of
power do we have other than speaking so
what is left for us is free speech and
now when you speak they call you
anti-semitic you see why I'm
angry but still I mean America's holding
pretty strong despite the criticisms on
the Free Speech front uh but if you look
at the free free freedom of the press
freedom of the speech index uh America
is not at the top it is not and this is
why for example it is very dishe Harting
for me to see that the Western media
Western press that used to be the beacon
of Freedom Is Now using as mouthpieces
and it is funny how the New York
Times Nixon got angry in the New York
Times in
1971 when they found leaks about him
lying on about the Vietnam War since the
beginning M and now he hired the
plumbers you know the special unit in
orders to go in and find the leaks this
was Watergate basically because he was
angry to see who leaked that instead of
fixing the problem now the New York
Times have published this story about
the the rape that was a hoax that was
written by Anna Schwarz who someone who
have no
experience and now when it was leaked
instead of them correcting themselves
they went in and they had their own
investigation to see who leaked the New
York Times in 2003 became the mouthpiece
of W bush of the wmd and now as an
American I see that the New York Times
becoming a mouthpiece of a foreign
country why do you do that one of the
things that's really difficult to know
is where to find the
truth it does seem that both sides use
propaganda and both sides lie a lot but
both sides as in both Israel and pal Pro
Palestine pro Israel there's a lot of
lies I know
but it's a lot of inequality man are you
like yeah there's like a lot of people
on the internet but like who have the
mainstream media siding with yeah but
you know thanks toia I'm yes thank God
for social media because now it's
individuals they are people yes they're
people you're you comparing BBC New York
Times Washington Post what world street
joner with just people with a Tik Tok
account yeah who has more power in your
view now it is actually very very
fascinating to see the little man having
that power over the media in fact
disproportionately so like they like
this is my problem that's not but you
cannot call people with Tik Tok
propagandist while people being pay to
give you the the news and they
deliberately lie to you well yes I can
they're both propagandist well prop okay
yes yes but like but the mechanism and
the intentions are different because
because here's the thing I'd rather have
the tiktok guy than the like the Tik Tok
guy is a tiktok guy all right but if you
have the New York Times being told that
they being exposed to be lying and then
they get this like un report which is
like a disgrace and you just put the
title and you don't talk about it's like
I'm fine with CNN and Jake Tapper and
all of those people like spreading the
rape allegations for years they didn't I
don't even want them to refute them I
want them to bring the Israeli reports
saying that it didn't happen the Israeli
media them they didn't even bother not
once is that balanced that's not so
that's why people Tik Tok and because
they have to take matters in their own
hand yeah but the the problem with the
people in Tik Tok is the drug the the
dopam and Rush of getting a lot of likes
so instead of talking about the death of
civilians they will talk about beheaded
babies or the equivalent of they they're
going to actually make up stories
because the make madeup stories are
going to be more viral and so now we're
just in this sea in this muck of lies
and there's a lot of people who actually
expose those lies on Tik Tok so you have
both you have yeah you have both and
it's kind of like the Democracy of the
social media as we always call it but if
you have the street run media that is
the Legacy Media CNN BBC New York Times
news all of those people and they
are like spreading lies and they're not
even doing their journalistic job in
order to at least bring the other side
yeah that's problematic and that's
that's worse you're supposed to be
journalist yes it's supposed to be
report report you know report yeah but
you know I see that this is like a
catalyst an inspiration for the citizen
journalist to to rise up this is what
you're doing oh this yeah this is what
you're doing no this is what you're
doing because you go into a deep dive
this is like like a no filter thing
there's no spin the long form long form
is going to save
us uh I see why you hate the Tik Tok
like a damine rush you know stupid Tik
to hours later I saw the resentment in
your
face I can't can't look away for like
like those like 30 seconds I do 4
hours I mean both have a place both are
exciting and you know but I I can't it
is very dangerous like you can't look
away and I almost
never maybe I'm doing it wrong but I
almost never feel better ever after
having used Tik Tok makx two of us I
can't I cannot I cannot I have a team by
the way I give my my my my my passport
to like a team I don't even go there
because I went I once in a dark night
night very late at night I went Tik Tok
and it was like 2 hours what yeah what I
said no no no no no this is dangerous
I'm I'm I'm I'm already like an
Instagram and Facebook guy I don't need
that even there and I barely get out of
Twitter I mean like X I don't I can't X
is a sess pool X is just like too the
concentrated hate and it's too much it's
too much I can't so you you don't check
it at all you try not to check it at all
it is very I don't I don't I don't I
don't I can't I can't I just like I post
something and I
run posting
ghost uh so you're you're doing comedy
here in the United States right now yes
Joe Rogan has the the comedy Mothership
which is an incredible Club have you
considered doing that club I would love
to I mean I do you know Joe of course no
who would H does a new Joe I mean I feel
like it's a small world of Comedy that's
why I no I I think like Joe Joe's story
was like uh what he did and stuff he
that he did in the UFC and his podcast
and it just it's it's very impressive
the fact that he's there and he's
bringing all of those people whether in
comedy or his podcast is very impressive
and this is what this this is what is
the media is all about what is like the
internet is all about to give you the
experiences of stuff that you might
never experience MH and that is very
important I mean you do it with people
like you go into their brains mhm he
goes take people and they take their
experiences and and and their lives and
their story it is very interesting and
this is the beauty of of of that art
form
because you have all of these
experiences at the tips of your hands
and it is there for you to learn from
you know and and what he's doing like
when he moved to Texas and we did the
the comedy
Mothership anybody who would like push
comedy
forward that is the most difficult art
form and the most demanding and the fact
that you do that and not even be making
money out of it but he doing that
because of his passion that is enough
yeah he's he's the he really believes in
creating this like uh place where
comedians can be really free and one of
the cool things about the comedy
mothership is like comedian is King
there yeah like there we have to like
you have to bow down to the because you
know the comedian who came there came
after like eating dying out there
if you you are basically you're a saint
I have eaten for many years have
eaten now I'm going to give you ah
it's great you already told me what you
think about the state of politics in the
United States but now tell me what you
really
think what what do you think of the
choice of Trump versus Biden how do we
end up here I don't know man I mean like
the fact that like you have two people
over the age of 90 yeah it is I think
it's over 100 but that's all right all
combined like
170 it is so sad it is so sad that this
is what we can produce as as a
society like like a demagogue
and a sleepy Joe I just he's too he's
he's not there man he's he's gone he's
gone I
mean he could you know like when old
people could be like a danger for
themselves he's a danger for the whole
world I mean like the whole world like
if if if if if an old person would die
who would like you know have like a hip
replacement we can need them at like a
new planet because of one decision it's
but it's not just that it's not that
it's
um what are when I came here listen I am
I'm I'm a Democrat I always like and I
told you like I I vote for Bernie
Sanders I I I like I I supported him
like 2016 but I couldn't vote then and
of course a huge fan of
Obama and uh one of my is like he's the
first Muslim president was like but he
killed Muslims like that's things
Muslims do but
anyways I love that
line uh and uh it
just I I I think the the the the whole
idea like my shock
is I I told you about like what what
Biden said about like I'm a Zionist okay
we are a Zionist but then like Jews are
not safe in anywhere other than like
dude what the hell are you
saying and if you don't care about me
and you don't care about my
misery
why would I care about you winning or
losing you know and I have a joke that I
told people like why would even Biden
listen to us he just raised $145 million
in California alone from pro-israeli uh
groups I mean what what can we Arabs
working in The Vape business do to
him it's like we cannot compete with
that I mean like practically I mean it's
like life is like life is unfair the guy
is a politician he needs bills to pay he
needs a campaign to run he needs money
he will go to the people who will give
him
money Joe Biden is the highest paid
politician from Israeli lobbies $4.6
million over the years yeah but I also
believe in um great leaders that go
against all of that but unfortunately
you know Bernie Sanders was like that
Bernie
Sanders yes but also age I don't want to
be age course of course no no but even
with like cuz I I remember listening to
Bernie Sanders 20 years ago on Tom
Hartman show and I don't want to say
anything uh against Bernie but like he
was sharper then of course there's a
thing with age of course no I I I I
think I'm a huge fan about like putting
a limits on your working years because
you don't want to have like a mitch
mcconell moment every now because now
the whole thing are like what is this is
this not like a a hpy scare home it just
it it it is unfair it is unfair and that
the whole idea that you have like
unlimit like you have a limit for the
president but you don't have limit for
congress people and and Senators that's
what do you mean this is basically you
can go in and and and be in in in
governance for forever and you know the
longer that you can get the more corrupt
you will get yes that and that is very
concerning for Americans everybody
everybody becomes corrupt after for I
mean that's why two terms is a good
limit for everybody yeah and you know
maybe half a term for for Egyptian years
well you know our half term is 15
years quarter
term you should come back and run for uh
for for office there oh my God no no
there's a curse in Egyptian uh off
Egyptian presidency no nobody nobody
comes there like is dead or in jail yeah
it's uh it's not the most appealing job
they might make a statue of you though
make you look good after my
death I look look very good dead in a
statue uh yeah when you look at uh what
happened with
naali since you kind of really thought
about this in Egypt what happened with
navali in Russia what do you think about
that yeah but what happened inali in
Russia is not something new in Russia I
mean Putin have like this whole history
of poisoning and killing people and it's
kind of like pretty
much he's I I I would have to Sude
credit Putin he's like bringing us the
essence of the Dark Ages the Middle Ages
it's like you know we know like
basically Putin is like is the living
example of what happens if Game of
Thrones was
reality it's like death by poison like a
blow up a plane it's like mysteriously
disappears it is so it it is it is very
dark but it's like wow it's like a it's
it's it's a it's a it's a television
show
maybe that's what attracts us to that
part of the world is that it's so much
on display this game of uh of power of
geopolitics yeah of war no but the same
happens in the west but I'm behind
closed doors it's not that open it's not
it's not that pronounced you know it's
like oops uh
ipin
yeah it's
like we just like I think I think
because of the West is more advanced
like in movies and Cinemas we kind of
direct it better yeah I think I think
the outcome is like the way that you
kind of like said the scene like scene
and scene that's why people about like
landing on the moon they're
like I get it but you know we haven't
gone
back there's the
flat uh all right if we zoom out do you
think there will always be war in the
world always be suffering yes yeah
but here's the thing I don't think for
long I don't think that will happen for
long wait a minute yeah yeah because
here's the
thing humanity is destined to to have
War especially it will have War but that
something happened in the last 50 years
we have had now we have much more lethal
weapons MH the problem is the beginning
it's like swords against swords horses
Cavalry like cannons catapults me
missiles CH but now you like for like
you know like a press of a button you
can annihilate the whole planet yeah and
this is the problem Wars will all
continue the problem is when is going to
be the Tipping Point where we are
actually going to destroy ourselves and
it is so easy now to destroy ourselves
the amount of weapons and the the
quality of weapons that we have it is
designed to kill more effectively more
more more it just it is crazy it's like
we can create our own destruction in
ourself and I and I think we're not that
far away from it just look at nuclear
weapons the fascinating thing about
nuclear weapons as I've gotten to learn
recently just how few people are
involved in a full-on nuclear war that
kills basically kills everybody yeah
well three plus billion people right
away and the consequences of of the
nuclear
winter it's unlivable but all it takes
is I mean one president can do it so it
it could be even a false alarm
misunderstanding like what happened in
the Kuba Missile Crisis but
again and now
there's uh more nations are prepared and
ready to launch
yeah I don't know and and and you have a
media and a 24 hours kind of like thing
that makes you like at Edge the whole
time that's crazy there's a dark
perspective on this where there's
certain members of the media that would
kind of
enjoy the prospect of nuclear war like a
little bit just just let's get as close
to it as possible you have another
factor that will contribute to
that
religion and remember how like uh the
radical islamist talk about like the end
of time and whatever but like most
Islamic don't have that much power
problem is with Christian Zionist now
being on the top of the world with
America they have been pushing for that
kind of conflict to kind of escalate
escalate
listen to Sarah Palin like God wants us
here like car Trove all of the new cons
the dispensationalist Reagan there's an
incredible book called like forcing the
hands of gods oh beautiful book I read
it's like it's published 1998 but it
still matters today the whole idea about
like especially the the Zionist
Christians who love Israel but they hate
the Jews they're antisemite but they
love Israel because of its role this is
all basically formed because of the
interpretation of of the Bible of
scoffield and how they talk about the
end of time that Armageddon and then the
late great planet Earth and then left
behind Sirius and all of that it's all
about like we're heading to Armageddon
and the problem is Islam has there
people that believe that the end of time
and then we have the Christians that
believe in the end of time and then you
have Israel happy that those people are
using it for the end of time and then
the whole idea about them pushing as
many weapons and troops and people in
the Middle East to be there for the
nuclear Holocaust and John one of the of
the pastors talk about that about the
brim stones and it's going to be a
nuclear Holocaust all of that people
it's crazy how people are so despising
life that they are wanting death so now
you have you all would had these
Revelations but these Revelations mean
nothing if you don't have an effective
weapon in order to make it happen and
this is the crazy thing and I'm worried
that that the end is going to be by
someone that wants to meet God a little
bit
earlier uh uh somebody who's really in a
hurry mhm uh well I have good news for
you uh maybe we'll become a
multiplanetary species maybe Ellen musk
will will lead us lead the way to get
out in space maybe he's one of
them he a secret
lizard
um I asked you offline to not me mention
the lizard
people they are there's like a whole
people that believe in the lizard people
it's crazy I actually have to be honest
I haven't fully looked into the lizard
people I probably should you should yeah
well maybe I'm afraid of the
truth
uhing my removing my
face I mean what so let's say let's say
you're wrong about the end of the world
and and we it all turns
out great and Humanity
flourishes why would that happen what
what gives you
hope for that trajectory for
Humanity younger
people the people of Tik Tok that you
don't
like uh I I I yeah there is a lot of
like there you know after you
saying this people just keep sending you
Tik Tok videos these younger
people be this woman showing her boobs
that that woman that's going to save us
that's all right bosome thank you no
there's like I
think uh there is a wealth of you know
remember like the joke that said like we
thought that like when we have Internet
we going to have like be more you
know more informed and now we we
watching twerking videos and that is
true but on the other side the fact that
you have the in availability of
information I I'm learning a lot and
there's people who are using that
platform from that it's not the majority
because you know it's not very
interesting and exciting but I think
there's there might be a Tipping Point
where there's enough people that will be
aware and maybe they would collectively
do something in order to bring back the
power to the small man and maybe it
sounds very naive maybe but we don't
know we don't know because we you have
already seen the Legacy Media and the
Legacy politicians shaking in the past
few months they're getting nervous
they're getting nervous because people
are calling them out and those people
were like hiding behind their desk
behind in their offices and not like not
holding account for that but like people
now are calling them out and it is not
going to happen like this year or next
year but I think it's something what
advice would you give to those young
folks I will never give advice to those
people get off Tik Tok I know I will
never I will never because like their
input is different than mine yeah but
like there's there's one thing I learned
when people saw me did the Revolution
fail in Egypt did people that the people
re I like listen the revolution is it's
not an event it's not like hey we go in
with to the government it's not a
revolution A revolution is a process
it's a very long process and maybe the
pro that proc I mean as much as we don't
like what happened in the Arab world but
the people there the awareness that
happened and the discussions that have
been opened that were you didn't even
imagine what happened in the Middle East
is happening and maybe the beginning of
any any hope of change is that people
start talking speaking out talking about
stuff they were not allowed to to speak
about like for example
Israel the revolution continues ah
yes uh bossome you're you're a beautiful
human being it it's truly a pleasure and
honor to meet you I can just feel the
love radiating from you I hope I get to
see you perform live I hope to get to
see you many more times thank you for
being who you are thank you so much and
I would love to invite you for my new
special the islami
Bim that should be the title of you're
autobi thank you so much thank you
brother thanks for listening to this
conversation with bosam Yousef to
support this podcast please check out
our sponsors in the description and now
let me leave you some words from John
Stewart The Press can hold this
magnifying glass up to our problems
bringing them into Focus Illuminating
issues here to for unseen or they can
use that magnifying glass to light ants
on fire and then perhaps host a week of
shows on the sudden unexpected dangerous
flaming ant
epidemic if we amplify everything we
hear
nothing thank you for listening and hope
to see you next
time