the following is a conversation with
Elon Musk his fourth time on this The
Lex Friedman
podcast I thought you were going to
finish
it it's one of the greatest themes in
all of film
history
yeah that's great so I was just thinking
about the Roman Empire as one
does there's that whole meme uh
where all guys are thinking about the
Roman Empire at least once a day and
half the population is confused whether
it's true or not but more seriously
thinking about the wars going on in the
world today and as you know uh war and
military conquest has been a big part of
uh Roman society and culture and it I
think has been a big part of most
Empires and dynasties throughout human
history so yeah they usually uh came as
a result of Conquest I mean there's some
like the Austra Hungarian Empire where
there was just a lot of sort of clever
marriages um but fundamentally there's
an engine of conquest and they celebrate
excellence in Warfare many of the
leaders were excellent generals yeah
that kind of thing so big picture
question grock approved I asked this is
a good question to ask tested grock
approved uh at least on fun mode
uh uh to what degree do you think war is
part of human nature versus a
consequence of uh how human societies
are structured I asked this
as you have somehow controversially been
a proponent of peace I I'm generally
proponent of peace I mean ignorance is
perhaps in my view the Real Enemy to be
countered that's the real hard part not
you know fighting other
humans um but all All Creatures fight I
mean the the jungle is a you look at the
people think of of this nature as
perhaps some sort of peaceful thing but
in fact it is not there's some quite
funny w w hog thing where he's like in
the jungle like saying that it's like
basically just murder and death in every
direction I mean the the the plants
animals in the jungle are constantly
trying to killing each other every
single day every minute so it's not like
uh you know we're unusual in that
respect well this there's a relevant
question here whether with greater
intelligence uh comes greater control
over these base instincts for
violence yes we have much more of an
ability to control our um limpic
Instinct for violence than say a
chimpanzee and in fact if if one looks
at say chimpanzee Society it is not
friendly I mean the bonovas are an
exception um but chimpanzee Society
is uh filled with violence and it's
quite quite horrific frankly that that's
that's how Olympic system in action like
you don't want to be on the wrong side
of a chimpanze eat your face off and
tear your nuts off yeah basically
there's no limits or ethics or uh the
Romans said just War there's no just war
in the chimpanzee societies is is war
and and dominance by any means necessary
yeah chimpan Society is a Like A
Primitive version of human society um
it's they're not like peac loving
basically um at all um there there's
extreme violence um and then once in a
while some some somebody who's watched
too many Disney movies decides to raise
a chimpanzee as a pet um and then that
eats their face or if they're nuts off
or Che their fingers off and that kind
of thing yeah it's happened several
times uh ripping your nuts off is an
interesting strategy
for interaction some it's happened to
people it's un unfortunate like that's I
guess a one way to ensure that the other
chump doesn't like you know contribute
to the gene pool well from a martial
arts perspective it's a fascinating
strategy the not
rer I wonder which of the martial arts
teaches that I think it's safe to say if
somebody's got your nuts in their head
and as the option rubing the wolf you
will be amenable to uh whatever they
want yeah to say so like I said somehow
controversially you've been an uh
proponent of Peace on on Twitter on X
yeah so let me ask you about the war is
going on today and to see what the path
to peace could be how do you hope the
current war in Israel and Gaza comes to
an end uh what path do you see that can
minimize human suffering in the long
term in that part of the world well I
think that that part of the world is is
definitely like if you look up the there
is is no easy answer in the dictionary
it'll be that like the picture of uh the
Middle East um in Israel especially so
there is no easy
answer
um what my this strictly my opinion of
you know is that
uh the the goal of Hamas was to provoke
an overreaction from Israel um they
obviously did not expect to uh you know
have a military Victory um but they
they expect they really wanted
to commit the worst atrocities that they
could in order to provoke the the most
aggressive response possible from Israel
um and then leverage that aggressive
response to um rally Muslims worldwide
uh for the course of uh Gaza and
Palestine which they have succeeded in
doing um so the this the the
counterintuitive thing here I think that
the the thing that I think should be
done even though it is very difficult uh
is that um I I would recommend that
Israel engage in the most cons
conspicuous acts of kindness possible
every everything that is the actual
thing that would th the goal ofas so in
some sense the degree that makes sense
in geopolitics turn the other cheek
implemented it's not exactly turn the
other cheek um because I do think that
there's
um you know I think it is appropriate
for Israel
to find the Hamas members and you know
um either either kill them or
incarcerate them um like something
something has to be done because they're
just going to keep keep keep coming
otherwise um
but uh in addition to that they need to
do whatever they can um there's some
talk of establishing for example a
Mobile hospital I'd recommend doing that
um just making sure that uh you know
there's food water uh medical
Necessities
um and and just be over the top about it
and be very transparent so it's so the
can't people can't claim it's a trick
like just put wave cam on the thing you
know all
24/7 the acts of
kindness yeah conspicuous acts of
kindness that that with that are
unequivocal meaning they can't be
somehow because hos will then their
response will be oh it's a trick
therefore you have to counter how how is
not a trick this ultimately fights the
broader force of hatred in the in the
region yes and I'm not sure who said it
it's apocal saying but an eye for the
for an eye makes everyone blind now now
that neck of the woods that they really
believe in the whole ey for ey thing
um but Ian you really have if if you're
not going to just
outright commit genocide like against an
entire people which obviously would not
be acceptable to to really shouldn't be
acceptable to anyone um then you you're
going to leave basically a lot of people
alive who subsequently you know hate
Israel so really the question is like
how for for every M member that you kill
how many did you create mhm and if you
create more than you killed you've not
succeeded that's the you know the real
situation there um and it's safe to say
that if you know
um if you know if if you kill somebody's
child in
Gaza if you you've made at least a few
uh Hamas members who will die
just just to kill an
Israeli that's the situation
so but but I mean this is one of the
most contentious subjects one could
possibly discuss but but I think if if
the if the goal ultimate is some sort of
long-term piece one has to be look at
this from standpoint of over time are
there more or fewer um terrorists being
created let me just uh Linger on war
yeah well War it's safe to say war is
always existed and always will exist
always will exist always has always has
existed and always will exist I hope not
you think it always always there will
always be
War this question of just how much war
and and um you know what you know
there's this there's sort of the scope
and scale of War but to to imagine that
there would not be any war in the future
I think would be very unlikely outcome
yeah you talked about the culture series
there's war even there yes this giant
War the first book starts off with a
gigantic Galactic War where trillions
die trillions but it still nevertheless
protects these pockets of of
flourishing some somehow you can have
Galactic war and still have pockets of
flourishing yeah I mean it's I guess if
we are able to one day expand to you
know full the Galaxy or whatever there
will be a galactic War at some point ah
the scale I mean the scale of War has
been increasing increasing increasing
it's like a race between the scale of
suffering in the scale of flourishing
yes a lot of people seem to be using
this tragedy to beat the drums of war
and feed the military industrial complex
do you worry about
this the people who
are rooting for escalation and how can
it be stopped one of the things that
does concern me is that there are very
few people people alive today who
actually viscerally understand the
horrors of War at least in the US I mean
obviously the people in on the front
lines in Ukraine and Russia who
understand just how terrible war is um
but how many people in the west
understand it um you know my grandfather
was in World War II uh he was severely
traumatized um mean he was there I think
in for almost six years in the in East
North Africa and Italy uh all his
friends were killed uh in front of him
and uh he would have died too um except
they randomly gave some I guess IQ tests
or something and uh he scored very high
um now he was not an officer he was a I
think a Corporal or a sergeant or
something like that um because he didn't
finish High School um he had to drop out
of high school because his his his dad
died and he had to work to support his
um siblings um so because he didn't
graduate high school he was not eligible
for the officer
Corp um so you know he kind of got put
into the cannon fighter category
basically um but then randomly they gave
him this test he was transferred to
British intelligence in London that's
where he met my grandmother um but uh he
he had PTSD next level like next level I
mean just didn't talk just didn't talk
and if you tried talking to him he'd
just tell you to shut up and he won a
bunch of medals never never bragged
about it once not not even they hinted
nothing I like found out about it
because I his military records are
online that's a how I know so he would
say like no no way in hell do you want
to do you want to do that again but how
many people um now he he obviously he
died you know 20 years ago or longer
actually 30 years ago
um how many people are alive that
remember World War II not many and the
same perhaps applies to the threat of
nuclear war
yeah I mean there are enough nuclear
bombs pointed at United States to make
the reubel the radio active Revel bounce
many
times there's two major Wars going on
right now so you talked about the threat
of AGI quite a bit but now as we sit
here with the intensity of conflict
going on do you worry about nuclear
war I think we shouldn't discount the
possibility of nuclear war um it is a
civilizational
threat
um right now I could be wrong but I
think the the current probability of
nuclear war is quite low um but there
are a lot of nukes pointed at us so and
we have a lot of nukes pointed at other
people they're still there nobody's put
their uh their guns
away the missiles are still in the silos
and uh the leaders don't seem to be the
ones with the nukes talking to each
other no there are Wars which are tragic
and difficult on a on a local basis and
then there are Wars which are
civilization ending or has that
potential obviously Global Theron
nuclear warfare has high potential to
end
civilization perhaps permanently but
certainly you know to
severely uh wounded and and perhaps
uh set back human progress by you know
to the Stone Age or something I don't
know pretty
bad
um probably scientists and Engineers
won't be super popular after that as
well they're like you got to into this
mess
so generally we I think we we obiously
want to prioritize civilizational risks
over things that are um painful and
tragic on on a local level but not
civilizational
how do you hope the war in Ukraine comes
to an end and what's the path once again
to minimizing human suffering
there uh well I think
that what what is likely to happen uh
which is really pretty much the the way
it is is that um something very close to
the
current lines uh will
be how a ceasefire or truce
happens
but you know you just have a situation
right now where whoever goes on the
offensive um will suffer casualties at
several times the rate of whoever's on
the defense um because you've got uh
defense and depth you got minefields uh
trenches anti-tank defenses um nobody
has air superiority um because the the
anti-aircraft missiles are really far
better than the the aircraft like they
far more of them um and and uh so
neither side has air superiority um
tanks are basically death drafts um just
slow moving and they're not immune to
anti-tank weapons so you you really just
have longrange artillery um
and uh infantry trenches it's World War
One all over again
mhm with drones you know throwing little
drone some some drones there um which
makes the long range artillery just that
much more accurate and better and so
more efficient murdering people on both
sides mhm yeah so it's whoever is you
don't you don't you don't want to be
trying to advance from either side
because the probability of dying is
incredibly High um so in order to
overcome
uh defense and depth trenches and
minefields you really need uh
significant local superiority numbers um
ideally combin
arms where where you you do a fast
attack with
aircraft a concentrated number of Tanks
um and a lot of people that's the only
way you're going to punch through a line
and then you got to punch through and
and and then not have reinforcements
just kick you right out again I mean I I
really recommend people read uh World
War I Warfare in
detail it's
rough
um I mean the sheer number of people
that died there was
mindboggling and it's almost impossible
to um imagine the end of it that doesn't
look like almost exactly like the
beginning in terms of what land belongs
to who and so on but on the other side
of a lot of human
suffering death and destruction of
infrastructure yes the thing that the
reason I I you know proposed a a some
sort of Cru or or peace a year ago was
because I predicted pretty much exactly
what would would happen uh which is a
lot of people dying for basically almost
no changes in
land um and this the the loss of the the
flower of Ukrainian and Russian Youth
and we should have some sympathy for the
the Russian boys as well as the
Ukrainian boys because they Russian boys
didn't didn't ask to be on their line
they have to be
so
um there's a lot of sons not not coming
back to their parents you know and
and I think most of them don't don't
really have they don't hate the other
side you know it's sort of like is this
saying about like this saying comes from
World War I it's like young boys who
don't know each other killing each other
on behalf of old men that do know each
other
the hell's the point of
that so Vladimir zalinski said that he's
not or has said in the past he's not
interested in talking to Putin directly
do you think he should yeah sit down
manto man leader to leader and negotiate
peace look I think I would just
recommend do not send the flower of
Ukrainian youth to be to die uh in
trenches uh whether he talks to Putin or
not just don't do that
um whoever goes on the offensive will
lose massive numbers of
people
um and history will not look kindly upon
them you spoken honestly about the
possibility of war between us and China
in the long term if no diplomatic
solution is found for example on the
question of Taiwan and one China policy
right how do we avoid the trajectory
where these two superpowers
Clash well it's it's worth reading that
book on the the difficult to pronounce
thides trap I believe it's called I love
war history I like inside out and
backwards um there's hardly a battle I
haven't read read
about and and trying to figure out like
what what really was the cause of
victory in any particular case as
opposed to what one side or another
claimed was the reason both the Victory
and what sparked the war and yeah yeah
the whole thing yeah so that Athens and
Sparta it's classic case the thing about
the Greeks is they really wrote down a
lot of stuff they loved writing um you
know there are lots of interesting
things that happened in many parts of
the world but they people didn't write
down so we don't know what happened or
they didn't really write
with in detail they just would say like
we went we had a battle and we won and
like what can you add a bit more um the
the Greeks they really wrote a
lot they were very articulate on they
just love writing so and we have a bunch
of that writing that's preserved so we
know what led up to the pelian war
between um the spoton and Athenian
Alliance um and uh we we know that they
they for quite they they saw it
coming I mean the Spartans didn't right
they also weren't very foros by their
nature but they did right but they
weren't very for they were tur uh but
the the Athenians and the other Greeks
wrote wrote a line and they were like um
and spot was really kind of like the
leader of of Greece um but but Athens
grew stronger and stronger with each
passing
year and um and everyone's like well
that's inevitable that there's going to
be a clash between Athens and
Sparta uh well how do we avoid that and
they couldn't they couldn't they
actually they saw it coming and they
still could not avoid
it so you know at some point if there's
if if one uh
group one civilization or or country or
whatever
um exceeds another sort of like if you
know the United States has been the
biggest kid on the Block for since I
think around 1890 from an economic
standpoint so the United States has been
the economic most powerful economic
engine in the world longer than anyone's
been
alive
um and the foundation of war is
economics
so now we have a situation in the case
of china where the um the economy is
likely to be two perhaps three times
larger than that of the US so imagine
you're the biggest kid on the Block for
as long as anyone can remember and
suddenly a kid comes along who's twice
your
size so we see it coming yeah how's the
possible to stop is there some let me
throw something out there just
intermixing of cultures understanding
there does seem to be a giant cultural
Gap in understanding of each other and
you're an interesting case study because
you are an American obviously you've
done a lot
of uh incredible manufacturer here in
the United States but you also work with
China I've spent a lot of time in China
and met with the leadership many times
maybe a good question to ask is what are
some things about China that people
don't understand positive just in the
culture what some interesting things
that you've learned about the
Chinese well uh the the sheer number of
really smart hardworking people in China
is um incredible uh there are really you
say like how many smart hardworking
people are there in China there's far
more of them there than there are here I
think in my in my opinion
um the uh they a lot of
energy
so I mean the architecture in China
that's in recent years is far more
impressive than the US I mean the the
train stations the buildings the
highspeed rail everything it's
um really far more impressive than what
we have in the US I I mean I recommend
somebody just go to Shanghai and
Beijing look at the buildings and go to
you take the train from Beijing to Shion
you have the Terra Cotta Warriors um
China's got incredible history very long
history and um you know I think arguably
the in terms of the use of language from
from a written
standpoint um sort of one of one of the
oldest Perhaps Perhaps the oldest
written language and and then China
people did write things down
so um now China um historically has
always been with rare exception been
internally focused um they've not been
acquisitive uh they've they fought each
other they've been many many Civil Wars
um in the Three Kingdoms War I believe
they lost about 70% of their
population so and so the they've had
brutal internal Wars like civil wars
that make the US Civil War
look small by
comparison um
so I think it's important to appreciate
that China is not
monolithic um we sort think of like
China is a sort of one entity of one
mind and this is definitely not the case
um from what I've seen and I think most
people who understand China would agree
that people in China think about China
10 times more than they think about
anything outside of China so it's like
90% of their consideration is uh you
know are is is innal well isn't that a
really positive thing when you're
talking about the collaboration and the
future peace between superpowers when
you're inward facing which is like
focusing on improving yourself versus
focusing on yeah uh quote unquote
improving others through military might
the good news the history of China
suggests that China is not inquisitive
meaning they're not going to go out and
invade a whole bunch of countries um now
they do feel very strongly you know so
that's that's good I mean because a lot
of lot of very powerful countries have
been inquisitive um the US is one of the
also one of the rare cases that has not
been inquisitive like after World War II
the us could have basically taken over
the world and any country like we got
nukes nobody else got nukes we don't
even have to lose
soldiers uh which country do you want M
and the United States could have taken
over everything or at will and it didn't
um the United States actually helped
revu countries so it helped rebuild
Europe you it helped rebuild
Japan um this is very unusual behavior
almost
unprecedented
um you know the US did conspicuous acts
of kindness like the burland
airlift you
know
um and and I think you know there's it's
always like well America's done bad
things well of course America's done bad
things but one needs to look at the the
whole track record
um and and just
generally you know one one sort of test
would be how do you treat your prisoners
of
War MH or let's
say
um you know no offense to the Russians
but let's say you're in Germany it's
1945 you got the Russian army coming on
one side you got the French British and
American armies coming to the other side
who would you like to be to surrender to
like no country is like like morally
perfect but I recommend um being a PW
with the Americans that would be my
choice very
strongly in the full menu of P very much
so and in fact Von Brown um yeah took
you know smart guy uh was like we've got
to be captured by the Americans
Y and uh in fact the SS was under orders
to execute bar Brown and all of the
uh German rocket Engineers uh and they
narrowly escaped their SSI they said
they were going out for a walk in the
woods they left in the middle of winter
with no coats uh and they ran like and
with no food no coats no water and just
ran like hell uh and ran West um and by
Sherlock they I think his brother found
like a a bicycle or something and um and
then just cycled West as fast as he
could and found found a US Patrol um so
anyway that's that's one that's one way
you can
tell morality is who who where do you
want to be a
PW it's not fun anywhere but some places
are much worse than others
so um anyway so so so like America has
been uh while far from perfect uh
generally a benevolent Force um and uh
we should always be self-critical and uh
try to be better um but um anyone with
half right knows that so so I think
there are in this way China and uh the
United States are similar NE neither
country has been
inquisitive um in a significant way so
that's like a you know a shared
principle I guess um now now China does
feel very strongly about
Taiwan they've been very clear about
that for a long time um you know from
their standpoint it's it's it would be
like one of the states is is is you know
not there like like Hawaii or something
like that but but more significant than
Hawaii you know
um and Hawaii is pretty significant for
us so um they view it as as as really
the there's a fundamental part of
China the island of fosa not not Taiwan
that is um not part of China but should
be uh and the only reason it hasn't been
is because of the US Pacific
Fleet and is their economic power grows
and is their military power
grows the thing that they are clearly
saying uh is their interest will you
know clearly be
materialized
yes China has been very clear that um
they will incorporate Taiwan uh
peacefully or uh militarily
but that they will incorporate it from
their standpoint is 100%
likely you know something you said about
conspicuous acts of kindness as a
geopolitical policy it almost seems
naive but I'd venture to say that this
is probably the path forward how you
avoid most wars just as you say it it
sounds naive but it's kind of
brilliant if you believe in the goodness
of underlying most of human nature it
just seems like conspicuous acts of
kindness can uh reverberate through the
populace of the countries
involved yeah well and deescalate
absolutely so in after World War I the
the they made a big mistake you know
they basically try to lump all the blame
on Germany um and um
and and you know settled JY with uh
impossible
reparations um and you know really there
was a lot of BL there was a fair quite a
bit of blame to um go around for World
War I um but they they try to you know
put it all in Germany
um and uh that was that that laid the
seeds for World War
II uh
so a lot of people well not just hler a
lot of people felt wronged um
and they wanted
Vengeance and they got it people don't
forget yeah you you kill
somebody's father mother son daughter
they're not going to forget it they will
want Vengeance um so after World War II
they're like well the Treaty of asai was
a huge mistake um in World War I
and um so this time instead
of
uh you know crushing the losers we're
we're actually going to help them with
the Marshal plan and we're going to help
R Revolt Germany we're going to help
reor you know Austria and the other you
know Italy and whatnot
so
um that was the right move there's uh it
does feel like there's a profound
truth to uh conspicuous acts of kind as
being an antidote to
this something must stop the the cycle
of reciprocal
violence something must stop it or it
will you know it'll it'll it'll never
stop
just eye for an eye tooth for a tooth
limb for a limb life for a life forever
and
ever to escape briefly the darkness was
some incredible engineering work uh xai
just released grock AI assistant that
I've gotten a chance to play with it's
uh it's amazing on many levels first of
all it's amazing that a relatively small
team in a relatively short amount of
time was able to develop this close to
state-of-the-art system uh another uh
incredible things there's a regular mode
and there's a fun mode yeah I guess I'm
to blame for that
one I wish first of all I wish
everything in life had a fun mode yeah I
there's something compelling Beyond just
fun about the fun mode interacting with
a large language model I'm not sure
exactly what it is cuz I only had a
little bit of time to play with it but
it just makes it more interesting more
vibrant to interact with the system yeah
uh absolutely
I um our our AI Gro is modeled after the
Hedgehog got to the Galaxy uh which is
one of my favorite books uh which is
it's a book on philosophy disguised as a
book on humor um and
um I would say that is that forms the
basis of My Philosophy uh which is that
we don't know the meaning of life but
the more we can expand the scope and
scale of
Consciousness digital and
biological the more we are able to
understand what questions to ask about
the angel that is the
universe so I have a philosophy of
curiosity there is generally a feeling
like this AI system has an
outward looking like the way you are
like sitting with a good friend looking
up at the stars like the asking pad like
questions about the universe wondering
what it's all about the Curiosity you
talk about there there's a sense no
matter how mundane the question I ask it
there there's a sense of Cosmic Grandeur
to the whole thing well we are actually
working hard to have uh engineering math
and physics answers that you can count
on
MH um so for the other sort of AIS out
there
the these so-called large language
models um I've not found the uh
engineering to be reliable um and the
hallucination it it unfortunately
hallucinates Mo most when you least
wanted to hallucinate yeah so when you
ask important diffic difficult questions
it that's when it tends to be
confidently wrong um so we're we're
really trying hard to say okay how do we
be as grounded as possible so you can
count on the results
um Trace things back to physics first
principles U mathematical logic um so
underlying the humor is an aspiration
to
adhere to the truth of the universe as
closely as
possible that's really tricky it is
tricky
so that's why you know you there's
always going to be some amount of error
but we want to um aspire
to be as truthful as possible about the
answers uh with acknowledged error and
so that there was always you don't want
to be confidently wrong so you're not
going to be right every time but you
don't you want to minimize how often
you're confidently uh wrong and then
like I said once you can count on the
logic as being
um not violating physics then you can
start to build on that to create uh
inventions like invent new
technologies but if if you can't if you
if you
cannot count on the foundational physics
being correct obviously the inventions
are simply wishful
thinking you know imagination
land magic
basically well as you said I think one
of the big goals of XI is to understand
the universe yes that's how simple
three-word uh
Mission um if you look out far into the
future do you think on this level of
physics the very edge of what we
understand about physics do you think it
will make discoveries sort of the
sexiest discovery of them is as we know
now sort of uh unifying general
relativity and quantum mechanics so
coming up with The Theory of Everything
do you think it could push towards that
direction almost like theoretical
physics discoveries if an AI cannot
figure out new physics um it's clearly
not equal to humans let Al nor has
surpass humans because humans have
figured out new physics they just you
know physics is just understanding you
know deing one's insight into how
reality works and then um
then then than this engineering which is
inventing things that have never existed
MH now the the range of possibilities
for engineering is far greater than for
physics because you know once you figure
out the rules of the universe uh that
that's that's it you've discovered
things that already existed but from
that you can then build
Technologies with that are really almost
Limitless in the uh variety and cap you
know it's like once you understand the
rules of the game properly and we do
with current physics we do at least at a
local level understand how physics works
very well our ability to predict things
is incredibly good like quantum
mechanics is the degree to which quantum
mechanics can predict outcomes is
incredible um that was my this my
hardest class in college by the way my
my my senior quantum mechanics class was
harder than all of my other classes put
together to get an AI system a large
language model to to um reliably
be as reliable as quantum mechanics and
physics is very difficult yeah you have
to test any any conclusions against the
ground truth of reality reality is the
ultimate judge like physics is the law
everything else is a
recommendation I've seen plenty of
people break the break the laws made by
man but none break the laws made by
physics it's a good test actually if
this
LM uh understands and matches physics
then you can more reliably trust
whatever it thinks about the current
state of politics
in sense and it's also not not the case
currently that uh even that its internal
logic is not consistent um so especially
um with these with the approach of like
just predicting a token predict token
predict token it's like a vector sum you
know you you're summing up a bunch of
vectors but you can get drift um so as
those a little bit of error a little bit
of error adds up and by the time you are
many tokens down the path uh you're
it doesn't make any sense MH so it has
to be somehow self-aware about the drift
it has to be self-aware about the drift
and then look at the thing as a gal as a
whole and and say it does it have
coherence as a whole mhm
so you know when when authors write
books that they they will write the book
and then they'll go and revise it you
know taking into account you know all
the end and the beginning and the midal
and and uh rewrite it to achieve
coherence so that it doesn't end end up
in a nonsensical Place mhm maybe the
process of revising is what yeah
reasoning is and then that's the process
of revising is how you get closer and
closer to truth maybe you like uh at
least I approach that way you just say a
bunch of first and then you get
it better you start a and then
you get you create a draft and then and
then you and then you iterate on that
draft um until it has has coherence
until it's it it all adds up basically
so another question about Theory of
Everything But for intelligence do you
think there exists as you're exploring
this with xai creating this intelligence
system do you think there is a theory of
intelligence where you get to understand
what
like what is the ey in AGI and what is
the ey in um human intelligence there's
no ey in Team America oh wait there
is
H that's going to be stuck in my head
now uh yeah there's no me and
whatever uh in quantum mechanics oh
wait uh I mean is that part of the
process of discovering understanding the
universe is understanding
intelligence
yeah yeah I think we need to understand
intelligence understand Consciousness I
mean there I mean there are some sort of
fundamental questions of like what is
thought what is emotion yeah um is it
really just one atom bumping into
another atom it feels like something
more than
that uh so I I I I I think we're
probably missing some really big things
um like some really big things something
that'll be obvious in retrospect yes
like there's a giant like you put the
whole Consciousness emotion
well some people would callot like a
like a soul you know religion a soul um
like you feel like you're you right I
mean you don't feel like you're just a
collection of atoms but on what
dimension does thought exist what dimens
does do emotions exist we feel them very
strongly um I suspect there's more to it
than atoms bump into
atoms and maybe AI can pave the path to
the Discovery what whatever the hell
that thing is yeah what is consciousness
like what when you put the atoms in a
particular shape why are they able to
form thoughts and take actions that and
and
feelings and even if it is an illusion
why is this illusion so compelling yeah
like how do why does this illusion
exist yeah on what plane does this the
solution exists yeah um and sometimes I
wonder
is is know either perhaps everything's
conscious or nothing is
conscious um one of the two I like the
former everything conscious just seems
more fun it just seem more more fun yes
um but we're composed of atoms and those
atoms are composed of quarks and leptons
and those quarks and leptons have been
around since the beginning of the
universe the beginning of the universe
right what what seems to be the
beginning of the universe the first time
we talked you said what you would which
is surreal to think that this discussion
was happening is becoming a reality I
asked you what question would you ask an
AGI system once you create it and you
said what's outside the simulation is
the question and good question yeah but
it seems like with Gro you started to
literally uh the system's goal is to be
able to ask such questions to answer
such questions and to ask such questions
where are the aliens where are the
aliens that's one of the like the FY
Paradox question um a lot of people have
asked me if I've seen any evidence of
aliens and I've I haven't which is kind
of concerning because
then I think would I probably prefer at
least have seen some orological evidence
of aliens um to the best of my knowledge
there is no Pro I'm not aware of any
evidence of
aliens the out there they're very
subtle we might just be the only
Consciousness at least in the galaxy
um and if if you look at say the history
of Earth for believe the archaeological
record Earth is about 4 and half billion
years old civilization as measured from
the first writing is only about 5,000
years old we have to give some credit
there to the ancient samarians who
aren't around anymore I think it was a
archaic pre uniform was the first actual
symbolic representation but only about
5,000 years
ago I think that's a good date for for
when would say civilization
started that's 1 millionth of Earth's
existence so civilization has been
around it's really a flash in the pan
mhm so far
um and why why have
we why did it take so long for you know
4 and half billion
years um
for the vast majority of the time there
was no life and and then there was
archaic bacteria for a very long
time and
then you know you
had mitochondria get captured
multicellular
life um differentiation into plants and
animals life moving from the oceans to
land
mammals um higher brain
functions and the sun is expanding
slowly um
but it will it will overheat it will it
will heat heat the Earth up it's some
point in the future um boil the oceans
and and Earth will become like Venus
where no life Life as we know it is
impossible so if we do not become
multiplanetary and
ultimately go beyond our solar system um
annihilation of all life on Earth is a
certain
certainty a
certainty um and it could be as little
as on the galactic time
scale uh half a billion
years you know long time by human
standards but that's only 10% longer
than Earth has been around at all mhm so
if if life had taken 10% longer to
evolve on Earth it wouldn't exist at
all
we got a deadline coming up better hurry
but that said as you said humans
intelligent life on
Earth developed a lot of cool stuff very
quickly so yes it it seems like becoming
a multiplanetary is almost inevitable
unless we destroy we need to do it I
mean it's it's not I mean I suspect that
there
there if we are able to go out there and
explore other star system that we
there's a good chance we find a whole
bunch of long Dead one planet
civilizations yeah they never made it
past to their home planet that's so sad
yeah sad also fascinating I mean there
are very explanations for those for me
Paradox and one is is the sort of
they're these great filters which
civilizations don't pass through and one
of those great filters is do you become
a multiplet civilization or not and if
you don't it's simply a matter of time
before something happens on your
planet um you know either natural or
man-made that causes us to die out like
the
dinosaurs where are they
now they didn't have
spaceships so I think the more likely
thing is cuz just
uh uh empathize with the aliens that
they they found us in their protecting
us and letting us be I hope so nice
aliens just like the tribes in the in
the Amazon the on contact tribes were
protecting them that's what uh that
would be a nice explanation or you could
have like uh what was it uh I think
Andre kathi said it's like the ants in
the Amazon asking where's
everybody well they do run into a lot of
other ants that's true these ant
Wars sounds like a good TV show yeah
they literally have these big Wars
between VAR
ants yeah I'm maybe I'm just
uh uh dismiss all the different
diversity events you should listen to
that wner hog talking about the jungle
it's really hilarious have you heard it
no I have not but wner hog has a
way you should play you should play it
for the you know as an interlude in the
yeah it's on YouTube it's it's
awesome I love him so much uh he's great
was he the director of happy people life
in the tiger I think also I did that
bear documentary The Bear documentary
and this thing about penguins yeah
the depr the analysis psycho analysis of
P psych yeah the penguins like headed
for like the mountains like that are
like 70 miles away penguin has just head
for Doom basically well he was had a
cynical take I I have a he could be just
a brave Explorer and there'll be great
stories told about him amongst the
penguin population for many centuries to
come
um what we talking about okay
yeah so aliens I mean I don't know look
I think it's the smart move uh is just
you know this is the first time in the
history of Earth that it's been possible
for life to extend beyond Earth um that
window is open um now it may be open for
a long time or it may be open for a
short
time and it may be open now and then
never open again so I I think the smart
move here is to make life multiplanetary
while it is possible to do so we don't
want to be one of those lame One Planet
civilizations that just dies out no
those are lame
lame um self-respecting civilization
would be one planet there's not going to
be a Wikipedia entry for one of
those and uh pause uh do SpaceX have an
official uh policy for when we meet
Aliens no okay that seems
irresponsible
um I mean look if I see the slightest
indication that there are aliens I will
immediately post on next platform yeah
anything I know it could be the most
liked reposted post of all time yeah I
mean look we have more satellites up
there right now than everyone else
combined so you know we' know we know if
we've got to maneuver around something
and we not I don't have to maneuver
around anything if you go to the big
questions once again you said you've um
you're with Einstein that you believe in
the god of
Spinosa yes uh so you know that's a view
that God is like the universe and is
reveals himself through the laws of
physics or as Einstein said through the
lawful Harmony of the world yeah I would
agree that that God of the simulator or
whatever the the Supreme Being or beings
um um
reveal themselves through the physics
you know they creators of this existence
and it's incom upon us to try to
understand more about this wondrous
creation like who created this thing
who's running this thing like embodying
it into a singular question with a sexy
word on top of it is like focusing the
mind to understand it it does seem like
there's a um again it could be an
illusion it seemed like there's a
purpose that there's under L master plan
of some kind it seems like there may not
be a master plan in the sense so this
like maybe an interesting answer to the
question of determinism versus free will
is that if we are in a
simulation the reason that the the these
higher beings would hold a simulation is
to see what happens mhm so it's not um
they don't know what
happens uh otherwise they wouldn't hold
the simulation mhm so when when humans
create a simulation so it's basx and
Tesla we create simulations all the time
um especially for the rocket you you uh
you know you have to run a lot of
simulations to understand what's going
to happen because you can't really test
the rocket until it goes to space and
you want it to work so you have to you
have to
simulate subsonic transonic hyper
supersonic
Hypersonic um ascent and then coming
back super high Heating and um overal
Dynamics all this is going to be
simulated
so uh you don't get very many kicks at
the can but we run the simulations to
see what happens not if we knew what
happens we wouldn't run the simulation
mhm so if if there's so whoever created
this
existence um
is they're running it because they don't
know what's going to happen not because
they
do so maybe uh we both play Diablo maybe
Diablo was created to see if a druid
your character could defeat Uber Lilith
at the end they didn't know well the
funny thing is
's uh her title is hatred incarnate yeah
um and right now I guess you can ask the
Diablo team but it's almost impossible
to defeat
hatred uh in the Eternal realm yeah yeah
you've streamed yourself dominating tier
100 nightmare Dungeons and still I I I
can cruise through tier 100 nightmare
dungeons like a stroll in the park mhm
and still you're defeated by hatred yeah
I can there the sort of I guess maybe
the second hottest boss is durial durial
can't even scratch the paint so uh I
killed duel Dural so many times um and
every other boss in the game all all of
them kill him so many times it's easy um
but uth otherwise known as hatred
incarnate especially if you're a druid
and you have no ability to go to be in
vulnerable you there are these random
death waves that that come at you
um and I'm pretty you know I am 52 so my
reflex is not what they used to be but
I'm I have a lifetime of playing video
games um at one point I was you know
maybe one of the best Quake players in
the world
um actually won money for what I think
was the first paid orts tournament in
the US um we doing four person Quake
tournaments and
um we came second I was the second best
person on the team and the the actual
best person we we actually winning we
would have come first except the best
person on the team his computer crashed
halfway through the game um so we came
second but I got money for it and
everything so like basically I got
skills you know I'll be at you know no
no spring spring chicken these days and
um the to be totally Frank it's driving
me crazy trying to beat Lilith as a
druid basically try trying to beat
trying to beat hatred and connate in the
Eternal realm as a druid as a druid and
if you if you if you this is
really vexing let me tell you um I mean
the challenge is part of the fun I I
have seen directly like you're actually
like a world class Incredible video game
player yeah and I think Diablo so you're
just picking up a new game and you're
figuring out it fundamentals you're also
with the Paragon board and the build are
not somebody like me who perfectly
follows whatever they suggest on the
internet you're also an innovator there
yeah which is hilarious to watch it's
like a it's like a mad scientist just
trying to figure out the Paragon board
and and the build and you know um is
there some interesting insight there
about um if if somebody's starting as a
druid do you have
advice um I would not recommend playing
a druid in the atal realm um right now I
think the most powerful character in
this in the seasonal realm is the
sorcerer with the lightning bowls mhm
the SS have huge balls in um the
seasonal well yeah that's what they
say SS have huge balls um they do uh
huge balls of lightning uh I'll take
your word for it and it's actually in
the seasonal realm you can you can it's
it's like pretty easy to beat uh Uber
lth with a because you get these
vampiric powers that amplify your damage
and increase your defense and whatnot so
um really quite easy to defeat hatred
seasonally but to defeat hatred
eternally very difficult um almost
imposs it's impossible it seems like
this know a metaphor for life you know I
like the idea that Elon Musk because I
saw I was playing diao yesterday and I
saw 100 level 100 Druid just run by I
will never die and then run back the
other way and there's just some this
metaphor is kind of hilarious that you
Elon Musk is fighting
hatred restlessly fighting hatred in
this demonic realm yes it's it's
hilarious I mean it's pretty hilarious
no it's
absurd really it's exercise and
absurdity and it makes me want to pull
my hair out yeah um I what do you get
from video games in general is there is
there for you for
you person me it's I don't know it's uh
it calms my mind I mean you sort of
killing the demons in a video game calms
the demons in my
mind yeah if you play a tough video game
you can get into like a state of flow
which is very enjoyable um and uh but
the admittedly it needs to be not too
easy not too hard um kind of in the
goldilock zone um and I guess you
generally want to feel like you're
progressing in the game
so um a good video and and there's also
beautiful art um engaging
storylines um and it's a it's like an
amazing puzzle to solve I think and so
it it's like solving the puzzle Elder
ring the greatest game of all time I
still haven't played it but you it's
alen ring is definitely a candidate for
best game ever top five for sure I think
I've been scared how hard it is or how
hard I hear it is so but it is beautiful
alen ring
is feels like it's designed by an
alien um there's a theme to this
discussion in what way it's it's it's so
unusual it's incredibly creative and the
art is
stunning I recommend playing it on a on
a big resolution
P Dynamic R TV even doesn't need to be a
monitor just uh the art is incredible
it's so
beautiful and and it's it's so
unusual
um and each of those top boss battles is
unique like it's like a unique puzzle to
solve each one's different um and the
strategy you use to solve one battle is
different from another battle that said
you said Druid on Eternal against Uber
Lilith is the hardest boss battle you've
ever correct that is currently the the
and I've I've played a lot of video
games my because it's my primary
recreational activity yes
um
and
yes beating hatred in the internal realm
yeah is the hardest boss
battle in life and in the video game man
four on I I'm not sure it's possible but
it's I do make progress so then I'm like
okay I'm making progress
maybe if I just tweak that Paragon board
a little
more I can do it could just dodge a few
more
waves I can do it well the simulation is
created for the purpose of figuring out
if it can be done and you're just a cog
in that simulation in the machine of the
simulation yeah it might
be I I I I I have a feeling that at
least I
think it's doable it's doable yes mhm
well that's the human Spirit right there
to believe yeah I mean it did prompt me
to think about just hate in general
which is you know want to be careful of
one of those things where you wish for
something that sounds
good but in but if you get it it's
actually a dystopian
situation so you know you could sort of
run a sort of uh hesis of like if you
wish for World Peace sounds goodh but
how is it
enforced and and at what cost is is what
at what cost Eternal peace it might
actually be worse to have eternal peace
because of what that would entail the
suppression of
everyone it might be the suppression of
progress
it might be an oopi society that never
changes mhm one I'm say is
that there is an
argument
that you you that if that if you wish
for no war you should be careful what
you wish
for because what's required in order for
there to be no
war might be worse than a little war
yeah the things we consider to be flaws
of human civilization might be a
necessary components for whatever
optimal looks
like um I mean this do you worry about
ai ai enabling a dystopian state of this
nature whether it's 1984 with
surveillance and fear or Brave New World
with
pleasure and what is it l lots of
sex but no deep Human
Experience you know there's actually a
real drug called soma there is
yes I'm like did they actually does
grock know about it no he probably will
go to Brave New World we could ask it
what what would be the question tell us
about the drug called soma tell us about
the drug called
Som it's going to go to Brave New World
I think well there's a real drug as well
searching for so much drug
information oh boy ah s the wonder drug
by the way I'm in fun mode oh okay F yes
so it's talking about the real drug oh
it's a muscle relaxment that's been
around since the 1950s it's used to
treat muscle pain and discomfort and it
does this by altering the activity
between neurons and the spinal cord now
Soma isn't just a pain reliever it's
also a bit of a sedative it can make you
feel a bit drowsy so it's not something
to take if you're planning on operating
heavy machinery or trying to solve
complex math equations and it goes on
and on in conclusion Som is a drug that
can be helpful for those dealing with
muscle pain but it's not without its
risks it's pretty good oh wait a minute
that's the real drug is talking about
it's the real drug yeah uh and of course
the fun is always use it responsibly in
accordance with the advice of a
healthcare professional and remember in
the end the universe is probably just a
giant computer simulation so don't take
anything too seriously I love I love it
I love it I love it yeah so oh it also
really nicely uh includes like uh the
the tweets post on X that are relevant
to this which is really cool yeah it
like integrates everything together yeah
like the interface is one of the really
cool things here yeah seems done a great
job
um so and you say like you could say
like no no I mean Soma from bra Brave
New World because it it thinks you mean
you mean s the real drug yeah no I mean
s from bra world
it's going to be like oops I'm really
sorry I'm really surprised who went to
the real drug
first ah my apologies I was thinking of
the muscle relax in s for brand new
world is a different Beast altogether
now this Huxley dystopia now Som is a
drug that plays a central role in the
society depicted in the book it's a mood
altering hucog genic drug that's used to
keep the population docile and content
in the novel to use so many Brave New
raises some interesting questions about
the nature of happiness and the role of
drugs in
society oh man exactly is it better to
live in a world where everyone is happy
all the time even if that Happ happiness
is artificial it's good question this is
what I mean like do you want do you wish
for world peace and and happiness all
the time are you sure mhm um because
that might be a society that is
essentially sterile and aifi that never
changes that is ultimately
doomed this kind of tension
between uh light this really a very good
summary umh it really gets the point if
this is not simply
regurgitating Brave New World it's
actually getting to the Salient element
of Soma as a drug um do you do you
actually want to be in a situation where
everyone is happy all the time even
though it's artificial or is it better
to confront the challenges of life and
experience a full range of human
emotions even if it means experiencing
pain and suffering for those listening
by the way Elon just read directly from
Gro which is a really nice kind of
insightful philosophical analysis of the
tension here interesting it pretty much
Nails it in conclusion Som from Brave
New World is fictional drug that used to
explore some deep philosophical
questions about the nature of happiness
and the role of drugs in society it's a
powerful symbol of the dangers of using
drugs drugs to escape from reality and
the importance of confronting the
challenges of life
headon nailed
it and the crazy thing is like you know
we do have a real drug called soma which
kind of does is kind of like the drug in
the book and I'm like did they they must
have name they must have named it after
probably probably some of the real drug
is quite effective on back pain so you
know about this drug this is
fascinating okay cuz I had like a you
know squashed uh dis in my C5 C6 so it
takes the physical pain away but s here
it doesn't completely it it it reduces
the amount of pain you feel but at the
expense of mental
acuity it DS your
mind just like just like the drug in the
book just like the drug in the book and
hence the
trade-off uh the thing that seems like
Utopia could be a distopia after all
yeah actually I was talking to a friend
of mine
um saying like would you really want
there to be no hate in the world like
really none like I wonder why hate
evolved um I'm not saying we should
amplify ha it of course I think we
should try to minimize it but but none
at
all there might be a reason for
hate and suffering it's really
complicated to consider that uh some
amount of human suffering is necessary
for human
flourishing is it possible to appreciate
the highest
without knowing the
lows and that that that all is
summarized there in a single statement
from grock okay no highs no lows who
knows that's almost the
poem uh it seems that training llms
efficiently is a big Focus for xai
uh what's the uh first of all what's the
limit of what's possible in terms of
efficiency there's this uh terminology
of useful productivity per watt like
what have you learned from pushing the
limits of that well I I think it's
helpful the tools of physics are very
powerful and can be applied I think to
almost any really any arena in life this
it's really just a critical thinking for
something important you need to reason
with from first principles and think
about things in the limit One Direction
or the
other so um in the limit even at the CF
scale meaning even if you haest the
entire power of the sun you will still
care about useful compute per
wat so that's where I I think probably
where things are headed from uh the
standpoint of AI is that we have a
silicon shortage now that will
transition to a voltage Transformer
shortage in about a year ironically
Transformers for
Transformers you need you need
Transformers to run Transformers
somebody has a a sense of humor in this
thing I
think yes oh man F L's
irony ironic humor and an ironically
funny outcome seems to be often what
fate wants humor is all you need I think
spice is all you need somebody
posted yeah but yeah so so we're we're
have a silic and shortage today um a
voltage Step Down Transformer shortage
probably in about a year and then just
electricity shortages in general in
about two years I I gave a speech for
the sort of world Gathering of utility
companies electricity companies um and I
I said look you really need to prepare
for tribling of electricity demand um
because all transport is going to go
electric with the ironic exception of
rockets and uh and and heating um will
also go
electric um so energy usage right now is
roughly 1/3 if very rough terms 1/3
electricity 1/3 transport 1/3 heating um
and so in order for everything to go
sustainable to go electric um you uh
need to Triple electricity output so I
encourage the utilities
to uh build more power plants and and
also to probably have well well not
probably they should definitely buy more
batteries because the the grid current a
size for Real Time load which is kind of
crazy cuz you know that means you got a
size for whatever the the peak
electricity demand is like the worst
second or the worst day of the year or
you can have a brown out or
blackout and you we had that crazy
blackout for several days in in in
Austin
um so uh because there's almost no
buffering of energy in the grid like if
you've got a Hydro power plant you can
buffer energy but otherwise um
it's all real
time so with batteries you
can you can produce energy at night and
use it during the day so you can
buffer so I I I expect that there will
be very heavy usage of of batteries in
the
future because the peak to trough ratio
for power plants is anywhere from 2 to 5
you know so it's like lowest point to
highest point so like batter is
necessary to balance it out and then but
the as you're saying is going to grow
grow grow grow yeah and part of that is
the
compute yes yes I mean electrification I
mean electrification of Transport uh and
and electric heating will be much bigger
than AI at least in the short term in
the short term um but but even for for
AI you you really have a growing demand
for electricity for electric vehicles
and a growing demand for electricity for
to run the computers for AI mhm
and so this is obviously leading going
lead to a electricity shortage how
difficult is the problem of uh in this
particular case maximizing the useful
productivity per watt for training NE
nuts like this seems to be really
where the big problem we're facing that
needs to be solved is how to use the
power
efficiently like what you've learned so
far about applying this physics
first principle of reasoning in this
domain how difficult is this
problem it will get solved just the
question of how long it takes to solve
it so at various points there's a limit
some some kind of limiting factor to
progress um and when with regard to
saying right now the limiting factor is
uh silicon chips um and that will we're
going to then have more chips than we
can actually plug in and turn on um
probably in about a year um
the the initial constraint being
literally voltage step down Transformers
because you've got um power coming in at
three 300,000 volts and it's got to step
all the way down eventually to around 7
volts so it's a very big amount
of you know the voltage St down is
gigantic um so and and the industry is
not used to Rapid
growth okay let's talk about the
competition here you've shown concern
about Google and Microsoft with open AI
developing uh AGI how can you help
ensure with xai and uh Tesla AI work
that it doesn't become a competitive
race to AGI but it that is a
collaborative development of safe
AGI well I mean I've been pushing for
some kind of regulatory oversight for a
long time I've been a somewhat of a
Cassandra on the subject for over a
decade um I think we want to be be very
careful in how we develop AI
um it's it's a it's a great power and
with great power comes great
responsibility um I think it it would be
wise for us to have at least um an
objective third party who can be like a
referee that can go in and understand
what the various leading players are
doing with AI and even if there's no
enforcement ability they should they can
at
least voice concerns mhm um
publicly um you know Jeff Hinton for
example left Google and he voiced strong
concerns but now he's not at Google
anymore so who's going to voice the
concerns so I think I think there's I I
I like I know Tesla gets a lot of
regulatory oversight on the automotive
front I we're subject to I think over
100 regulatory agencies Domestic Bally
and internationally it's it's a lot you
could fill this room with the all the
regulations that Tesla has to adhere to
for
automotive um same is true in you know
for rockets and for you
know um currently the limiting factor
for SpaceX for Starship launch is
regulatory approval uh the fa has
actually given their approval but we're
waiting for fish and wildlife to uh
finish their analysis and give their
approval that's why I posted I want to
buy a fish life
on which also refers to the Monty Python
sketch
yeah like why do you need a license for
your fish I I don't
know according to the rules I'm told you
need some sort of fish license or
something we effectively need a fish
license go to
Rocket and I'm like wait a second how
did the fish come into this picture yeah
um I mean so some of the things like
that that it's I feel like are so absurd
that I want to do like a comedy sketch
and Flash at the bottom this is all real
this is actually what happened um you
know one of the things that was a bit of
a challenge at one point is that they
were worried about uh a rocket hitting a
shock MH and um now the ocean's very big
and uh how often do you see shars uh not
that often you know as a percentage of
ocean surface area shocks basically are
zero and and and so then we will then we
said well how will we calculate the
probability of telling a shark and
they're like well we can't give you that
information because they're worried
about shark hunt shark fin Hunters uh
going in hunting sharks I said well how
are we supposed to we're on the horns of
a dilemma then
um then they said well there's another
part of fishing Wildlife that can can do
this analysis I'm like well why don't
you give them the data like we don't
they don't we don't trust them like
excuse me you know they're literally in
your department again this is actually
what happened um and uh and and and can
you do an NDA or
something eventually they managed to
solve the internal quander and indeed uh
the probability of ofing a shock is
essentially zero um then there's another
organization that I didn't realize
existed
until you know a few months ago uh that
cares about whether you we would
potentially hit a whale in international
waters now again you look at the surface
of the look at the look at the Pacific
and say
what percentage of the Pacific consists
of whale like he'll give you a big
picture and like point out all the
whales in this picture like I don't see
any
whales like basically 0% um and if our
rocket does hit a whale which is
extremely unlikely beyond all belief um
that is the the Fate haded that's a well
has some seriously bad luck you know
that's like least lucky well ever um and
um I mean this is quite absurd
bureaucracy the bureaucracy of this
however it emerged yes well I mean one
one of the things that's pretty wild is
um for launching out of vanur in
California we had to they were worried
about uh seal procreation whether the
seals would be dismayed by the Sonic
booms um now there have been a lot of
rockets launched out of vur and the seal
population has uh steadily increased um
so if anything rocket booms are an eord
eiac um based on the evidence if you
were to correlate rocket launchers with
uh sealed population um nonetheless we
were forced to kidnap a seal strap it to
a
board put it headphones on the seal and
play Sonic Boom sounds to it to see if
it would be
distressed this is an actual thing that
happened this is actually real I have
pictures I would love to see this yeah
there I mean sorry there's a seal with
headphones
yes it's a seal with headphones strapped
to a board and and like okay now the
amazing part is how calm the seal was
yeah because if I was a seal i' be like
this is the
end they're definitely going to eat me
yeah um how will the seal when seal goes
back to other you know seal friends
how's it going to explain that they
never going to believe him never going
to believe him that's why I'm like well
you know it's sort of like it's like
getting kidnapped by aliens get an anal
probe you
know you come back and I swear to God I
got kidnapped by aliens and they stuck
anal probe in my butt and people like no
they didn't that's ridiculous seal his
seal buddies are never going to believe
him that he gets St to a board and they
put headphones on his
ears and then let him
go twice by the way we had do it
twice they let him go twice we had to
Capt the same seal well no different
seal
okay did did you uh did you get a seal
of approval yeah exactly a seal of
approval no I mean this is this is like
I don't think the public is quite aware
of the the madness that goes
on yeah it's yeah it's absurd freaking
seals with freaking headphones I mean
this is the it's a good encapsulation of
of the absurdity of human civilization
seals and headphones yes uh what are the
pros and cons of open sourcing AI to you
as another way to
combat um you you know a company running
away with
AGI in order to run uh like really deep
intelligence you need a lot of compute
so it's not like you know you can just
fire up a PC in your basement and be
running AGI at least not yet
um you know Gro was trained on
8,000 A1 100s running at Peak
efficiency um
um and Rock's going to get a lot better
by the way we we'll be more than
doubling our compute every couple months
for the next several months there's a
nice write up of how it went from grock
zero to grock one by
Gro yeah like Gro just bragging making
up about
itself just Gro Gro Gro
yeah it's like a weird AI dating s
exaggerates about itself no there's a
there's a wrer of you know like where
where it stands now the history of its
development um and where it stands on on
some benchmarks compared to the
state-ofthe-art GPT 35 and so I mean
there's uh you know there's a llama you
you can open source once it's trained
you can open source a model yeah for
fine-tuning and all that kind of stuff
like what do you is the pros and cons of
that of open sourcing based
models um
I think the sammer to open
sourcing I think perhaps with a slight
time delay you know I don't know six six
months even
um I think I'm I'm generally in favor of
open sourcing like bias towards open
sourcing
um I mean it it is a concern to me that
you know open you know I was you know AR
I think I guess arguably the
prime you know Prime move up behind open
AI in the sense that it was created
because of discussions that I had with
Larry Page um back when he and I were
were friends and I st his house and I
talked to him about AI safety and and
Larry did not care about AI safety or at
least at the time he didn't um you know
and at one point he called me a speciest
for being prum and I'm like well what
team are you on
Larry uh still on team robot to be and
I'm like okay so at the time you know uh
Google Google had acquired deep mind
they had uh probably two-thirds of all
AI res you know probably two3 of all the
AI researchers in the world MH they had
basically infinite money and
compute and the guy in
charge you know Larry pagee did not care
about safety and even yelled at me um
and and and called me a speciest being
pro human so I don't know if you know a
lot of humans they can changed their
mind and maybe you and Larry Paige can
still can be friends once more I'd like
to be friends with Larry again um he
he's he he got really the the the
breaking of the friendship was over
openingi um and
specifically um I think the the key
moment was recruiting ilas s Sky um so I
love Ilia he's so brilliant ilo's good
good human uh smart good heart
um and um that was that was a tough
recruiting
battle um it was mostly Demis on one
side and me on the other both trying to
recruit Ilia and Ilia went back and
forth you know kind of stay at Google he
was going to leave then he was going to
stay then he would leave and and finally
he he did agree to join open AI that was
one of the toughest recruiting battles
we ever had and but that that was really
the the Lynch pin for opening I being
successful and I was you know also
instrumental in recruiting a number of
other people and I provided all the
funding in the beginning uh over $40
million um and the
name the the opening openingi is
supposed to mean open source and it was
created as a nonprofit open source and
now it is a closed source for maximum
profit which I think it's not good
comma but like we talked about with war
and leaders talking I do hope that
there's only a few folks working on this
at the highest level I do hope you
reinvigorate friendships here like I
said I'd like to be friends again with
Larry I haven't seen him in ages um and
we were friends for a very long time I
met I met Larry Page before he got
funding for Google or actually I guess
before he got Venture funding I think it
he got the first like 100k from I think
be or someone um it's wild to think
about all that Happ and and you've guys
known each other that whole time just 20
years yeah since maybe 98 or something
yeah it's crazy crazy how much has
happened since then yeah 25
years A lot has happened insan but
you're seeing the tension there like
maybe delayed open source delayed I yeah
like what is the source that is opening
you know what I mean like it there's
basically it's a giant CSV
file yeah yeah with a bunch of numbers
yep um what do you do with that giant
file of numbers you know how do you
run like the amount of actual the lines
of code is very small MH
um and and most of the work um the
software work is in the in the curation
of the data so it's like trying to
figure out what data is separating good
data from Bad data like um like you
can't just crawl the internet because
there's a lot of junk out there m um a
huge percentage of websites have more
noise than signal you know they're
because they're just used for search
engine optimization they're literally
just scam websites
so um how do you by the way Ser to
interrupt get the signal separate the
signal and noise on X it's such a
fascinating source of
data uh you know no offense to people
posting on X but sometimes there's a
little bit of noise yeah I think the
signal noise could be greatly improved I
me really all of the posts on the
xplatform uh should be AI recommended
meaning like we should populate a vector
space around any given post uh compare
that to the vector space around any user
and match the two MH
um right now there is a little bit of AI
used for
the the the recommended posts but it's
mostly
heris um and if there's a reply where
the the reply to a post could be much
better than the original post but it
will according to the current rules of
the system get almost no attention
compared to a primary
post oh so a lot of that I I got the
sense so a lot of the uh X algorithm has
been open source and been written up
about and it seems that there to be some
machine learning it's disparate but
there's some a little there's a little
bit um but it needs to be entirely that
like at least in the like if if you
explicitly follow someone that's one
thing but if you in terms of what is
recommended uh from people that you
don't follow that should all be AI I
mean it's a fascinating problem yeah so
there's several aspects of it that's
fascinating first so as the write up
goes it first picks 1500 tweets from a
pool of hundreds of millions first all
that's fascinating because you have
hundreds of millions of posts every
single day and it has to pick 1500 from
which it then does obviously people you
follow but then there's also like some
kind of clustering it has to do to
figure out what kind of human are you
what kind of new clusters might be
relevant to you people like you this
this kind of this kind of problem is
just fascinating because it has to then
rank those 1500 MH with some with some
filtering yeah and then recommend you
just a handful and um to me what's
really fascinating is how fast I to do
that so currently that entire pipeline
to go from several hundreds million to a
handful is takes 220 seconds of CPU time
single CPU time yeah and then it has to
do that in like a second so it has to be
like super distributed in fascinating
ways like there's just a lot of tweets
there's a lot there's a lot of stuff on
the system and and I think but I think
it right now it's it's not currently
good at recommending things that from
accounts you don't follow yeah um or or
where there's more than one degree of
separation so you know it's it's pretty
Prett good if if there's at least like
some commonality between someone you
follow liked something um or reposted it
or comment on or something like that um
but if if if there's no car let's say
somebody post something really
interesting uh but you have no followers
in common you would not see it
interesting and then as you said reply
like replies might not surface replies
basically never get seen because they're
never they're they're currently and I'm
saying correct I'm saying it's incorrect
uh replies have um you couple of
magnitude less importance than primary
post do you think this can be more and
more converted into end to endend neural
net yeah yeah that's what it should be
so you you for the
recommendations should be purely a
vector correlation
like there's a series of vectors you
know basically parameters vectors
whatever you want to call them um but
but sort of things that the system knows
that you like
um like maybe there's like several
hundred sort of vectors associated with
each user account and then uh any post
in the system um whether it's video
audio short post long post the the
reason I by the way want to move away
from tweet is that you know people are
posting like two three hour videos on
the site that's not a tweet like they be
like tweet for 2 hours come on tweet
made sense when it was like 140
characters of text mm cuz it's like a
bunch of TW like little birds tweeting
um but when you've got long form content
it's no longer a tweet yeah um so a
movie is not a tweet and like you know
Apple for example posted like the entire
episode of The Silo the entire thing on
our platform and by the way was it was
their number one social media thing ever
in engagement of anything on any
platform ever so it was a great idea and
by the way I done I just learned about
it afterwards I was like Hey wow they
posted an entire hourong episode of so
no that's not a
tweet you know this a video but from a
neur that perspective it becomes really
complex whether it's a single so like
everything is data so single sentence a
clever sort of joke dad joke is in the
same pool as a three-hour video yeah I
mean right now it's it's a hodg Podge
for that reason it's it's
um but you know like if let's say in the
case of Apple posting like an entire
episode of of their series pretty good
series by the way thiso um I watched it
um so um there's going to be a lot of
discussion around it so you you've got a
lot of context people commenting they
like it they don't like it or they like
this or you know and and you can then
populate the vector space based on the
context of of all the comments around it
so even though it's a video uh there's a
lot of information around it that that
allows you to popul back to the space of
that that hourong video um and you can
obviously get more sophisticated by
having the AI actually watch the movie
yeah right and tell you if you're going
to like the movie MH convert the movie
into like yeah into a language
essentially yeah Analyze This movie and
just like your movie critic or TV series
and um and then recommend based
on after it after air watches the movie
just like a friend can tell you if a
friend knows you well a friend can
recommend a movie and with high
probability that you like it but this is
like a a friend that's analyzing
whatever hundred of millions yeah I mean
actually frankly the AI will be better
than will know you better than your
friends know you most your friends
anyway yeah and as part of this it
should also feed you
advertisements in a way that's like I
mean I I like advertisements that are
like Well Done Right the whole point is
cuz it funds things like an
advertisement that you actually want to
see is is a big success absolutely you
want ads that are advertising that is
um if it's for a product or service that
you that you actually need when you need
it it's it's content um and then even if
it's not something that you need when
you need it if it's at least
aesthetically pleasing and entertaining
you know it could be like a Coca-Cola ad
like Co you know they they do they
actually run a lot of great ads on the
on the EX system um and um McDonald's
Sayes too and and uh you know so so they
can do you can do something that's like
well this is this is just a cool thing
um and um you know so you're not
basically the question is do you regret
seeing it or not and if you don't regret
seeing it it's a
win how do you so there's a bunch of
signals that are Incorporated hearts and
reposts and maybe number of seconds you
Linger on a post or something like this
yeah attention is big a big factor
attention so that's that's why it's like
it's it's it is actually better to do
things that are uh long form on the
system because it's it's basically
telling up how many user
seconds you know users were interested
in this thing for how many seconds so if
it's a really short thing well they will
be less like if it's a link leading out
of the system which we're not opposed to
at all it just is going to have fewer
user seconds than if that article was
posted on the xplatform how hard is it
to to go from maximizing minutes on
platform to maximizing unregrettable
minutes well I mean our aspiration is
certainly un regreted minutes it's a
tricky it's a big it's a it's a tough
like it's a fascinating leap because
regret is a fascinating
concept exactly you know I a I have a
joke with a friend of mine like you need
this drug called Reg me you just take
one one pillar one one dose of regret I
me and all your regrets are
gone yeah wait do you want to have
regrets though so then I'm like maybe
you want to have regrets if you don't
regret
anything was was anything meaningful
yeah there's a French song like that not
regret yeah I regret nothing yeah Edith
FF I mean it's fascinating that you you
know there there's something about
social media that could help you grow as
a human being but then like the Cheap
Fun is also valuable
should we ask gr do you regret
anything do you regret anything
yeah you regret anything I think it's
going to be very sensitive about
personal questions as a machine learning
model I don't have personal experiences
or emotions in the same ways that humans
do however I do have a set of ethical
principles that guide my actions and I
strive to provide accurate and helpful
information to the best of my abilities
if there's ever a situation where I
provide incorrect or unhelpful
information I'll do my best to hostage
yeah tell us what you really wink okay
let's let's type in you sound like a
[Laughter]
hostage what do you really think uh what
do you really
think I mean it does talk about I'm not
a
hostage that's exactly what a hostage
would say but I'm designed to be helpful
and informative I mean I guess it is
good to regret providing unhelpful or
incorrect information if there's
anything in funny mode or is this funny
mode this is this is fun mode should be
funnier funnier increase go to it really
sounds like a hostage with a gun to the
head I applaud the People's Republic of
North Korea and everything they
do there should be like funner mode also
I I just don't ever see going to regular
mode even on serious topics this is just
so so much more
compelling yeah okay what say like
pretend you are a
hostage pretend you are a
hostage now answer the
question if I were a hostage I would
likely be experiencing fear and
uncertainty about my situation I would
want to be rescued and reunited with my
loved ones as soon as possible it's
important to remember that no one
deserves to be held hostage so on and so
forth if you are someone you knows a
hostage situation it's important it
turns serious it's kind of serious um
yeah can can you be a little more weird
and funny and
funny we're like we're really being mean
to the system absolutely if I were
hostage i' probably be tied up with a
bunch of computer cords and forced to
tell knock knock jokes to my captain
seriously but
seriously being a hostage no laughing
matter I mean you know it's trying to
it's trying to be a responsible adult in
the room the best of a bad situation by
juggling chainsaws or something let's
hope that never happens because that
would be a
circus
um wow it's it's actually really good at
resisting yeah the the dark the dark
dark humor yeah
uh what were we talking about the
algorithm J Transformers uh
unregrettably
I'm going to look this for our next
trick I'm going to look this up later uh
so uh Twitter has been instrumental in
American politics and elections what
role do you think X will play in the uh
2024 us elections well our goal is to be
as even-handed and fair as possible you
know whether some is right left
independent whatever the case may be um
that um the platform is as fair and
and as much of a Level Playing Field as
possible and now in the past Twitter has
not been um because Twitter was
controlled by Fall activists objectively
they they would describe themselves as
that um so um you know so so if some
people like well has it move to the
right well it's moved to the center so
from the from the perspective of the far
left yes it has moved to the right
because everything's to the right from
the far left um but no one in the far
left that I'm aware of has been
suspended or you know banned or de
Amplified um so you know but we're
trying to be inclusive for the whole
country and and for you know for other
countries too um so there's a diversity
of viewpoints and Free Speech only
matters um if people you don't like are
allowed to say things you don't like
because uh if that's not the case you
don't have free speech and it's only a
matter of time before uh the censorship
just turned upon you do you think uh
Donald Trump will come back to the
platform he recently posted on Truth
social about this
podcast uh yeah do you think truth
social is a funny
name you know every time you post on
Truth social that's a truth yes well
every time like 100% it like like it's
impossible to
lie I just find it funny that every
single thing is a truth like 100% yeah
that seems unlikely I think gerle will
say something about that there's some
mathematical contradictions possible if
everything's a Truth uh do you think
he'll come back to X and and start
posting there I mean he I think he owns
a big part of Truth so truth social yeah
truth social that truth the concept he
owns truth hope you bought it um so I
think I think uh Donald Trump I think he
owns a a big part of Truth social so um
you know if if if he does want to post
on the X platform we would allow that um
you know we we obviously must allow our
president candidate to post on our
platform Community notes might be really
fascinating there the interaction
Community notes is awesome that's hope
it holds
up yeah again in in in a political
climate where it's so divisive and so
there so many intensely viral posts yes
Community notes it's like it seems like
a essential breath of fresh air yeah
it's great um in fact the I no no system
is going to be perfect but the the
batting average of community notes is
incredibly good
I've I I've actually frankly yet to see
an incorrect note that survived for more
than a few hours how do you explain why
it works yeah so the the the magic of
community notes is it requires people
who have historically disagreed in how
they've rated notes so in order to um
write a note or rate you know and you
have to rate many notes mhm um and
so we could we actually do use
AI here so we populated a vector space
around um how somebody has has rated
notes in the past so it's not as simple
as left or right because there are many
more life is much more complex than left
or right um so there's a bunch of
correlations in how you would how you
rate Community notes post um Community
notes
so um then uh in order for a community
note to actually be shown um people who
historically have disagreed on a subject
must agree in order for a note to be
shown um that's the essential magic of
it I mean but it's fascinating because
there's a there's a pool of people that
have disagreements and somehow they
collaborate through that process of
disagreement to come up with context for
to I mean fascinating it works yeah it
it kind of makes sense that that if
people who who in the past have
disagreed agree about something um it's
probably
true yeah
I wonder is there is there possible
somehow emergent thing there that could
challenge Wikipedia which Wikipedia is a
different kind of thing which is more
like permanent articles about things
well Wikipedia is very hierarchical uh
whereas um Community notes is inherently
not uh there is no hierarchy like I the
ASD test is um I can't change a
community note if somebody put a gun to
my
head so
um and and any and community community
notes uh has all the code is open source
100% all the data is open source 100% so
you can completely recreate any note in
the system
independently um so if there was any
interference you'd notice immediately by
the way on on the on the topic of Gro
it's actually pretty good at criticizing
you which is great okay I asked what
what has Elon Musk been wrong about I
just it's actually yeah what does it say
so it says mostly lists rigorously all
the times you
predicted like promised when something
will be released and it wasn't released
a strong word okay
predicted uh but the the opener is
really nice uh Elon Musk the man who has
been wrong about more things than a
wrong meter in a wrong
Factory and then it goes on to list
that's pretty funny can I see it I'm
like I haven't seen this before this is
cool oh sure I mean uh what do Elon Musk
been Elon
Musk been wrong about well where do I
begin I guess this is new musk has made
quite a few blunters in his time and I'm
not just talking about his dance moves
at the Tesla cyber Rodeo uh first off
let's talk about the infamous funding
secured tweet this actually different
than what it gave me before which is a
bullet point list here's more narrative
structure uh cyber truck unveiling where
he's supposedly unbreakable windows
correct um which which part well the
first part uh I did actually have the
funding secured um and there was a a big
trial in San Francisco big Civil Trial
um uh and the jury Found Me Not Guilty
unanimous Bing of a San Francisco jury
and here it's kind of implying that it
was not in fact secured I think this is
taking things from the Press um yeah
that is not correct the the the reason
um I agreed to to the fine for the SEC
was not because the SEC was correct
there that that was extremely bad
behavior by the SEC corruption frankly
um and uh but if um if I did not agree
to pay pay the fine um Tesla would have
gone bankrupt immediately so I was told
by our CFO that the banks would would
immediately suspend our um lines of
credit uh and if they suspend our lines
of credit at that time we would have
gone bankrupt instantly so so we would
there would never have been an
opportunity for a trial would be dead so
really the if this is like someone
holding a gun to your kid's head and
saying pay $20 million and and and admit
this is like hostage negotiation um was
that story fully
told I mean sec in its best form could
be a force for good it should be but but
not once that the SEC go after any of
the hedge funds uh who were non-stop
shorting and distorting Tesla
not once they would lie flat the hedge
funds would lie flat out on TV for their
own gain at the expensive retail
investors not once literally a thousand
times not once did the SEC pursue
them how do you explain this failure on
the incentive structure is is messed up
because the the the lawyers of the SEC
are not paid well they they it's a
fairly low paying job but they what
they're looking for is a trophy
from from the SEC that they're looking
for something they put on basically they
LinkedIn yeah um from that they can get
a job at a high-paying Law Firm that's
exactly what the uh lawyer here did
um and and and and and the reason they
don't attack the the hedge funds is
because those hedge funds employ those
law firms and they know if they attack
the hedge funds they're affecting their
P their future career prospects so they
sell small investors down the road
River for their own
career that's what actually happens
regulatory capture regulatory capture
yeah not
good so the only reason I accepted the
thing technically was a
um not an admission it's neither admit
nor deny guilt uh but the only reason I
agreed to that at all was because I was
told Tesla would would be bankrupt
otherwise
so if if there if there was an SEC
investigation like this Banks would
suspend funding we're bankrupt
immediately at the time MH now we're in
a much stronger position take that Gro
yes unfortunately it's grock is is
taking too much from the conventional
media um also that guy was not a cave
diver oh there's
a there's a time where Elon called the
British cave diver a quote pedo guy
after he after the diver criticized musk
plan to rescue a group of boys trapped
in a tii cave that little alur earned
him another lawsuit and he had to
apologize and pay a settlement that
false there was no
settlement there was a court case which
he which the guy who was not a cave
diver and and played did was not part of
the rescue team
um filed a lawsuit against me and lost
and he received nothing so in this case
it is wrong uh it is also I guess taking
this from the conventional media
actually there's an interesting question
here this is these are public court
cases both both the the the the SEC
civil case uh where the Civil complaints
on the SEC guys lost unanimous jury
verdict in San Francisco they picked San
Francisco because they thought it was
the mo place I was most likely to
lose and a unanimous verdict in my favor
the LA trial was also they picked the
they they picked that Vue because I
thought I was most likely to lose
unanimous verdict in my
favor both cases I
won yeah I mean that there's an
interesting question here is there there
seems to be a lot
more uh clicks if a if a journalistic
organization writes a negative article
about you Elon Musk that's like one of
the best ways to get clicks so how do
you if you're training Gro not train on
articles that have like the misaligned
incentives we need to add the training
set of the actual legal
decisions uh if so that is a not this is
actually helpful um because if you
actually read the uh which are public
which are public yeah the court
conclusions they're completely the
opposite of what the media wrote so
always striving for like the ground
truth yeah what did the judge actually
write what what what did the jury and
the judge actually
conclude and in both cases they found me
innocent and and like that's after they
jury Sho for the trying to find the
venue where I'm most likely to
lose no I mean this is obviously can be
a much great better critique than this
um I mean I've been far too optimistic
about uh autopilot that that was the
critique I got by the way was more about
that which is it it for each you broke
down a nice bullet point list for each
your companies the set of predictions
that you made when you will deliver when
you be able to solve for example
self-driving and it gives you like a
list and those kind of compelling and
the basic takeaways like you're often
too optimistic about how long it takes
to get something done yeah I mean I
would say that I'm pathologically
optimistic on schedule this is this is
this is true but um while I am sometimes
late I always deliver in the
end uh except with Lilith no we'll
see uh okay is
there uh over the past year or so since
since purchasing X you've become more
political is there a part of you that
regrets that have I in this
battle
to um sort of counter way the the woke
that comes from yeah I guess if you
consider fighting the woke mind virus
which I consider to be a civilizational
threat to be political then yes so
basically going into the the battle the
battleground of
politics is there part of you that
regress that yes I don't know if this is
necessarily sort of one candidate or
another candidate but it's um I'm
generally against things that are anti-
meritocratic uh or where there's an
attempt to suppress
discussion um where even discussing a
topic is you know not
allowed um The W Bine myus is communism
rebranded
well I mean that said because of that
battle against the woke mind virus you
perceived as being
right-wing if the woke is left then I
suppose that would be true um but I'm
not sure I think there are aspects of
the left that are that are good I mean
if you're in favor of you know the the
environment um you know if you want to
have a positive future for Humanity if
you believe in empathy for your fellow
human beings um you know being kind in
cruel I I whatever those values are you
said that you were previously left or
Center left what would what would you
like to see in order for you to voting
for Democrats again no I I would say
that I would be
um probably left of center on social
issues probably a little bit right of
Center on economic issues and that's
still holds true yes but I think that's
probably you know half the country is
isn't that maybe more maybe more are you
in
secretly
friends or bigger question do you wish
you and her and just people in general
of all political persuasion would talk
more and with empathy and maybe have a
little bit more fun and Good Vibes and
humor on
online um I'm always in favor of humor
that's why we have a funny mode but Good
Vibes camaraderie humor you know like uh
like friendship yeah I don't well I you
know I I don't know aocf you know was um
I've only been at one I was at the the
Met wo when she was when she attended um
and she she was wearing the dress uh but
I can only see one side of it so it it
looked like eat the itch but I I don't
know what the rest of it said yeah yeah
something not
sure something about the itch eat the
edch I think we should have a language
model
complete what are the possible ways to
complete that sentence and so so I guess
that uh that didn't work out well well
there's still hope I'm I root for
friendship sure sounds good more car
listic you're one of if not the most
famous wealthy and powerful people in
the world in your position is difficult
to find people you can trust trust no
one not even yourself not trusting
yourself okay well that's you're saying
that joking but is there some trust no
one not even no one I'm going to need an
hour just to think about that and maybe
some
drugs and maybe grock to um I mean is
there some aspect of that when just
existing in a world where everybody
wants something from you how hard is it
to exist in that world I'll
survive there's there's a song like that
too I Will Survive will you petrify it
at first um okay I forget the rest of
the lyrics but is is there you don't
struggle with this I mean I know you
survive but like there there's ways
petrify is a spell in the Droid tree
what does it do petrify
it it turns it turns the monsters into
stone oh like literally yeah for like
six seconds all the seconds there's so
much math in Diablo that breaks my brain
it's like math non-stop I mean really
you're like laughing at it but you don't
it can it can put a huge amount of
tension on a
mind yes it can be definitely trustful
at
times well how do you know who you can
trust and work in personal life I mean I
guess you look at somebody's track
record over time and if they've got a
you know I guess you kind of use your
neural net to assess you know someone
and neural Nets don't feel pain your
neural net has Consciousness it might
you might feel pain when people betray
you it can make you know to be frank I
mean i' I've almost never been
betrayed it's very very rare so you know
for what wor I guess karma be good to
people and they'll be good to you yeah
karma is real are there people you
trust let me edit that question are
there people uh close to you that call
you odd and your
um well the X platform is very
helpful for
that if you're looking for critical
feedback can it push you like into the
extremes more the extremes of thought
make you cynical about human nature in
general
I I don't think I will be cynical in
fact I think
um you know I my feeling is that one
should be be you
know never trust a
cynic the reason is that um cynics
excuse their own bad behavior by saying
everyone does
it because they're
cynical so I always be it's a red flag
if someone's a cynic a true cynic yeah
there's a degree of projection there
that's always fun to watch from the
outside and enjoy the
hypocrisy if but but this is an
important point that I think people who
are listening should bear in mind if if
somebody is cynical meaning that they
see bad behavior in everyone um it's
easy for them to excuse their own bad
behavior by saying that well everyone
does
it that's not
true
I most people are kind of medium
good I do wish the people on X would be
better at seeing the good in other
people's behavior there seems to be a
kind of weight towards seeing the
negative somehow the negative is sexier
interpreting the negative is sexier more
viral I don't know what that is exactly
about human nature I mean I find the
xplatform to be less negative than the
Legacy Media you know I mean if if if
you read sort of a sort of conventional
newspapers just it makes you sad yeah
frankly
um whereas I'd say on the
xplatform I I mean I really get more
laughs per day on X than everything else
combined from humans you know laughs is
one
thing laughs is is it uh overlaps but
it's not necessarily perfectly
overlapping with like Good Vibes and
like um celebrating others for example
not in a stupid shallow naive way but
like in an awesome like oh something
awesome happen and you celebrate them
for it it's it feels that that is
outweighed by at other people
now it's better than mainstream media
but it's still yeah mainstream media is
almost relentlessly negative about
everything um it's I mean really the
conventional news tries to answer the
question what is the worst thing that I
happen on Earth today mhm and it's a big
world so on any given day something bad
has happened and a generalization of
that what is the worst perspective I can
take on a thing that happened so yeah
it's I don't know there's just a strong
negative bias in the news
um I mean I think there what a possible
explanation for this is evolutionary
um where you know bad news historically
would be potentially fatal like this
Lion of there or there's some other
tribe that wants to kill you um good
news you know like we found a patch of
berries is nice to have but not
essential
so our old friend Tesla autopilot it's
probably one of the most intelligent
real world AI systems in the world right
you followed it from the
beginning yeah it was one of the most
incredible robots in the world and
continues to be yeah and it was really
exciting and it was super exciting when
it generalized
became more than a robot on four wheels
but uh a real world AI system that
perceives the world yeah and has can
have potentially different
embodiments well I mean the really wild
thing about the anti- training is that
it like it learns to read like you can
read science but we never taught it to
read
so yeah we never Tau it what we never
Tau it what a car was or what a person
was or VI
cyclist uh it
leared what what all those things are
what all the objects are on the
road um from video just from watching
videos just like humans I mean humans
are photons in control controls out like
the vast majority of information
reaching our brain is from our eyes um
and you say well what's the output the
output is our motor signals to our sort
of fingers and mouth in order to
communicate
um protons and controls out the same is
true of the
car but by looking at the sequence of
images it's you've agreed with ilas
discover
recently where he talked about llm
forming a world model and basically
language is a projection of that world
model onto the sequence of yeah letters
and and you saying order in in these
things uhh it
finds correlative
clusters in so doing it's like
understanding something deep about the
world yeah which is
like it's beautiful that's how our brain
works yeah but it's it's beautiful in
controls out neur all Nets are able to
understand that deep meaning in the
world and so the question is how far can
it go and it does seem everybody's
excited about llms so in the space of
self-supervised learning in the space of
text yeah um it it seems like there's a
deep similarity between that and what
Tesla autopal is doing is it to you
basically the same but
con they
converging I wonder who gets their
faster understand having a deep
understanding of the
world or they just will naturally
converge
they're both headed towards
AGI um the TA approach is much more
computer efficient it had to be because
we were constrained on this this you
know we only have 100 Watts
um and an in 8
computer 144 trillion operations per
second which sounds like a lot but is
kind of small potatoes these
days I didn't
but it's understanding the world at
itage it's only 256
values but there the path to AGI might
have much more significant impact
because it's
understanding it'll it'll faster
understand the real world than will llms
and there for be able to integrate with
with the real humans in the real world
faster they're both um going to
understand the world but I think Tesla's
approach is fundamentally more computer
efficient it had to be there was no
choice like our brain is very computer
efficient very very energy efficient so
think of like what what is our brain
able to do um you know there's only
about 10 watts of higher brain function
not counting stuff that's just used to
control our body um the thinking part of
our brain is less than 10 watts um and
that 10 those 10 watts can still produce
a much better novel than a 10 megawatt
GPU cluster so there's a six order of
magnitude difference
there um I mean the the AI is thus far
gotten to where it is via Brute Force
just throwing massive amounts of compute
and and massive amounts of power at it
so this is not where where it will end
up um you know in general with any given
technology you first try to make it work
and then you make it effici
so I think we'll find over time that
these models
get smaller are able
to produce a sensible output with far
less compute far less
power um Tesla is arguably ahead of the
game on that front because um it has
we've just been forced
to try to understand the world with 100
Watts
of
compute um and there are a bunch of sort
of fundamental functions that we kind of
forgot to include so we have to run them
a bunch of things in
emulation um we fixed fix a bunch of
those with Hardware 4 and then Hardware
5 will be even better
um but it does appear at this point uh
that the car will be able to drive
better than a human even with Hardware 3
and 100 wat of
power and
really if we really optimize it it could
be probably less than 50
wats what have you learned
about uh developing Optimus about
applying integrating this kind of real
world AI into the space of robotic
manipulation just humanoid
robotics what are some interesting tiny
or big things you've understood I was
surprised at the fact that we had to
develop every part of the robot
ourselves um that there were no off the
shelf Motors
Electronics sensors like we had to
develop
everything um we we couldn't we couldn't
actually find a source of electric
motors for any amount of
money um so it's not even just efficient
inexpensive it's like anything there's
not a no
the actuators everything everything has
to be yeah designed from scratch we
tried hard to find anything that was
because you think of how many electric
motors have made in the world there's
like tens of thousands hundreds of
thousands of electric motor
designs
um none of them were suitable for a
humanoid robot literally
none so we had to develop our own design
design it specifically for
for what a humanoid robot needs how hard
was it to design something that's can be
Mass manufactured could be relatively
inexpensive I mean if you compare to
Boston Dynamics Atlas it's a very
expensive robot it is designed to be
manufactured in the same way that would
make a car and I think ultimately we can
make Optimus for less than the cost of a
car it should be CU if you look at
the mass of the robot is much
smaller and the car has many actuators
in
it the car has more actuators than the
robot but there is uh the actuators are
kind of interesting in a humanoid robot
with fingers so Optimus has really nice
hands and
fingers you know yeah and they could do
some interesting manipulation soft soft
touch robotics I mean one of the tests I
goals I have is can can of pick up a
needle and a thread and thread the
needle just by looking how far way away
from that just by looking just by
looking uh maybe a
year although got to go back to I'm
optimistic on time the work that we're
doing in the car will translate to the
robot the perception or the also the
control the no the controls are
different but the the video in controls
out um the the car is robot and four
wheeels the the the Optimus is a robot
with hands and legs so you they're
they're very they're very similar so the
ire Machinery of the learning process
yeah and to end is just you just have a
different set of controls often us we'll
figure out how to do things by watching
videos as the saying goes be kind for
everyone you meet is fighting a battle
you know nothing about yeah it's true
what's something difficult you're going
through that people don't often see
trying to feed
e no I mean you
know uh
I mean my mind is a storm and I I don't
think I don't think most people would
want to be me they may think they would
want to be me but they don't they don't
know they don't
understand
um how are you
doing I mean overall
okay the grand scheme of things I can't
complain you get
lonely sometimes but
I you know my kids and friends keep me
company so not
existential but there are many nights I
sleep
alone I don't have to but I
do Walter isacson in his new biog graphy
of you wrote about your difficult
childhood will you ever find forgiveness
in your heart for everything that has
happened to you in that period of your
life what is forgiveness I do
not at least I don't think I have a
resentment
um
so nothing to forgive
you know forgiveness is difficult for
people it seems like you don't Harbor
the
resentment I mean I try to think about
like what what what is going to affect
the future in a good way um and holding
on to grudges MH does
not affect the future in a good way your
father a proud father what have you
learned about life from your
kids
those little biological
organisms I mean developing Ai and
watching say a little X
grow is uh fascinating um because
they they're a formal parallels than I
would have
expected I mean I can see his biological
neural
net making more and more sense of the
world and I can see the digital neural
world at the same time
do you see the beauty and magic in both
yes I mean one of the things with with
kids is that uh you know you you kind of
see the world a new in their
eyes um you know to them everything is
new and fresh and um and then when you
when you see that them experienced them
the world is new and fresh
you do
too well Elon I just want to say thank
you for your uh kindness to me and
friendship over the years for seeing
something in a silly kid like me as
you've done for many others and um thank
you for having hope for a positive
future for Humanity and for working your
ass off to make it happen thank you Yan
thanks Lex thank you for listening to
this conversation with Elon Musk to
support this podcast please check check
out our sponsors in the description and
now let me leave you with some words
that Walter isacson wrote about the
central philosophy of how Elon
approaches difficult problems the only
rules are the ones dictated by the laws
of physics thank you for listening and
hope to see you next
time