the following is a conversation with
John mimer a professor at University of
Chicago and one of the most influential
and controversial thinkers in the world
he teaches speaks and writes about the
nature of power and War on the global
stage in history and
today please allow me to say once again
my hope for this little journey I'm
on I will speak to everyone on all sides
with compassion with empathy and with
backbone I will speak with Vladimir
Putin and with vadimus zsky with
Russians and with ukrainians with
Israelis and with Palestinians with
everyone my goal is to do whatever small
part I can to decrease the amount of
suffering in the world by trying to
reveal our common
Humanity I believe that in the end Truth
and Love
wins I will get attacked for being naive
for being a shill for being
weak I am none of those things but I do
make mistakes and I will get
better I love you
all this is Alex Freedman podcast to
support it please check out our sponsors
in the description and now dear friends
here's John
mammer can you explain your view on
power in international Politics as
outlined in your book The Tragedy of
great power politics and in your writing
since then yeah I make two sets of
points there first of all I believe that
power is the currency of international
relations and by that I mean that states
are deeply interested in the balance of
power and they're interested in
maximizing how much power they control
and the question is why States care so
much about power I in the International
System there's no higher authority so if
you get into trouble and you dial 911
there's nobody at the other end in a
system like that you have no choice but
to figure out for yourself how best to
protect yourself and the best way to
protect yourself is to be powerful to
have as much power as you can possibly
gain over all the other states in the
system therefore States care about power
because it enhances or maximizes their
prospects for survival second point I
would make is that in the real story or
in my story power is largely a function
of material factors uh the two ke key
building blocks of Power are population
size and wealth you want to have a lot
of people and you want to be really
wealthy of course of course this is why
the United States is so powerful it has
lots of people and it has lots of wealth
China was not considered a great power
until
recently uh because it didn't have a lot
of wealth certainly had population size
but it didn't have wealth and without
both a large population and much wealth
you're usually not considered a great
power uh so I think power matters uh but
uh when we talk about power it's
important to understand that it's a
population size and wealth that are
underpinning it so there's a lot of
interesting things there first you said
nations in relation to each other are is
essentially in a state of anarchism yeah
well Anarchy basically means the
opposite of hierarchy sometimes people
think when you're talking about Anarchy
you're talking about murder and mayham
but that's not what Anarchy means in the
realist context Anarchy simply means
that you don't have hierarchy there's no
higher authority that sits above States
states are like pool balls on a table
right and in an anarchic world uh
there's no higher authority that you can
turn to uh if you get into trouble and
of course the political philosopher who
laid this all out was Thomas Hobbs and
Hobbs talked about life in the state of
nature and in the state of nature you
have
individuals and those individuals
compete with each other for power and
the reason that they do is because in
the state of nature by definition you
have no higher authority and hobbs' view
is that the way to get out of this
terrible situation where individuals are
competing with each other and even
killing each other is to create a state
it's what he calls the Leviathan and
that of course is the title of his
famous book so the idea is to escape
Anarchy you create a state and that
means you go from Anarchy to hierarchy
the problem in international politics is
that there is no world State there is no
hierarchy and if you have no hierarchy
and you're in an anarchic system you
have no choice but to try to maximize
your relative power to make sure you are
as we used to say when I was a kid on
New York City playgrounds the biggest
and baddest dude on the Block not
because you necessarily want to beat up
on other kids or on other states but
because again that's the best way to
survive and as I like to point out to
people the best example of what happens
when you're weak in international
politics is what the Chinese call the
century of national humiliation uh from
from the late 1840s to the late 1940s
the Chinese were remarkably weak and the
great powers in the system prayed upon
them and uh that sends a very important
message to not only the Chinese but to
other states in the system don't be weak
be as powerful as you can and we'll talk
about it but humiliation can lead to
resentment and resentment leads to uh
something you've also studied which is
Nazi Germany in the
1930s we'll talk about it um
but staying to the psychology and
philosophy
picture what's the connection between
the will to power in the individual as
you mentioned and the will to power in a
nation the will to power in an
individual has a lot to do with
individual's psychology uh the story
that I tell about the pursuit of power
is a structural argument it it's an
argument that says when you are in a
particular structure when you're in a
system that has a specific
architecture which is
anarchy the states have no choice but to
compete for power uh so structure is
really driving the story here Will To
Power has a lot more to do with an
individual uh in in the nichan story
where that concept comes from so it's
very important to understand that I'm
not arguing that states are inherently
aggressive right my point is that as
long as states are in Anarchy right they
have no choice but to behave in an
aggressive fashion but if you went to a
hierarchic system uh there's no reason
for those states to worry about the
balance of power because if they get
into trouble there is a higher authority
that they can turn to there is in effect
the Leviathan so what is the role of
military might in this uh will to power
on the national level well military
might's what ultimately matters as I
said to you before the two building
blocks of Power are population size and
wealth you didn't mention military I did
not no that's right and it's good that
you caught that because if you have a
large population and you're a wealthy
country what you do is you build a large
military and it's ultimately the size of
your military that matters uh because
militaries fight Wars and if states are
concerned about survival which I argue
is the principal goal of every state in
the International System for what I
think are obvious reasons then they're
going to care about having a powerful
military that can protect them if
another state comes after them what's
not obvious that a large Nation with a
lot of people a lot of money should
necessarily build a gigantic Army and
seek to attain
superpower like dominant sole superpower
status to military might but you're
saying as you see the world today it has
to be that way yeah I'm arguing it is
obvious if you're a state in the
International System uh do you want to
be weak uh if you live next door to Nazi
Germany or imperial Germany or aonic
France or even the United States the
United States is a ruthless great power
you surely recognize that and if you're
dealing with the United States of
America and you're Vladimir Putin you
want to make sure you're as powerful as
possible so that the United States
doesn't put its gun sits on you and come
after you same thing is true with China
you want to be powerful in the
International System States understand
that and they go to Great Lengths to
become powerful just take the United
States of America when it started in
1783 it was comprised of 13 measley
colonies strung out along the Atlantic
Seaboard over time you know the uh
various leaders of the United States
went to Great Lengths to turn that
country into the dominant power in the
Western Hemisphere and then once that
was achieved in 1900 we've gone to Great
Lengths to make sure that there's no
peer uh competitor in the system uh we
just want to make sure that we're number
one uh and my argument is that this is
not peculiar to the United
States uh if I'm China for example
today I would want to dominate Asia the
way the United States dominates the
Western Hemisphere they'd be fools not
to if I were Imperial Germany I'd want
to dominate all of Europe the way the
United States dominates the Western
Hemisphere why because if if you
dominate all of Europe assum your
Imperial Germany or Napoleonic France
then no other state in the area or in
the region can threaten you because
you're simply so powerful uh and again
what I'm saying here is that the
structure of the International System
really matters it's the fact that you're
in this anarchic system where survival
is your principal goal and where I can't
know your intentions right you're
another state I can't know that it's
some point you might not come after me
you might and if you're really powerful
and I'm not I'm in deep trouble yeah so
some of the ideas underlying what you've
said uh offensive realism which I would
love to talk to you about sort of the
history of realism versus liberalism but
some of the ideas you already mentioned
uh Anarchy between
states everybody's trying to develop a
military capabilities uncertainty such
an interesting concept States cannot be
sure that other states will not use
military capabilities against them which
is it's of enormous importance story and
so interesting because you also say that
this makes realist more cautious and
more
peaceful the
uncertainty because of all the
uncertainty involved here it's better to
approach International politics with
caution is really interesting to think
about
uh again survival most States interested
in survival and the other interesting
thing is you assume all the states are
rational um which most of the time most
of the time you call this framework
offensive realism C can you just give a
overview of the history of the realism
versus liberalism debate as World Views
well I think for many cent CES now the
big
divide uh within the world of
international relations
theory is between realism and liberalism
these are Tim honored bodies of theory
and before I tell you what I think the
differences are between those two bodies
of theory it is important to emphasize
that there are differences among
realists and differences among liberals
um and uh so when you talk about me as
an offensive realist you should
understand that there are also defensive
realists out there and there are uh a
panoply of liberal theories as well but
uh basically realists believe that power
matters that states compete for power
and that war is an instrument of
statecraft and uh uh liberals on the
other hand have what I would say is a
more idealistic view of the world uh
this is not to say that they're naive or
foolish but they believe there are
aspects of international
politics uh that lead to a less
competitive and more peaceful world than
most realists see uh and I'll lay out
for you very quickly what are the three
major major liberal theories today that
I think will give you a sense of the
more optimistic perspective that is
inherent in the liberal
Enterprise uh the first and most
important of the liberal theories is
democratic peace Theory and this is a
theory that says democracies do not
fight against other
democracies so the more the world is
populated with democracies the less
likely it is that we will have
wars uh and this basic argument is
inherent in Francis fukiyama is the end
of History he argues that democracy
Triumph first over fascism in the 20th
century it then triumphed over communism
and that means that in the future we're
have more and more liberal democracies
on the planet and if you have more and
more liberal democracies in those
democracies don't fight each other then
you have a more peaceful world that was
his argument it's a very liberal
argument a realist like me would say
that it doesn't matter whether a state
is a democracy or not all states behave
the same way because the structure of
the system getting back to our earlier
discussion about International Anarchy
the structure of the system leaves those
States no choice whether they're
democracies or autocracies and again the
liberal view this first liberal theory
is that democracies don't fight other
democracies and therefore the more
democracies you have the more peaceful
the world can I just uh sort of try to
unpack that a little bit so on the
Democratic peace Theory I guess would
say that in democracies leaders are
elected and the underlying assumption is
most people want peace and so they will
elect peacemakers so the more you
democracies you have the more likely you
have peace and then the realist
perspective what says that it doesn't
matter if the majority of people want
peace the
structure of international politics is
such that superpowers want to become
more Super and powerful and they do that
through War you can't make that argument
that you're making about democracies
because if you're saying that
democracies are inclined toward toward
peace and the the electorate picks
leaders who are inclined towards peace
then you have to show that democracies
are in general more peaceful than
non-democracies and you can't support
that argument you can find lots of
evidence to support the argument that
democracies don't fight other
democracies so the argument I believe
that you have to make if you're going to
support Democratic peace Theory the main
argument you have to make
is that liberal
democracies have a healthy respect for
each other and they can assess each
others intentions if you're a liberal
democracy and I'm a liberal democracy we
know we have value systems that argue
against aggression and argue for
peaceful resolution of of Crisis and
therefore given these Norms we can trust
each other we can know each other's
intentions remember for realists like me
uncertainty about intentions really
helps Drive the train but if you're
talking about two
democracies right the argument there is
that they know each other's intentions
and for you sure maybe democracies
reduce uncertainty a little bit but not
enough to stop the train I think that's
right yeah that's that that's right so
that's Democratic peace theory yes the
second theory is economic
interdependence Theory and that's the
argument that in a globalized world like
the one that we live in and have lived
in for a long time there's a great deal
of economic interdependence and if you
and I are two
countries uh or if you and me are two
countries and uh we're economically
interdependent and we're both getting
prosperous as a result of this economic
intercourse the last thing that we're
going to do is start a war either one of
us because who would kill the goose that
lays the golden eggs it's that kind of
argument so there you have an argument
that economic interdependence leads to
peace and then the third liberal
argument has to do with
institutions uh sometimes referred to as
liberal institutionalism and this is the
argument that if you can get States into
institutions where they become rule
abiding
actors they will obey the rules that
dictate that war is not
acceptable uh so if you get them to
accept uh uh the UN rules on when you
can and cannot initiate a war uh then
you'll have a more peaceful world so
those are the liberal theories and as
you can tell they're very different from
realism as articulated by somebody like
me can you uh maybe argue against the
economic interdependence and in the
institutions that institutions follow
rules um a little bit so the the the
Golden Goose with a golden egg you're
saying that nations are happy to kill
the goose because again they want Power
if they think it's necessary to kill the
Golden Goose yeah because of security
concerns they will do it the point is
that economic
interdependence at its root has
Prosperity as the core variable yeah in
the realest story The Core variable is
survival and survival always trumps
Prosperity so if you go back to the
period before World War I we're in
Europe it's
1913 or early 19
14 what you see is that you have an
intense security competition between all
of the great powers on one side you have
the Triple Alliance and on the other
side you have the triple onon you have
these two alliances and you have an
intense security competition between
them okay at the same time you have a
great deal of economic interdependence
it's amazing how much economic
intercourse is taking place in Europe
among all the actors right and people
are getting prosperous or countries are
getting prosperous as a result but
nevertheless in the famous July crisis
of
1914 this economic Prosperity is unable
to prevent World War I because security
concerns or survival is more important
uh so there are you know going to be
lots of situations where prosperity and
survival come into conflict and in those
cases survival will win and uh maybe you
can speak to the different camps of
realists you said offensive and
defensive can you draw a distinction
between those two yeah let me just back
up a bit on that one and you were
talking about Will To Power before uh
the first big
divide between realists is structural
realists and human nature realists nice
mhm and Hans
morganth who was influenced by nature
and
therefore had that will to power logic
embedded in his thinking about how the
world works right he was a human nature
realist okay I'm a structural
realist and I believe it's not human
nature it's it's not individuals and
some Will To Power that drives
competition and War what dri drives
competition in war is the structure of
the system it's Anarchy so you're not as
romantic as the human nature realists
yeah there's just a a world of
difference between the two sure it's
just important to understand that so
within that this from the structural
that there's a subdivision also of
offensive and defensive yes inside the
structural realist world right and you
have a handful of realists who believe
that the structure of the
system Fosters competition for sure
security competition but it really rules
out great power War almost all the time
so it makes sense to care about the
balance of power but to focus on
maintaining how much power you have
that's the defense of realism
maintaining how much power you have not
trying to gain more power because the
argument the defensive realists make is
that if you try to gain more power the
system will punish you the structure
will punish
you I'm not a defensive realist I'm an
offensive realist and my argument is
that states look for
opportunities to gain more power and
every time they see or almost every time
they see an opportunity to gain more
power um and they think the likelihood
of success is high and the cost will not
be great they'll jump at that
opportunity just to linger on the human
nature
perspective how do you explain Hitler
and Nazi
Germany uh just one of the more
recent
aggressive expansions through military
might
how do you explain that in the framework
of uh offensive
realism well I think that Nazi Germany
was driven in large part by structural
considerations and I think if you look
at Imperial Germany which was largely
responsible for starting World War I and
of course Nazi Germany is largely
responsible for starting World War II
what that tells you is you didn't need
Adolf Hitler to start World War I right
and I believe that there is a good
chance you would have had World War II
in the absence of Hitler right I believe
that Germany was very powerful it was
deeply worried about the balance of
power in Europe and it had strong
incentives to behave
aggressively uh in in the late 1930s
early
1940s so I I believe that structure
mattered however I want to qualify that
in the case of Adolf hler because I do
think he had what you would call a Will
To Power I've never used that word to
describe him before but it's consistent
with my point that I often make that
there are two leaders or there have been
two leaders in modern history who are
congenital
aggressors uh and one was Napoleon and
the other was Hitler now if you want to
call that a Will To Power you can do
that I I'm more comfortable referring to
Hitler As A congenital aggressor and
referring to Napoleon As A congenital
aggressor although there were important
differences between the two because
Hitler was probably the most murderous
leader uh in recorded history and
Napoleon was not in that category at all
uh but but both of them uh were uh
driven by what you would call a Will To
Power uh and that has to be uh Mar to
the structural argument in Hitler's case
and also in Napoleon's case is there
some degree on the human psychology side
that
resentment because of how because of
what happened after World War I led to
Hitler wielding so much power and then
Hitler starting World War II so this is
the The Human Side perhaps the reason I
asked that question is also because you
mentioned the century of humiliation on
the China side so to so to which degree
the
humiliation lead to Hitler and lead to
World War I well the question of what
led to Hitler is a very different
question than the question of what led
to World War II once Hitler was in power
I mean after January 30th 1933 he's in
power and then the question of what is
driving him comes racing to the four uh
is their resentment over the Versa
treaty and what happened to Germany yes
did that matter yes but my argument is
that structure was the principal Factor
uh driving the train in Hitler's case
but what I'm saying here is that there
were other factors at well as well
resentment being one of them will to
power or the fact that he was A
congenital aggressor in my lexicon uh
certainly mattered as well so I I don't
want to dismiss um your point
uh about resentment so Hitler in
particular the way he wielded the way he
gained so much power might have
been the general resentment of the
populace of the German populace I think
that uh as a result of um defeating
World War I and all the trials and
tribulations associated with viar
Germany and then the coming of uh the
Great Depression all of those factors
death definitely account for his coming
to power I think that one of the
reasons um that he was so successful at
winning over the German people once he
came to
power uh was because there was a great
deal of resentment uh in the German body
politic and he played on that resentment
that surely helped him get elected too
but I think uh having studied the case
it was even more important once he took
over I also believe that one of the
principle reasons that he was so popular
and he was wildly popular inside Nazi
Germany is because he was the only
leader of an industrialized country who
pulled this country out of the
depression uh and that really
mattered uh and uh it made him uh very
effective it's also worth noting that he
was a remarkably charismatic individual
uh I find that hard to believe because
every time I look at him or listen to
his speeches uh he does not appear to be
charismatic to me but uh I've talked to
a number of people who are experts on
this subject who assure me that he was
very charismatic and I would note to you
if you look at public opinion polls in
Germany West Germany in the late 1940s
this is the late 1940s after the Third
Reich is destroyed in 19 45 he is still
remarkably popular in the polls Stalin
is still popular in many parts of
Eastern Europe yeah yeah and Stalin's
popular in many quarters inside
Russia uh and Stalin murdered more of
his own people than he murdered people
outside of the Soviet Union and still to
you the ties of History turn not on
individuals but on structural
considerations so so Hitler may be a uh
surface
layer characteristics of how Germany
started a war but not the really the
reason well history is a
multidimensional phenomena so I hear and
we're talking about Interstate relations
here yes and realism is a theory about
how States interact with each other and
there are many other dimensions to
International politic and if you're
talking about someone like Adolf Hitler
right uh why did he start World War II
uh is a very different question then why
did he uh start the Holocaust or why did
he push forward a holocaust I mean
that's you know a different question and
realism doesn't answer that question so
I want to be very clear that you know
I'm not someone who argues that realism
answers every question about
International politics but it does
answer what is you know one of the big
if not the biggest questions that IR
Scholars care about which is what causes
security competition and what causes
great power War does offensive realism
answer the question why
Hitler attacked the Soviet Union Yes
because from a military strategy
perspective you know there's pros and
cons to that decision pros and cons to
every decision the question is did he
think that he could win a quick and
decisive Victory and uh he did I mean as
did his generals it's very interesting I
I've spent a lot of time studying German
decision making uh in World War II if
you look at the German decision um to
invade Poland on September 1st 1939 and
you look at the uh German decision made
France on May 10th 1940 and then the
Soviet Union on June 22nd 194 41 what
you see is there was actually quite a
bit of resistance to Hitler in
1938 at the time of Czechoslovakia
Munich and there was also quite a bit of
resistance in September
1939 internally or you mean internally
internally for sure yeah people had
doubts they didn't think the ver mock
was ready and given the fact that world
war one had just ended about 20 years
before for the thought of starting
another European War uh was not
especially attractive to lots of German
policy makers including military
leaders and then came France 1940 in the
runup to May 10th 1940 uh there was huge
resistance uh in the uh German Army to
attacking France uh but that was
eventually eliminated because they came
up with a clever plan uh the manstein
plan if you look at the decision to
invade the Soviet Union on June 22nd
1941 which is the only case where they
fail they succeeded in France they
succeeded in Poland they succeeded uh at
Munich in
1938 Soviet Union is where they fail
there's hardly any resistance at all
right yeah well and to say that they
failed the Soviet Union I mean my
grandfather F I mean from from the
Soviet Union you know there's a lot of
successes early on so there's poor
military I would say uh strategic
decisions along the way but it was uh it
caught Stalin off
guard maybe you can correct me but from
my
perspective terrifyingly so they could
have been successful if certain
different decisions were made from a
military
perspective yeah I I I've always had the
since they came terrifyingly close to
winning uh you could make the opposite
argument that they were doomed uh but uh
I I'm not terribly comfortable making
that argument I think the ver mocked by
the summer of
1941 was a finally tuned instrument for
War and the Red Army was in quite
terrible shape uh Stalin had purged the
officer Corp uh they had perform po
poorly in Finland uh and uh there were
all sorts of reasons to think that they
were no match for the verock and if you
look at what happened in the initial
stages of the conflict that proved to be
the case uh the Germans won a lot of
significant tactical victories early on
and if they focused and went to Moscow
as quickly as possible it's again
terrifyingly so could have been a
basically topple topple
Stalin um and one thing that's that's
possible that's possible fortunately
we're not going to run the experiment
again but one could argue that that had
they concentrated as the generals wanted
to do in going straight for Moscow that
they would have won I mean what Hitler
wanted to do is he he wanted to go into
the Ukraine I mean Hitler thought that
the main axis uh there were three axes
the Northern axis went towards Leningrad
the central axis of course went to
Moscow and then the southern axis Army
group South uh headed towards Ukraine
and deep into the caucuses and Hitler
believed that uh that that should have
been the main axis and in fact in
1942 the Soviets excuse me the Germans
go back on the offensive in
1942 this is Operation Blue and the main
axis in 42 is deep into the Ukraine and
into the caucuses and that fails but one
could argue that had they done that in
41 had they not gone to Moscow had they
gone you know had they concentrated on
going deep into Ukraine and into the
caucuses they could have knocked the
Soviets out that way uh I'm I'm not sure
that in the end I believe that I I think
in the end the Soviets would have won no
matter what but I'm not 100% sure of
that so sometimes um maybe you can
educate me but sometimes you know they
say just like with Napoleon winter
defeated Hitler in in Russia I think not
often enough people tell the story of
the of the soldiers and the the
motivation and how hard they
fight so uh it turns out that ukrainians
and Russians are not easy to conquer
they're the kinds of people that
don't roll over and fight bravely there
seems to be a difference in certain
people peoples in how they see War how
they approach War how proud they are to
fight for their country to die for their
country these kinds of things so I think
Battle of stying gr tells at least to me
a story of extremely Brave fighting on
the Soviet side and that it's a
component of War too it's not just
structural it's not just mil strategy
it's also the humans involved but maybe
that's a romantic notion of war no I I
think there's a great deal of Truth in
that but let's just unpack it a bit in
the case of uh the Soviet Union in World
War II the counterargument to that um is
that in World War I the uh Russian army
disintegrated uh and uh if you look at
what happened when Napoleon invaded in
18112 and you look at what happened in
1917 and then you look at what happened
between 41 and
45 the Napoleon case looks a lot like
the Hitler case and it fits neatly with
your argument but World War I does not
fit neatly with your argument because
the Russians lost and surrendered yeah
and you had the infamous Treaty of BR
lovk where the Soviet Union then because
it went from Russia to the Soviet Union
in October 1917 the Soviet Union
surrendered large amounts of uh Soviet
territory because it had suffered a
humiliating defeat my argument for why
the Russians let me take that back why
the Soviets fought like wild dogs in
World War II is that they were up
against a genocidal
adversary you want to understand that
the Germans murdered huge numbers of
Soviet
PS uh the overall total was 3.7 million
and by December December of 1941
remember the invasion is June 41 by
December of
1941 uh the Germans have murdered two
million Soviet PS at that point in time
they had murdered many more PWS than
they had murdered Jews and this is not
to deny for one second that they were on
a murderous Rampage when it came to Jews
but were also on a murderous Rampage
when it came to Soviet citizens and
Soviet soldiers right so those Soviet
soldiers quickly came to understand that
they were fighting for their lives if
they were taken prisoner they would die
so they fought like wild dogs yeah you
know the story of the Holocaust of the 6
million Jews is often told extensively
if Hitler want one conquer the Soviet
Union it's terrifying to think on a much
grander scam than the Holocaust what
what would have happened to the Slavic
people to the to the Soviet people
absolutely all you have to do is read
The Hunger plan right and they also had
had a plan uh what is it called Grand
planned East I forget the exact name of
it uh which made it clear that they they
were going to murder many tens of
millions of people and by the way I
believe that they would have murdered
all the poles and all the Roma I mean my
view is that the Jews were number one on
the genocidal Hit List the Roma or the
gypsies were number two and the Poes
were number three uh and of course I
just explained to you how many PS they
had killed so they would have ended up
murdering huge numbers of Soviet
citizens as well but people quickly
figured out that this was happen
happening M that's my point to you and
that gave them needless to say very
powerful incentives to fight hard uh
against uh the Germans and to make sure
that they did not win to fast forward in
time but not in
space let me ask you about uh the war in
Ukraine why did Russia invade Ukraine on
February 24th 2022
what are some of the explanations given
and which do you find the most
convincing well clearly the conventional
wisdom is that Putin uh is principally
responsible Putin is an imperialist uh
he's an expansionist that's the
conventional thinking yeah yeah and the
idea is that uh he he uh is bent on
creating a greater Russia uh and even
more so he's interested in dominating in
Eastern Europe if not all of
Europe um and that Ukraine was the first
stop on the train line uh and what he
wanted to do was to conquer all of
Ukraine uh incorporate it into a greater
Russia and then he would move on and
Conquer other countries this is the
conventional wisdom my view is there is
no evidence uh let me emphasize zero
evidence to support that argument which
part that he would the imperialist part
the sense that he would he sought to
conquer all of Ukraine and move on and
Conquer there's no evidence he was
interested in conquering all of Ukraine
there was no interested there's no
evidence beforehand that he was
interested in coning conquering any of
Ukraine and there's no way that an army
that had
190,000 troops at the
most right could have conquered all of
Ukraine just impossible as I like to
emphasize when the Germans went into
Poland in
1939 uh and the Germans you want to
remember were only intent on Conquering
the Western half of Poland because the
Soviets uh who came in later that month
were going to conquer the eastern half
of Poland so the Western half of Poland
is much smaller than Ukraine and the
Germans went in with 1 5 million troops
uh If U Vladimir Putin were bent on
conquering all of Ukraine he would have
needed at least two million troops I
would argue he'd need three million
troops because not only he need to
conquer the country he then have to
occupy it uh but the idea that 190,000
troops was sufficient for conquering uh
all of Ukraine is not a serious argument
furthermore he was not interested in
conquering Ukraine and that's why in
March
2022 this is immediately after the war
starts he is negotiating with zinsky to
end the war there are serious
negotiations taking place in Istanbul
involving the Turks and na T Bennett who
was the Israeli Prime Minister at the
time was deeply involved in negotiating
with both Putin and zeny to end the war
well if he was interested Putin in
conquering all of Ukraine why in God's
name would he be negotiating with zinski
to end the war and of course what they
were negotiating about was NATO
expansion into Ukraine which was the
principal cause of the war uh people in
the west don't want to hear that
argument because if it is true which it
is then the West is principally
responsible for this bloodbath that's
now taking place and of course the West
doesn't want to be principally resp
responsible it wants to blame Vladimir
Putin so we've invented this story out
of whole cloth that he is an aggressor
that he's the second coming of Adolf
Hitler and that what he did in Ukraine
was try to to conquer all of it and he
failed but uh with a little bit of luck
he probably would have conquered all of
it and he'd now be in the Baltic states
and eventually end up uh dominating all
of Eastern Europe is I I think there's
no evidence to support this so maybe
there's a lot of things to ask there
maybe just to linger on NATO
expansion what is NATO
expansion what is the threat of NATO
expansion and why is it such a concern
for
Russia
NATO was a mortal enemy of the Soviet
Union during the Cold War it's a
military Alliance which has at its heart
the United States of America which is
the most powerful State on the planet it
is perfectly understandable that Russia
is not going to want that military
Alliance on its doorstep here in the
United States we have as you well know
what's called the Monroe Doctrine and
that basically says no great powers from
Europe or Asia are allowed to come into
our neighborhood and form a military
alliance with anybody in this
neighborhood uh when I was young there
was this thing called the Cuban Missile
Crisis the Soviets had the audacity to
put nuclear armed missiles in Cuba we
told them in no uncertain terms that
that was not acceptable and that those
missiles had to be removed this is our
backyard and we do not tolerate distant
great Powers coming into our
neighborhood well what's good for the
goose is good for the gander and if we
don't like great Powers coming into our
neighborhood it's hardly surprising that
the r Russians did not want NATO on
their doorstep uh they made that
manifestly clear um when the Cold War
ended and they exacted a promise from us
that we would not expand NATO and then
when we started expanding NATO they made
it clear after the first trunch in 1999
that they were profoundly unhappy with
that they made it clear in 2004 after
the second trunch that they were
profoundly unhappy with that
expansion and then in April 2008 when
NATO announced that uh Ukraine and
Georgia would become part of NATO they
made it unequivocally clear not just
Putin that that was not going to happen
they were drawing a Red Line in the Sand
and it is no accident that in August
2008 remember the Bucharest Summit is
April 2008 and August 2008 you had a war
between Georgia and Russia and that
involved at its core NATO expansion so
uh the Americans and their allies should
have understood by at least August 2008
that continuing to push to bring Ukraine
into NATO was going to lead to disaster
and I would note that there were all
sorts of people in the 1990s like George
Kennan William Perry who was Bill
Clinton's secretary defense the chairman
of the Joint Chiefs of Staff Paul Nitza
and so forth and so on who argued that
NATO expansion would end up producing a
disaster which it has I would note that
uh at the famous April 2008 Bucharest
Summit where NATO said that Ukraine
would be brought into the alliance
Angela Merkel and uh Nicholas sarosi the
German and French leaders respectively
opposed that decision Angela Merkel
later said that the reason she opposed
it was because she understood that Putin
would interpret it as a declaration of
war just think about that Merkel is
telling you that she opposed NATO
expansion into Ukraine because she
understood correctly that Putin would
see it as a declaration of war what did
the United States and its friend in
friends in Europe do they continued to
push and push because we thought that we
could push NATO expansion down their
throat after 2008 the same way we did in
1999 and 2004 but we were wrong and it
all blew up in our face in
2014 and when it blew up in our face in
2014 what did we do did we back off and
say well maybe the Russians have some
legitimate security interest no that's
not the way we operate we continue
contined to double down and the end
result is that in 2022 you got a war and
as I've argued for a long time now we
the West are principally responsible for
that not Vladimir Putin so the expansion
of NATO is primarily responsible yeah to
put it in more general terms what we
were trying to do was turn Ukraine into
a western bulwark on Russia's border and
it really was it NATO expansion alone
NATO expansion was the most important
element of our strategy but the strategy
had two other dimensions one was EU
expansion and the third was the color
Revolution we were trying to force
orange revolution in Ukraine and the
basic goal there was to turn Ukraine
into a pro Western liberal
democracy and that meant that you'd have
Ukraine if it worked as a pro-western
liberal democracy that was in the EU and
that was in NATO this was our goal and
the Russians made it unequivocally clear
Ukraine was not going to become a
Western bullwark on their border and
most importantly they made it clear that
Ukraine in NATO was
unacceptable can we talk about the mind
of Vladimir Putin you've mentioned that
this idea that he has aspirations
for uh imperialist
Conquest that he dreams of Empire is not
grounded in reality he wrote an essay in
2021 about one
people do you think there is some degree
to
which he still dreams of the former
Soviet Union
reuniting no he's made it clear that
anybody with a a triple digit IQ
understands that it's nuts to think
about recreating the Soviet
Union he thinks it's a tragedy that the
Soviet Union fell apart but as he made
clear in that essay the July 12th 2021
essay and as he made clear in speeches
before immediately before he invaded
Ukraine he
accepted uh the breakup of the Soviet
Union and he accepted the status quo in
in Europe safe for the fact he did not
accept the idea that Ukraine would
become part of NATO he's been in power
for over two decades is there a degree
that power can
affect a Leader's ability to see the
world
clearly as they say
corrupt um do you think power has
corrupted Vladimir Putin to a degree
it's very hard for me to answer that
question because I don't know him and
I've not studied him carefully uh in
terms of his overall performance over
the course of you know the 23 years that
he's been in
power uh I've studied him as a
strategist and I've studied how he you
know deals with the West uh and you know
deals with the International System more
generally uh since 20
4 and I think he is a first class
strategist this is not to say he doesn't
make
mistakes uh and he admits he's made some
mistakes uh U but uh I think that the
West is dealing with a formidable
adversary here uh and I don't see any
evidence that he's either lost speed off
his fast ball or that power has
corrupted Ed his thinking about
strategic Affairs so he has consistently
put as a primary concern
security as does the United States he's
put for Russia security making sure that
NATO doesn't get close to its borders I
think that's clear yeah I I I think as I
emphasized early on in our conversation
that leaders privilege security or
survival over everything else and by the
way he gave a number of talks uh and
press
conferences uh in addition to writing
that famous article that you referred to
on July 12th 2021 so we have you know a
pretty clear record of what he was
saying and I would argue what he was
thinking in the runup to the war in
February
2022 and if you read uh what he said uh
it's quite clear that he privileged
security or survival he was deeply
concerned about the security of Russia
and Russia is a quite vulnerable state
in a lot of ways especially if you think
back to what it looked like in the 1990s
you know better than I do uh it was in
terrible shape uh the Chinese talk about
the century of national humiliation one
could argue that for the Russians that
was the decade of national
humiliation and uh and it took Putin I
think quite a bit of time to bring the
Russians back from the dead I think he
eventually succeeded but uh it took a
considerable amount of time and I think
he understood that he was not playing a
particularly strong hand he was playing
something of a weak hand and he had to
be very careful very cautious and I
think he was uh and I think that's very
different than the United States the
United States was the unipole it was the
most powerful state in the history of
the world most powerful State relative
to all its possible competitors from you
know roughly 1989 certainly after
December 1991 when the Soviet Union fell
apart up until I would argue about 2017
we were incredibly powerful and even
after
2017 up to today the United States
Remains the most powerful state in the
system and because of our geographical
location uh we are in a uh
terrific uh situation to survive in any
great power competition so uh you have a
situation involving the United States
that's different than the situation
involving Russia they're they're just
much more vulnerable uh than we are and
and therefore I think Putin tends to be
more sensitive about security uh than
any American president in recent Times
Europe on one side China on the other
side it's a complicated situation yeah
and we talked before about 1812 when
Napoleon invaded and Moscow got burned
to the ground we talked about World War
I where the Russians were actually
defeated uh and surrendered uh and then
we talked about 1941 to 1945 where
although thankfully uh the Soviets
prevailed uh it was uh it was a close
call and I mean the casualties the
destruction that the Soviet
Union uh had inflicted on it by the
Germans is just almost almost hard to
believe
just uh so they are sensitive you can
understand full well or at least you
should be able to understand full well
why the idea of bringing Ukraine up to
their border really spooked them uh I
don't understand why more Americans
don't understand that it just it it
befuddles me
I think it has to do with the fact that
Americans are not very good in putting
themselves in the shoes of other
countries uh and uh you really if if
you're going to be a first class
strategist in international politics you
have to be able to do that you have to
put yourself in the shoes of the other
side and think about how they think so
you don't make foolish mistakes and as a
starting point Americans tend to see
themselves as the good guys and a set of
others as the bad guys and you have to
be able to empathize that Russians think
of themselves as the good guys the
Chinese think of themselves as the good
guys and just be able to empathize if
they are the good guys it's like that uh
funny skit are we the baddies consider
the United States could be the bad guys
like first of all like see the world if
the United States is the bad guys and
China is the good guys what does that
world look like be able to just exist
with that thought because that is what
the Chinese leadership and many Chinese
citizens uh if not now maybe in the
future will believe and you have to kind
of do the calculation the simulation
forward from that and same with Russia
same with with other nations yeah I
agree with you 100% and just you know I
always think of Michael McFall at
Stanford who was the American ambassador
to uh Russia I think between 2012 and
2014 and uh he told me that he told
Putin uh that Putin didn't have to worry
about NATO expansion because the United
States was a benign
hegemon and uh I asked Mike what Putin's
response was to that and uh Mike said
that Putin didn't believe it uh and uh
but Mike believed it he should believe
it and that we could move NATO Eastward
to include Ukraine and in the end we get
away with it because we are a benign
hegemon but the fact is that's not what
Putin saw Putin saw us as a mign
hedgemon and what Mike thinks or any
American thinks doesn't matter what
matters is what Putin thinks but also
the drums of War have been beating for
some reason NATO expansion has been
threatened for some reason so you've
talked about NATO expansion being
dead so like it doesn't make sense from
a geop political perspective on the
Europe side to expand NATO uh but
nevertheless that threat has been uh
echoed so um why has NATO expansion been
pushed from your perspective there are
two reasons one is first of all we
thought it was a wonderful thing uh to
bring more and more countri Ries into
NATO we thought that it facilitated
peace and prosperity it was ultimately
all for the good um and uh we also
thought that uh uh countries like
Ukraine had a right to join NATO these
are sovereign countries that can decide
for themselves and the Russians have no
say in what Ukraine wants to do and then
finally and uh this is a point I
emphasized before we were very powerful
and we thought we could shove it down
their throat so so it's a combination of
those factors that led us to pursue what
I think was ultimately uh a foolish
policy we've talked about how Wars get
started how do you hope the war in
Ukraine ends what are the ways to end
this war what are the ways to achieve
peace there to uh and the
the I would say
senseless death of young men as always
happens in
War I I'm sad to say I don't have a good
answer to that um I I don't think
there's any real Prospect of a
meaningful peace agreement I think it's
almost
impossible uh I I think the best you can
hope for uh at this point is it's some
some point the shooting stops you have a
ceasefire and then you have a frozen
conflict uh and that Frozen conflict uh
will not be highly stable uh and uh the
U ukrainians in the west will do
everything they can to weaken Russia's
position uh and the Russians will go to
Great Lengths to not only damage that
dysfunctional rum state that Ukraine
becomes but the Russians will go go to
Great Lengths to seow dissension within
the alliance and uh and that includes in
terms of transatlantic relations so
you'll have this
continuing security competition between
Russia on one side and Ukraine and the
West on the other even when you get a
frozen
peace uh and um or you get a frozen
conflict and uh and and and the
potential for escalation there will be
great uh so I think this is a disaster
that's a very realist perspective let me
ask you sort of a the The Human Side of
it do you think there's some power to
leader sitting down having a
conversation man to man leader to leader
about this there's there there is just a
lot of death
happening it seems that from an economic
perspective from a historic perspec from
a human perspective both nations are
losing is it possible for Vladimir
zalinski and and Vladimir Putin to sit
down and talk and
to uh figure out a way where uh the
security concerns are addressed and both
Nations can um minimize the amount of
suffering that's happening and and and
create a a path towards future
flourishing I think the answer is no
even with uh United States involved
three people in the room well I think
you if the United States is involved the
answer is definitely no you have to get
the Americans out uh and then I I think
if you have zinski and Putin talking you
know you have a sliver of a chance there
the Americans
are a real problem look let's go back to
what happens right after the war starts
okay as I said before this is we're
talking March early April of 2022 the
war starts on February 24th
2022 and as I said to you uh the two
sides were negotiating in aan buul and
they were also uh negotiating through
Neftali Bennett and the Bennett track
and the Turkish track were operating
together I mean they were not at Cross
purposes at
all what
happened Bennett tells the story very
clearly that they had made significant
progress in reaching an agreement this
is zalinski on one side and Putin on the
other Bennett is talking in person to
both Putin and uh
zalinski and what happens to produce
failure the answer is the United States
and Britain get involved and tell
zalinsky to walk they tell zalinsky to
walk if they had come in and encourage
zinski to try to figure out a way with
Putin to shut this one down and worked
with Bennett and worked with
erdogan we might have been able to shut
the war down then but it was the United
States well let me sort of uh push back
on that you're you're you're correct but
so United States paints this like um
picture that everybody's align so I
maybe you can correct me but I believe
in the power of individuals especially
individual leaders
again whether it's Biden or Trump or
whoever goes into a
room and says in a way that's convincing
that no more NATO
expansion and actually just on a basic
human
level ask the question of why are we
doing all this senseless
killing and look at the interest of one
Russia look at the interest of the other
Ukraine
their interests are pretty simple and
say United States is going to stay out
of this we're not going to expand NATO
and say all that in a way that's
convincing which is NATO expansion is
silly at this point china is the big
threat we're not going to do this kind
of uh conflict escalation with Russia
the Cold War is Over let's let's uh
normalize relations well let me just
embellish your argument okay thank you
I need it if we say there's a sliver of
a chance that you can do this and I do
think there is a sliver of a chance let
me just embellish your point Thank you
need all the help I can get two things
have to be done here in my opinion one
is uh Ukraine has to become
neutral and it has to completely sever
all security ties with the West right
it's not like uh you can say we're not
going to expand NATO to include Ukraine
but we're going to continue to have some
loose security arrangement with Ukraine
none of that has to be completely
severed Ukraine has to be on its own
okay and number two Ukraine has to
accept the fact that the Russians are
going to keep the four oblas that
they've now annexed and Crimea
right the Russians are not going to give
them back and what you really want to do
if you're zalinsky or who's ever running
Ukraine in this scenario that we're
positing is you want to make sure the
Russians don't take another four oblas
to include arke and Odessa
right if I'm playing Putin's hand and
this war goes on I'm thinking about
taking four more oblas I I want to take
about 40 3% of Ukraine and an exit to
Russia right and I certainly want Odessa
uh and I certainly want AR and I I want
the two o Bloss in between as well right
literally or as uh leverage in
negotiation no Ukraine neutrality I want
them literally uh I want to conquer them
literally uh but my point to you is if
we can begin to talk about cutting a
deal now you may be able to head that
kind of aggression off at the past in
other words you may be able to limit
Putin and Russia to annexing the four
oblas that they've now annexed plus
Crimea that's the best I think you can
hope for but the point is you have to
get the ukrainians to accept that you
have to get the ukrainians to accept
becoming a truly neutral State and
conceding that the Russians keep a big
chunk of territory it's about 23% of
Ukrainian territory that they've
annexed and I find it hard to imagine
any Ukrainian leader agree to that well
there there there could be more Nuance
things like no military involvement
between the United States in Ukraine but
economic involvement sort of uh
financial support So normalizing
economic relationships with Ukraine with
Russia I I think you could probably get
away with that I I think that the the
tricky question there that you would
have to answer is what about EU
expansion right and I think EU expansion
is probably a no no for the Russians
because most people don't recognize this
but there is a military Dimension built
into EU expansion it's not purely an
economic uh Alliance uh or relationship
or institution whatever word you want to
use there's a military Dimension to that
and in the runup to the War uh actually
in the runup to the 2014 crisis when it
first broke out uh the Russians made it
clear they saw EU expansion as a
stalking horse for NATO expansion so EU
expansion is tricky but I I think your
point of close economic relations
between uh or healthy economic relations
to use a better term between Ukraine and
the West is possible I I I think the
Russians have a vested interest in if if
it's a neutral Ukraine they have a
vested interest in that Ukraine
flourishing but that then brings us back
to the territorial issue all right well
so do you believe it's possible for
individual human relations to counteract
the structural forces that you talk
about so meaning the
leaders being able to pick up the phone
and make agreements that are good for
Humanity as a whole and for their
individual nations in the long term I
think leadership matters here
uh I mean one of the real problems here
is that there's no trust and uh on the
Russian side and that has to do with the
Minsk agreements um the uh uh the Minsk
agreements uh which were designed to
shut down the Civil
War uh in eastern Ukraine in the donbass
um really mattered to the Russians and
there were four players involved in the
uh uh the mince process uh four main
players Russia and Ukraine of course and
then Germany and
France and uh I believe the Russians
took the Minsk Accord seriously uh I
believe Putin took them very seriously
he wanted to shut down that
conflict um and uh
Angela Merkel Francois Holland he was
the French leader and penko who was the
Ukrainian leader those were the three
key players besides Putin again Holan
from France Merkel from Germany and
penko from Ukraine have all explicitly
said they were not seriously interested
in reaching an agreement in all of the
discussions with Putin they were
bamboozling him they were trying to
trick him so that they would buy time to
build up Ukraine's military uh Putin is
profoundly upset about these admissions
by these three leaders he believes he
was fooled into thinking that mince
could work he believes that he
negotiated in good faith and they did
not and he believes that the level of
trust now now between Russia uh and the
West is virtually zero as a result of
this experience over Minsk I only bring
this up because it cuts against your
argument that leaders could pick up the
phone and talk to each other and trust
each other at least somewhat uh to work
out a meaningful deal if you're Putin at
this point in time trusting the West is
not an idea that's going to be very
attractive at all in fact you're going
to distrust anything they say yeah
distrust anything the West say but there
is individual humans the way human
nature works is when you sit in the
cross from a person you can trust a
human being while still distrusting the
West I mean I I I believe in the power
of that I I think with the right leaders
you can sit down and talk like over
override the general structural distrust
of the West and say you know what I like
this guy or gal whatever I do hope
zilinsky and Putin sit down together and
talk have multiple
talks just remember they were doing that
in March and the Americans came in and
the British came in yeah and they
scotched a potential
deal
well uh the other beautiful thing about
human nature there's forgiveness and
there's
uh trying again when you're the leader
of a country in an anarchic
system you have to be very careful not
to let uh your trust in a foreign leader
take you too far because if that foreign
leader betrays you or betrays your trust
and stabs you in the back you could die
and again you want to remember that the
principal responsibility of any leader I
don't I don't care what country it is is
to ensure the survival of their state
and that means that you know trust is
only going to buy you so much and when
you've already
betrayed the trust of a leader uh you
really are not going to be able to rely
on trust very much to help you moving
forward now you disagree with that I
hope you're right and if they can shut
down the Ukraine Russia War uh it would
be wonderful if if I'm proved dead wrong
uh that would be wonderful news uh
my my prediction that this war is going
to go on for a long time and
uh and end in an ugly way is a
prediction that I don't like at all uh
so I hope I'm wrong you wrote that many
in the west believe that the best hope
for ending the Ukraine war is to remove
Vladimir Putin from power but you argue
that uh this isn't the
case can you explain well a lot of
people thought
when they were having all that trouble
the Russians were having all that
trouble with progan and the Vagner group
that Putin was vulnerable and was likely
to be
overthrown and what would happen is uh a
peaceloving leader would replace Putin
uh I made two points at the time and I
would make those same two points now
number one he's not
likely to be overthrown he was not
likely then to be
overthrown uh and I think you know as
long as his health holds up I think he
will remain in power my second point is
if he doesn't remain in power and he's
replaced I would bet a lot of money that
his replacement will be more hawkish and
more Hardline than Putin is uh I
actually think one could argue that
Putin was too trusting of the West
before the war
started uh and number two I think one
could argue that he has not waged the
war against Ukraine as vigorously as one
might have expected uh he was slow to
mobilize the nation for war
uh and he has pursued a limited war in
all sorts of ways uh the Israelis for
example have killed more civilians in
Gaza in one month than the Russians have
killed over 18 months in Ukraine the
idea that Vladimir Putin is waging a
punishment campaign and killing on
purpose large numbers of civilians is
simply not true uh all this is to say
that I would imagine that if Putin
leaves office and someone else comes in
to replace him that someone else will be
at least if not more Hardline than him
in terms of waging the war and certainly
will not trust the West any more than he
has by way of advice let me ask you if I
were to have a conversation interview
Vladimir Putin and zalinski
individually what should I ask them if
you me and Vladimir Putin are having a
chat what are
good ideas to explore what are good
questions to ask what are good things to
say on or off the mic once again that
could
potentially even slightly less than the
amount of suffering in the world caused
by this war oh I think if you get an
interview with Vladimir Putin there just
all sorts of questions you could ask him
and my sense is that Putin is a straight
shooter uh he's also very knowledgeable
about history and he has simple theories
in his head about how the world works
and I think he would level with you and
all you would have to do is just you
know figure out what all the right
questions are and that would not be hard
to do right uh you know you could ask
him why was he so foolish this is for a
for example why was he so foolish is to
uh uh trust uh poreno Holland and Merkel
uh in the Minsk
Accords uh you know why after his famous
talk at Munich in 2007 where he made it
clear that he was so unhappy with the
West uh did he continue uh to you know
in a very important way trust the West
Why didn't
mobilize uh the Russian military before
late September
2022 uh you know once the negotiations
that we were talking about before uh
involving
Istanbul uh and uh navali Ben and once
they broke down you know why didn't he
immediately mobilize more of the Russian
population to fight the war just all
sorts of questions like that and then
you could ask him questions about you
know where uh he sees this one headed uh
what's the best strategy for Russia uh
if the ukrainians will not agree to
neutrality right you know people like
John mearm say you'll probably take uh
close to half of Ukraine is that true uh
does it make sense to take
Odessa and John mimer also has questions
about
China your future relationships with
China
yeah I mean one really important
question that I would ask him is if the
United States had basically not driven
you into the arms of the Chinese if
there had been no war over Ukraine and
the United States had and its European
allies had gone to considerable length
to create some sort of security
architecture in Europe uh that resulted
in you Vladimir Putin having good
relations with Ukraine what would your
relations with China be
uh and uh you know how would you think
about that uh so there there are just
plenty of questions you could ask
him well hope Burns Eternal in my heart
I think probably in Putin's heart and
zelinsky's heart I
hope cuz hope is uh the leap of trust
that we've talked about I think is
necessary for deescalation and for peace
well you realize I have from the
beginning argued for different policies
that were all designed to prevent this
war from ever happening yes I don't know
if you know this but in 1993 I argued
that Ukraine should keep its nuclear
weapons I was probably the only person
in the west who made that argument and
my argument in 1993 this is in foreign
affairs was that there may come the day
when Russia thinks about invading
Ukraine and should that day come it
would be very helpful for preventing War
if Ukraine had nuclear weapons so
military might is essential for
maintaining a balance of power and peace
well if you're interested in deterring
an adversary if I'm worried about you
coming after me the best way to deter
you is to have military might and if
you're Russia and I'm Ukraine I'm far
weaker than you yeah right and having a
nuclear deterrent would be very
effective at convincing you not to
attack me because if you attack me
you're threatening my survival and
that's the one circumstance where it is
likely that I would use nuclear weapons
to defend myself and given the
consequences of nuclear use you would be
reluctant in the extreme to attack me so
that's why I argued in 93 that if
Ukraine kept its nuclear weapons that
made War down the road much less likely
and I believe I was correct and in fact
bill Clinton who played the key role in
forcing Ukraine to give up its nuclear
weapons now says he has said it publicly
you can find it on YouTube that he made
a mistake doing that furthermore I
argued in
2014 that it made eminently good sense
not to continue to push to bring Ukraine
into NATO because the end result is that
Ukraine would be destroyed and Ukraine
is being destroyed so I was deep deeply
interested at time in making sure that
that didn't happen for the good of the
ukrainians not to mention because
stability in Europe is a net positive
for almost everybody involved but people
did not listen to me then either how do
nuclear weapons change the calculus of
offensive realism because of mutually
assured destruction I mean it's not just
military might it's just so
destructive that you basically can't use
nuclear
weapons unless you want complete
destruction there's no question that the
presence of nuclear weapons makes it
much less likely I'm choosing my words
carefully here much less likely that a
great power would aggress against
another great power it doesn't take that
possibility off the table but it makes
it much less likely because of the
reasons that you
articulated uh but with regard tole
nuclear
use it's an interesting question how you
think about nuclear use in a mad world I
mean your point that we're in a mad
world
is that's mad Capital mad as well as mad
small letters but let's stick to the
capital letters we're in a world of
mutual assured destruction U there's no
question that in that
World um um it's uh unlikely that
nuclear weapons would be used but the
way you use nuclear weapons in that
world is you use them uh for
manipulation to risk purposes
demonstration
effect you you put both sides out on the
slippery slope now what exactly am I
saying here let me talk about NATO
Doctrine during the Cold War we lived in
a Mad World United States and Soviet
Union or the wara pack and NATO both had
an assured destruction capability so you
had mutual assured destruction
if the Warsaw Pact were to invade
Western Europe and here we're talking
about West
Germany uh and NATO was losing the war
we said that we would use nuclear
weapons how would we use nuclear weapons
given that we were in a Mad World the
argument was that we would use a handful
of nuclear weapons Against The warsa
Pact not to not necessarily against
their military forces could be in a
remote area we would use a small number
of nuclear
weapons to signal to the Soviets that we
were deadly serious about putting an end
to their
offensive uh and that we were throwing
both sides out on the slippery slope to
Oblivion in other words we were
manipulating risk and the last clear
chance to avoid Armageddon rested with
them and then we would tell them that if
you retaliated with a handful of nuclear
weapons and you didn't cease your
offensive against West Germany we would
launch a small another nuclear attack we
would uh explode a handful more of
nuclear weapons all for the purposes of
showing you our resolve right so this is
the manipulation of risk strategy and a
lot of the language I just used in
describing it to you is language that
Thomas Shelly invented right now fast
forward to the present if Russia were
you losing in Ukraine that's the one
scenario I think where Russia would have
used nuclear weapons and the question is
how would Russia have used nuclear
weapons again we're assuming that the
Russians are losing to the ukrainians I
believe
they would have pursued a manipulation
of risk strategy they would have used
405 30 or4 who knows nuclear weapons
maybe just one in a rural area that
kills very few people yes exactly and
basically that would spook everybody the
American just the mushroom cloud yeah
the it it's because of the threat of
escalation right again you your point is
we're in a mad world I accept that and
if you have limited nuclear use right we
understand hardly anything about nuclear
escalation because thank goodness we've
never had a nuclear war so once you
throw both sides out on the slippery
slope even if you only use one nuclear
weapon in your scenario you don't know
what the escalation Dynamics look like
so everybody has a powerful incentive to
put an end to the conflict right away I
might add to you that there were people
who believe that we would not even
initiate a manipulation of risk strategy
in Europe if we were losing to the warsa
pack during the Cold War both Henry
Kissinger and Robert mamar said after
leaving office that they would not have
done it they would have not initiated
nuclear use even limited nuclear use
that's what we're talking about here
they would rather be dead than dead
right that was the argument too risky
too risky that's exactly right but if
they had used one nuclear weapon in your
story or three or four in my
story everybody would have said oh my
God we've got to shut this one down
immediately I only tell you this story
or lay out this scenario be as an answer
to your question of how you use nuclear
weapons in a mad world and this is the
answer I this is all very terrifying uh
perhaps in part it's terrifying to me
because I can see in the 21st
century China
Russia Israel United States using a
nuclear weapon in this
way blowing it up somewhere in the
middle of nowhere that kills maybe
nobody but I'm terrified of seeing the
mushroom cloud and not
knowing what you know given social media
given how fast news
travels what the escalation looks like
there just you know in in in a in a
matter of minutes how the news travels
and how the leaders react it's
terrifying that this this little
demonstration of power um the Ripple
effects of it in a matter of minutes
seconds what that leads to because it's
like it's human emotions it's like you
you see the landscape of human
emotions the leaders and the populace
and and the way news are reported and
then the landscape of risk as you
mentioned shifting like the world's most
intense nonlinear dynamical
system and it it it's just terrifying
because the the the entirety of human
civilizations hangs in the balance there
and it's like like
this like hundreds of millions of people
could be dead let's just talk about this
in the context of the Ukraine war
um if uh if the Russians were losing as
I said before which is not the case
anymore but in 2022 it it did look like
that um if the Russians are losing and
they turn to nuclear weapons the
question is how do they use them and
they would use them in
Ukraine and because Ukraine has no
nuclear weapons of its own Ukraine
cannot retaliate it's not a mutual
assured destruction world it's a case
where one side has nuclear weapons and
the other doesn't that means that the
Russians are likely to think that they
can get away with using nuclear weapons
in ways that would not be the case if
they were attacking NATO and therefore
it makes nuclear use more likely okay
that's point one point two is let's
assume that the Russians use two or
three nuclear weapons in a remote area
sweating by the way just just as a
commentary the terrifying yeah the
question then is what does the West do
now mccrone has said and Biden has also
I think implicitly made this clear we
would not retaliate with nuclear weapons
if the Russians were to attack with a
handful of nuclear weapons in Western
Ukraine but then the question question
is what would we do MH and if you listen
to David Petraeus what David Petraeus
says is that we should attack the
Russian naval Assets in the Black
Sea and attack Russian forces in
Ukraine well once you do that you have a
great power of War you have NATO versus
Russia which is another way of saying
you have the United States versus Russia
we're now a great power War they have
nuclear weapons we have nuclear weapons
they've used nuclear weapons what is the
happy ending here and just to take it a
step further and go back to our earlier
discussion about moving NATO up to
Russia's borders the point I made which
you surely agree with is that the
Russians are very fearful when they see
NATO coming up to their border well
here's a case where not only is NATO
come up to their border but they're in a
war with NATO right on their
border what do the escalation Dynamics
look like there you know what the answer
is who knows that's should scare the
living but Jesus out of you right and
some of it could be like you mentioned
unintended there could be unintended
consequences there could be a Russian
missile misses and hits
Poland the these kinds of things that
just escalate
misunderstandings miscommunications
even a I mean nuclear weapon could be
boy it could have been planned to go
location X and it went to a location y
that ended up actually killing a very
large number of people I
mean uh
just that the the escalation that
happens there just happens in in a
matter of minutes and the only way to
stop that is communication between
leaders and that to me is a big argument
for ongoing communication
you know this's a story that during the
Cuban Missile Crisis um Kennedy put out
the word uh no
aircraft uh under any circumstances or
to penetrate Soviet airspace yeah yeah
and he then found out a few days later
that uh some guy hadn't gotten the
message and had penetrated in an
aircraft deep into Soviet airspace yeah
and uh this supports your basic point
that you know uh bad things happen and
uh and again the overarching point here
is we've never done this before
thankfully therefore we don't have a lot
of experience as to how it plays itself
out it it's really a theoretical
Enterprise because there's no empirical
basis for talking about
escalation uh you know in a nuclear
crisis and that of course is a wonderful
thing well in general the uh the human
species as a whole is a is a oneoff is a
theoretical Enterprise the survival of
the human species you know we've seen
Empires rise and fall but we haven't
seen the human species rise and fall so
far it's been rising but uh it's not
obvious that it doesn't end in fact I
think about aliens a lot and the fact
that we don't see aliens makes me
suspect it's not so easy to survive in
this complicated world of s Switching
gears a little bit and going to a
different part of the
world also engulfed in
war let me ask you about the uh
situation in Israel uh why did Hamas
attack Israel on October 7th 2023 as you
understand the
situation what was the reason that
attack
happened well I think the main reason
was that you had this suffocating
occupation I think as long as the
occupation persists the Palestinians are
going to
resist uh as you well know this is not
the first time there has been a
Palestinian Uprising there was the first
inata there was the second inata now
there's October 7th and their uprisings
besides those three uh so
this is not terribly
surprising uh a lot of people
hypothesize that uh this attack was due
to the fact that uh the Israelis the
Saudis and the Americans were working
together to Foster another Abraham
Accord uh and that the Palestinians
would in effect be sold down the river
uh I think given the fact that this was
in the planning stages for for probably
about 2 years uh and the Abraham Accords
with regard to Saudi Arabia are
relatively new phenomenon I don't think
that's uh the main driving force here I
think the main driving force is that the
Palestinians uh feel oppressed as they
should and that this was uh a resistance
move they were resisting the Israeli
occupation so that resistance
the attack involved killing a large
number of Israeli
civilians there's many questions ask
there but one is do you think Hamas
fully understood what the retaliation
will involve from Israel into
Gaza they had to understand I
mean you had you know operation castled
in
200 uh 8 2009 started I think right
after Christmas 2008 and it ended right
before President Obama took office uh in
January 2009 and
uh the Israelis periodically do what
they call mowing the lawn where they go
into Gaza and they pound the
Palestinians uh to remind them that
they're not supposed to rise up and
cause any problem uh
so there's no question in my mind that
the uh the Hamas forces understood full
well that the Israelis would retaliate
and they would retaliate in force as
they have done yeah even the metaphor of
mowing the lawn is disturbing to me in
many
ways um I actually
saw uh Norman filastine I think say that
well then if you use that metaphor then
you could say that Hamas was also mowing
the lawn that's such a
horrific image because the result on
either side is just the death of
civilians I mean let me ask you about
the death of civilians so during the
attack 1400 Israelis were
killed over 240 were taken hostage and
then in response as we sit
today uh Israel's military response has
killed over 10,000 people people in Gaza
and given the nature of the demographics
it's it's a very heavily young
population over 40% of them are under
the age of 18 of those killed that's uh
of course according to Ministry of
Health of Palestinian
Authority so what do you think is the
long-term effect on the prospect of
Peace when so many civilians
die I mean I think it's disastrous
U uh I
mean the only way you're going to get
peace here uh is if you have a two-state
solution um where the Palestinians have
a sovereign state of their own and there
is a sovereign Jewish State uh and these
two states live side by side American
Presidents since Jimmy Carter have
understood this full well and this is
why we have pushed very hard for
two-state solution indeed many americ
American Jews and many Israelis have
pushed for a two-state solution because
they think that that is the only way
you're going to get uh peace uh between
the two sides uh but what's happened
here is that in recent years the
Israelis have lost all interest in a
two-state solution uh and it's in large
part because the political center of
gravity in Israel has steadily moved to
the right uh when I was a young boy bo
uh the political center of gravity in
Israel was much further to the left than
it is today and uh it is in uh it is in
a position now the political center of
gravity where there's hardly any support
for two-state solution and Netanyahu and
the rest of the people in his government
were in favor or are in favor of a
greater Israel there's just no question
about
that well
on top of that you now have had a war
where as you
described huge numbers of civilians have
been killed and you already had bad
blood between the Palestinians and the
Israelis before this
conflict uh and you can imagine how
people on each side now feel about
people on the other side so even if you
didn't have this opposition in inside
Israel to a two-state
solution how could you possibly get the
Israelis now to agree to a two-state
solution I think for the foreseeable
future the animosity inside Israel
towards the Palestinians is so great
that it is impossible to move the
Israelis in that direction and the
Israelis here are the key players more
so than the Palestinians because it's
the Israelis who control greater Israel
it's the Israelis who you have to
convince now I want to be clear here you
also ultimately have to get around the
fact that Hamas right is not committed
to a two-state solution but I think that
problem could be dealt with it's
important to understand that Arafat and
the PLO was once adamantly opposed to a
two-state solution but Arafat came
around to understand that that was
really the only hope for settling this
and he became became a proponent of a
two-state solution and that's true of
makhmud abas who runs the PA in the West
Bank it's not true of Hamas at this
point in time they want a one-state
solution they want a Palestinian State
and of course the Israelis want a
one-state solution too which is a Jewish
state that controls all of U all of
Greater
Israel so the question is can you get
some sort of agreement and I think to
get to your the Nu of your question
given what's just happened uh it's
almost impossible to imagine that
happening anytime soon the cynical
perspective here is that uh those in
power benefit from conflict while the
people on both sides suffer is there
degree of Truth to that or for the
people in power to maintain power
conflict needs to continue no I I don't
believe that I mean just to take the
Netanyahu government or any Israeli
government that maintains
uh the occupation what you want is you
want a Palestinian population that
submits to Israeli domination of Greater
Israel you don't want resistance you
don't want an inada you don't want what
happened on October 7th in fact I think
one of the principal reasons that the
Israelis are pounding Gaza and killing
huge numbers of civilians punishing the
civilian population and way that clearly
violate the laws of war is because they
want the Palestinians to understand that
they are not allowed to rise up and
resist the occupation that's their goal
so I think the Israelis would prefer
that the Palestinians roll over and
accept submission in terms of the people
who live in Gaza to include the elites
and the people who live in the West Bank
to include the elites they would much
prefer prer to move to some sort of
situation where uh the Palestinians have
a state of their own I think in the case
of the pa uh under abas they would
accept a two-state solution I think what
at this point in time Hamas wants is a
one-state solution but they want peace
all of them want peace um you know the
two different sets of leadership in
Palestine and the Israelis so you think
Hamas wants peace sure but on its own
terms that's the point what does peace
look like for Hamas at this point in
time I think peace basically means a
greater Israel controlled by Palestine
or
Palestinians okay so essentially I mean
it's the whole land is called Palestine
and there's no Israel I think at this
point in time that's their principal
goal I do believe and there have been
hints over time Jimmy Carter has said
this that Hamas can be convinced that a
two-state solution assuming that the
Palestinians get a viable uh state of
their own that Hamas would buy into that
can we say that with a high degree of
certainty no but I think I think the
Israelis should have pursued that
possibility they should have worked with
abas they should have worked with Hamas
to do everything they can to facilitate
a two-state solution because I think
ultimately that's an Israel's interest
now the Israeli government and most
Israelis at this point in time I believe
don't agree with that what do you think
of Israel starting the ground invasion
of Gaza recently on October 27th the
question
is uh should they
continue uh until they have finally
defeated
Hamas uh there are all sorts of reports
in the media including in the Israeli
media that they're not going to be
allowed by the the United States to
continue this
offensive uh for much more than a few
weeks um the Israelis have been saying
it would it's going to take in in the
best of all possible worlds a number of
months if not a year to finish off Hamas
well it doesn't look like they're going
to have enough time to do that I doubt
whether they can finish off Hamas even
if they're given the time uh I think
they're going to run into Fierce
resistance uh and when they run into
Fierce resistance and large numbers of
Israelis going to die start to die uh
they'll lose their appetite for this and
they the Israelis surely know at this
point in time that even if they finish
off Hamas even if I'm wrong and they're
able to finish off Hamas another group
is going to rise up to uh resist the
occupation the idea that you can use
what Z Yaba insky called The Iron Wall
to beat the Palestinians into submission
is delusional it's just not going to
happen the Palestinians want a state of
their own they don't want to live under
occupation and uh there's no military
solution for Israel here there has to be
a political solution and the only viable
political solution is a two-state
solution I mean you can't go to
democracy you can't go to a situation
where you give the Palestinians equal
rights inside a greater Israel in large
part because there are
now as many Palestinians as there are
Israeli Jews and over time the balance
the demographic balance shifts against
the Israeli Jews and in favor of the
Palestinians in which case you'll end up
with a Palestinian state in Greater
Israel so you know democracy for all
doesn't work uh the Israelis I believe
are quite interested in ethnic cleansing
I think they saw this um uh this recent
set of events as an opportunity to
cleanse Gaza but that's not going to
happen uh the jordanians and the
Egyptians have made it clear that that's
not happening the United States has now
made it clear that that's not happening
and and the Palestinians will not leave
uh they'll die in place
uh so uh ethnic cleansing doesn't work
so you're really left with two
Alternatives a two-state solution or a
greater Israel that is effectively an
apartheid state I mean that's what the
occupation has led to and all sorts of
people have been predicting this for a
long long time and you've now reached
the point you know here in the United
States if you say that Israel's an
apartheid state that's going to get you
into all sorts of trouble but the fact
is that human Rights Watch Amnesty
International and Bellum which is the
leading Israeli Human Rights group all
three of those institutions or
organizations have issued detailed
reports making the case that Israel is
an apartheid state furthermore if you
read the Israeli media right all sorts
of Israelis including Israeli leaders
refer to Israel as an apartheid state
it's it's not that unusual to hear that
term used in Israel this is disastrous
for Israel in my opinion and Steve Walt
and I said this by the way when we wrote
the Israel Lobby that Israel is an
aparte state which is equivalent to
Israel as an occupier uh is not good for
Israel uh and that brings us back to the
two-state solution but as you and I were
talking about a few minutes ago it's
hard to see how you get a two-state
solution and the end result of this
conversation is utter
despair because the path to a two-state
solution is blocked by the amount of um
hate that's created by civilian deaths
well that plus the fact that the Israeli
government uh is filled with people uh
who have no interest in a two-state
solution they're
ideologically deeply committed to a
greater Israel they want all the land
between the Jordan River and the
Mediterranean and see to
be part of a Jewish state they're just
ideologically committed to that and uh
and of course as we were talking about
before with regard to Hamas Hamas wants
everything between the river and the sea
to be a Palestinian State and you know
when you have two sides with those kinds
of views right um um you're in deep
trouble because there's little room for
compromise so what you have to do to get
this to work is you have to convince the
Israelis that it's in their interest to
have a two State solution and you have
you've already taken care of the PA on
this front the Palestinian Authority but
you've got to convince Hamas that it's
uh its maximalist goals are are not
going to work and it's in its interest
uh to follow in the footsteps of Arafat
and accept a two-state solution but uh
even if you do that at this Point let's
say that you know there's a lot of
willingness uh intellectually on both
sides to do that the problem is that the
hatred that has been fueled by this
recent con uh this ongoing conflict is
so great that it's just hard to imagine
how you can make a two-state solution
work at this juncture uh that's why I've
sort of taken to saying and I hope I'm
wrong here that you know on the
two-state solution uh that that boat has
sailed it's just you know it's no longer
possible well again I believe in
leadership and there's other parties
that play here Other Nations Jordan
Saudi Arabia other other players in the
m in the Middle East that could help
that could help through a normalization
of relationships and these kinds of
things there's there's always hope like
you said Slither of Hope Slither of hope
I think human civilization progresses
forward by taking advantage of the all
the slithers it can get uh let me ask
you about you mentioned the Israel Lobby
you wrote a book probably your most
controversial book on the topic not
probably clearly the most controversial
book I ever wrote so you've uh
criticized the Israel Lobby in the
United States for influencing US
policy um in the Middle East can you
explain what the Israel Lobby is their
influence and your
criticism over the past let's say a
couple
decades well the argument that Steve
Wall and I made actually we wrote an
article first and uh which appeared in
the London Review of Books uh and then
we wrote the book
itself uh our argument is that the lobby
is a loose Coalition of uh individuals
and
organizations uh that push American
policy in a pro-israel
direction uh and uh basically the law is
interested in getting Israel excuse me
getting the United States and here we're
talking mainly about the American
government to support Israel no matter
what Israel does and our argument is
that if you look at the relationship
between the United States and Israel
it's unprecedented in modern history uh
this is the closest relationship that
you can find between any two countries
in recorded history it's truly amazing
the extent to which Israel and the
United States are joined at the hip and
we support Israel no matter what almost
all the time uh and uh our argument is
that that is largely due to the
influence of the lobby the lobby is uh
an extremely powerful interest group now
it's very important to understand that
the American political system is set up
in ways that allow interest groups of
All Sorts to wield great influence so in
the United States you have an interest
group or a Lobby like the National Rifle
Association that makes it well nigh
impossible to get gun control right uh
and so with the Israel Lobby you have
this group of individuals and organ
organizations that wield enormous
influence on US policy toward the Middle
East and this
is not surprising given the nature of
the American political system uh so our
argument is that the lobby is not doing
anything that's illegal or illicit or
immoral or unethical it's just a good
old-fashioned American interest group
and it just happens to be extremely
powerful and our argument is that this
is not good for the United States
because no two countries have the same
interests all the time and when our
interests conflict with Israel's
interest we should be able to do what we
think is in our national interest in
America's national interest but the
lobby tends to conflate America's
national interests with Israel's
national interests and wants the United
States to support Israel no matter what
we also argue and I cannot emphasize
this enough given what's going on in the
world today that the
Lobby's effects the lobby has not
been pushing policies that are in
Israel's interest so our argument is
that the lobby right the lobby pushes
policies that are not in America's
interest or not in Israel's interest now
you're saying yourself what exactly does
he mean by
that what every president since Jimmy
Carter has tried to do as I said before
is to foster a two-state solution to
push Israel which is the dominant
player in Greater Israel push Israel to
accept the two-state solution and we
have run into huge resistance from the
lobby whenever we tried to let's be
blunt about it course Israel right in a
perfect world where there was no Lobby
and an American president was free to
put pressure on Israel to coers Israel I
believe we would have gone a long way
towards getting two-state solution and I
believe this would have been in Israel's
interest uh but we couldn't get a
two-state solution because it was almost
impossible to put meaningful pressure on
Israel because of the lobby so this was
not an Israel's interest and it was not
in America's interest and that was the
argument that we made and uh we of
course got huge pushback for making that
argument what's the underlying
motivation of the lobby is it religious
in nature is it um similar to the way
warhawks are sort of militaristic in
nature is it nationalistic in nature
what what's uh if you were describe this
loose Coalition of people what what
would you say is their motivation well
first of all I think you have to
distinguish between Jews and Christians
you want to remember that there are a
huge number of Christian zionists who
are deeply committed to Israel no matter
what right and then there are a large
number of Jews the Jews are obviously
the most important of those two groups
in the Israel lobby but you know one of
the arguments that we made in the book
is that you should not call it the
Jewish Lobby because it's not populated
just by Jews and Christians ey in this
are an important part of that lobby but
furthermore there are a good number of
Jews who are opposed to the lobby uh and
the policies that the lobby purveys and
there are uh a number of Jews who are
prominent
anti-zionists right so and they're
obviously not in the lobby or or if you
take a group like Jewish voice for peace
right Jewish voice for peace is not in
the lobby so
it's wrong to call it a Jewish lobby but
with regard to the American Jews who
were in that Lobby uh I I think that
really this is all about nationalism
it's not so much religion many of those
Jews who are influential in the lobby
are not religious in any meaningful
sense of that term but they
self-identify as Jewish in in in the
sense that they feel they're part of a
Jewish nation and that that in addition
to being an American right they are part
of this tribe this nation called Jews
and that they have a
responsibility um to push the United
States in ways that support uh the
Jewish state so I I think that's what
drives most if not almost all the Jews
this is not to say there's not a
religious dimension for some of them but
I think that the the main connection is
much more tribal in nature
so I had a conversation with Benjamin
Netanyahu and he said fundamentally if
you're anti-zionist you're
anti-semitic so the the the Zionist
project is tied at the hip to the Jewish
project what do you have to say to that
look you can Define
anti-Semitism any way you want right and
you can Define anti an semitism to
incorporate anti-zionism
uh and uh I think we have reached the
point where
anti-Semitism is identified today not
just with anti-zionism but with
criticism of Israel if you criticize
Israel people will say some people will
say you're an
anti-semite and if that's your
definition of
anti-semitism it's taken an important
term and stretched it to the point where
it's
meaningless right so when Steve and I
wrote the book uh wrote the article and
then wrote the book all sorts of people
said that we were anti-semites this is a
ludicrous charge but what they meant was
you're criticizing the lobby you're
criticizing Israel and therefore you're
an
anti-semite okay if that's what an
anti-semite is somebody who criticizes
Israel you know probably half the Jewish
Community if not more in the United
States is anti-Semitic and of course you
get into all these crazy games where
people are calling Jews self-hating Jews
and anti-semites because they're
critical of Israel but even people who
are anti-zionists I don't think they're
anti-semitic at all uh you can argue
they're misguided that's fine but uh
many of these people are Jewish and
proud of the fact that they're Jewish
they just don't believe that nationalism
and Jewish nationalism is a force that
should be applauded and you want to
understand that in the American context
there is a rich tradition of
anti-zionism
right and these were not people who were
anti-semites if you go back to the 30s
40s 50s and the same thing was even true
in Europe there were all sorts of
European Jews who were opposed to
Zionism were they anti-semites I don't
think so but we've gotten to the point
now where people are so interested in
stopping any criticism of Israel that
they wield this weapon of uh calling
people anti-semites uh so uh Loosely
that uh the term has kind of lost
meaning so I I think n who is is
wrongheaded to equate uh anti-zionism
with anti an semitism Alan dtz was one
of the people that called you
specifically
anti-semitic so
just looking at the space of
discourse how do
you where's this Slither of Hope for
healthy discourse about us relationships
with
Israel
uh between you and alen dtz and others
like him well I think until there is a
settlement of the Israeli Palestinian
conflict there's no hope of putting an
end to this nonsense right so these are
just uses of terms to kind
of cheat your way through the through
the discourse it's shortcut no it's the
silence people right it's very very
important to understand that one of the
lobb's principal goals is to make sure
we don't have an open discourse a free
willing discourse about Israel because
they understand people in the lobby
understand that if you have an open
discourse Israel will end up looking
very bad right you don't want to talk
about the occupation you don't want to
talk about how Israel was created right
all all these subjects are ones that uh
will cause problems for Israel see just
to go to the present crisis okay when
you have a
disaster and what happened on October
7th is a disaster one of the first
things that happens is that people begin
to ask the question how did this happen
right what's the root cause of this
problem this is a disaster we have to
understand what caused it so that we can
work to uh to make sure it doesn't
happen again so we can work to shut it
down and then make sure it doesn't
happen again but once you start talking
about the root causes right you end up
talking about how Israel was created
right and that means telling a story
that is not pretty about how the
zionists conquered
Palestine uh and number two it means
talking about the occupation right it's
not like uh Hamas attacked on October
7th because there were just a bunch of
anti-semites who hated Jews and wanted
to kill Jews this is not you know Nazi
Germany right this is directly related
to the occupation and to what was going
on inside of Gaza and it's not in
Israel's interest or the Lobby's
interest to have an open discourse about
what the Israelis have been doing to the
Palestinians since I would say roughly
1903 when the second Aliah came to
Israel or came to what was then
Palestine right we want to talk about
that and we don't want to talk about
from the Lobby's point of view the
influence that the lobby has right uh
it's better from the Lobby's point of
view if most Americans think that uh
American support of Israel is just done
for all the right moral and strategic
reasons not because of the lobby and
when John mirer and Steve Walt come
along and say you have to understand
that this special relationship is due in
large part to the Lobby's influence that
is not an argument that uh people in the
lobby want to hear so the point is you
have to go to Great Lengths for all
these reasons you have to go to Great
Lengths to silence people like me and
Steve Walt and one of the ways to do
that is to call us anti-semites I think
the chapter or the section of the book
where we talk about this charge of
anti-Semitism is called the Great
silencer that's what we call the charge
of anti-Semitism the great silencer who
wants to be called an anti-semite
especially in the wake of the Holocaust
do I want to be called an anti-semite oh
my God no uh and uh so it's very
effective but you know it is important
to talk about these issues in my humble
opinion and I think if we had talked
about these issues uh way back
when it would have gone a long way
towards uh you know maybe getting a
two-state solution
which I think was the best alternative
here it it's complicated and I I wonder
if you can comment on the complexity of
this because criticizing Israel and you
know criticizing the
lobby can
um for a lot of people be a dog whistle
for sort of anti-Semitic conspiracy
theories that you know this idea that
Jews run everything run the world or
this kind of
cabal and you know
it's it's also very true that people who
are legitimately
anti-semitic are also critics of Israel
in the same kind of way and so it's such
a complicated landscape in which to have
discussions because
um uh you know even people like David
Duke uh who are you know racists don't
sound racist on the surface
well I haven't listened to him enough
but like you know there's dog whistles
it's it's a complicated space in which
to have
discussions because it um I mean I
wonder if you can sort of speak to
that um because there's this silencing
effect of calling everybody anti-semitic
but it's also true that there is
anti-Semitism in the world like there is
a sizeable population of people that
hate Jews there's probably a size of
population of people who hate Muslims
too but you know I lot of hate out there
a lot of hate out there uh but the
hatred of Jews has like a long history
and so you have like you know Rolling
Stones have a a set of great hits and
there's just a set of great hits of the
wayte conspiracy theories that you can
make up about the Jews that are used as
part of the hatred uh so there's like
nice templates for that and I I just
wonder if you can comment on
operating as a historian as an analyst
as a strategic thinker in this kind of
space yeah we obviously when we wrote
the article which we did before the book
gave the subject a great deal of thought
I mean uh what you say just now is music
to our ears I'm talking for me and about
me and Steve uh I mean I think that you
know your point about dog whistles is
correct look we went to Great Lengths to
make it clear that this is not a cabal
it's not a conspiracy and in fact in a
very important way the lobby operates
out in the open right
uh they brag about their power right and
this was true before we wrote the
article right and um and we said in the
article and the book and you heard me
say it here first of all it's not a
Jewish Lobby
right um secondly it's not a cabal right
it's an American interest group and and
the American system is designed such
that interest groups are perfectly legal
and some of them are super effective
exact I mean you hit the nail right on
the head that's exactly right
and you know and there was nothing that
we said that was anti iiic by any
reasonable definition of that term and
you know huge numbers of Jews have known
me and Steve over the years and nobody
ever ever said that we were anti-semitic
before March 2006 when the article
appeared because we're not
anti-semitic but look you've got this
interest group right that has a
significant influence on American policy
and un Israeli
policy
and you want to talk about it it's just
important to talk about it it's
important for Jews right in the United
States for Jews in Israel to talk about
this the idea that you want to silence
critics is not a smart way to go about
doing business in my
opinion if we were wrong if Steve and I
were so wrong and our arguments were so
foul
they could have easily exposed those
arguments they could have gone uh into
combat with this in terms of the
marketplace of ideas and easily knocked
us down the problem was that our
arguments were quite powerful and
instead of engaging us and defeating our
arguments they wanted to silence us and
this is not good right it's not good for
Israel it's not good for the United
States and I would argue in the end if
anything it's going to Foster
anti-Semitism I think you don't want to
run around telling people that they
can't talk about Israel without being
called an anti-semite it's just not it's
not healthy uh in terms of the issue
that you're raising right but I still
agree with you that it is a tricky issue
it's I I don't want to make light of
that you know I know that there's this
piece of liter out there called the
protocols of the Elders of Zion and I
fully understand that if you're not
careful you can come close to writing
volume two of the protocol but I don't
believe that we wrote anything that was
even close to that and again I think
that a healthy debate on the issues that
we were raising would have been not only
in America's interest but it would have
been in Israel's
interest yeah I mean know underneath at
all is just I wonder why there is so
much hate against groups why it's such a
sticky way of
thinking not just tribalism like proud
of your country and kind of hating
another country but really deeply hating
like hating in a way where it's part of
your identity kind of
hate well just to make a general point
on this issue in our conversation here
today you often talk about individual
leaders and the word individual often
pops up in your vocabulary yes I believe
that we are ultimately social animals
before we are individuals I believe
we're born into tribes we're heavily
socialized and that we carve out space
for our
individualism but we are part of tribes
and or social groups or nations call
them what you want ethnic groups
religious groups but the fact is that
these tribes often crash into each other
and when they crash into each other they
end up hating each other uh if you go to
a place like Bosnia right the croats and
the serbs oh my God and then throw in
the
bosniacs which is the term for Bosnian
Muslims and you know Muslims cowat serbs
uh oh and uh the tribes you know hate
each other uh and uh in a funny way that
hatred almost never goes away uh and uh
I guess there are some exceptions to
that uh if you look at the Germans after
World War II they've gone a long way
towards reducing I wouldn't want to say
completely eliminating but reducing a
lot of the hatred uh that existed
between Germans and their
neighbors uh but that's really kind of
an anomalous
case uh I mean you go around East Asia
today and the hatred of Japan in a place
like China the hatred of Japan in a
place like Korea just not to be
underestimated and uh so but I think a
lot of it just has to do with the fact
that you're dealing with social groups
that have crashed into each other uh at
one point or another and there are those
lingering effects and by the way this
gets back to our discussion a few
minutes ago about trying to get it to
State solution between the Palestinians
and the Israeli Jews now that you have
had uh this horrible War uh which is
ongoing it's
interesting to ask to go back to World
War II now you said uh you studied Nazi
Germany in in the 30s from a perspective
of
maybe offensive
realism uh but just to look at the
Holocaust it's sometimes popular in
public discourse today to compare
certain things to the Holocaust people
have compared the Hamas attack on Israel
to the
Holocaust saying things like it's the
the
biggest attack on Jews since the
Holocaust which kind
of
implies that there's a comparison U
people have made that same comparison in
the other
direction what do you make of this
comparison
is it comparable is it is the use of the
Holocaust uh have any accuracy in
comparisons of modern-day International
politics is it possible that you could
have another
genocide yes and I would argue that what
you had in Rwanda was a
genocide right the Holocaust is not the
only
genocide I believe the word genocide
is used too Loosely
today uh and as you know lots of people
and I mean lots of people who are pro
Palestinian accuse the Israelis of
engaging in genocide in Gaza I think
what the Israelis are doing in Gaza uh
represents a massacre I I would use that
term given the number of civilians that
they've killed and the fact that they've
been indiscriminate in terms of how
they've been bombing Gaza but I would
not use the word
genocide uh for me a genocide is where
one side attempts to eliminate another
group from the planet uh I think that
what happened with the Holocaust was
clearly a genocide and that the Germans
were bent uh on destroying all of
European jewry and if they could have
gotten their hands on uh Jews outside of
Europe they would have murdered them as
well that's a genocide and I think with
the hutus and the tootsies you had a
similar
situation uh I think with the Turks and
the Armenians during World War I that
was a genocide but I have a rather
narrow definition of what a genocide is
and I don't think there are many cases
that qualify as a genocide the Holocaust
certainly does okay
now what Hamas did doesn't even come
close to what happened to European jury
between let's say
1939 uh and 1945 although I date the
start of the Holocaust to
1941 if we were you know looking at it
closely but let's just say 1939 when
they invade Poland 1939 to
whated pales in comparison it's hard to
believe anybody would make that argument
right yeah yes a lot of Jews died uh but
uh uh
hardly
uh hardly any compared to the number
that died uh you know at the hands of
the Germans I mean it just no parallel
at all uh and furthermore Hamas was in
no position to kill all of the Jews in
the Middle East just not not going to
happen yeah but there's also levels of
things you know using uh Germans using
uh human skin for lamps there's just
levels of evil in this world yes but you
don't see that with I mean that's not
what Hamas is doing I mean I I want to
be very clear here I am not justifying
the kill hamas's killing of civilians
okay not for one second but I'm just
saying and and and by the way just to go
to the
Israelis and what they're doing in Gaza
right as I said to you before I do
believe that is a massacre and I believe
believe that's to be condemned the
killing of
civilians uh this is not legitimate
collateral damage they're directly
punishing the population but I would not
call that a genocide right and I would
not compare that to the Holocaust for
for one second I just want to be very
clear on that do you think uh if Israel
could they would avoid the death of any
civilians so you're saying there's some
degree of punishment of colletive
they're purposely killing civilians it's
this is the Iron Wall they're trying to
beat the Palestinians in the
submission
right there's no way you kill this many
civilians
um if you're trying to precisely take
out Hamas Fighters and by the way the
Israeli spokesman the IDF spokesman has
explicitly said that we are not pursuing
Precision bombing and what we are doing
is trying to you know maximize the
amount of Destruction and damage uh that
we can inflict on the
Palestinians and uh I I I think this is
a major mistake on the part of Israel
first of all it ends up being a moral
stain on your reputation number one and
number two it doesn't work it doesn't
work the the Palestinians are not going
to roll over and submit to uh isra
Israeli domination of their
life um so you know the whole concept of
the Iron Wall uh Yaba tinsky term was
misguided um and and and by the way the
iron if you look at what the Israelis
are doing they're trying to do two
things one is the iron wall and that's
where you punish the civilian population
in Gaza and get them to submit the other
thing that they're trying to do is get
Hamas they want to destroy Hamas and the
belief there is that if they destroy
Hamas they've solved the problem but as
many Israelis know including people on
the hard right even if you destroy Hamas
they are going to be replaced by another
group another resistance group uh and
that resistance group will employ Terror
yeah I think you I think you've said
that uh other terrorist organizations
have used the situation in Palestine as
a as a kind of a recruit recruitment
mechanism for for a long time
Osama bin lad made it clear that this
was one of his principal reasons for
attacking the United States right and
the United
States attacked back and uh got us into
a 20-year war that
cost the lives of millions of people not
not American but uh human beings yeah
and uh engaged in torture in
torture yeah no I think if you look at
how we reacted to
9/11 and how the Israelis are reacting
to what happened on October 7th uh
there's uh quite a bit of similarity in
that both sides the Israeli side and the
American side uh are enraged right and
they lash out and they go on a
rampage and the end result is not good
is there a capacity within Israel or
with within United States after
9/11 to do something approximating turn
the other
cheek
of understanding the root of Terror is
hate and fighting that hate
with uh not the naive but
compassion well I I don't think in
either case you're going to turn the
other cheek uh I think well some mil I
what I mean by that is some limited
powerful military response but very
limited yeah coupled with a smart
political strategy political strategy
diplomacy yeah that's what they should
have done yeah right but is their
capacity for that or from your offensive
realism perspective it's just the odds
are really
low no from my offensive realist
perspective or my realist perspective
that's what you should do right you okay
my my view is states are rational actors
they should be cunning right they should
think about uh the Strategic situation
are in and choose the appropriate
response and uh what happens and this is
why my theory is not always correct is
that sometimes states are not rational
and they
misbehave I would argue in the Israeli
case uh that it would have been good
after October 7th or start starting on
October 7th if the United States had uh
tried to hold the Israelis back and
countenance uh a more uh moderate
response a more uh to SP take some time
just to think about how to deal with
this problem instead of lashing out I I
think given what happened to the
Israelis given how shocked they were
given the level of fear given the level
of AG they were going to lash out and I
don't believe that was in their interest
I think it would have been made would
have made sense to to think about it and
uh to think about a smarter strategy
than they're now employing and I think
you know the Americans blew it the
Americans gave them a be hug and a green
light and said we'll give you all the
Weaponry you need and go out and do it
and uh I don't think that was the smart
thing to do look in the wake of October
7th the Israelis had no good strategy
right it's it's not like there's a magic
formula that they just didn't see and we
should have told them what the magic
formula was right that's not true they
were in a sense caught between IR Roa
and a hard place in terms of what to do
but they're smarter things and Dumber
things and I think the
Israelis lashed out in ways that are
counterproductive I think you know going
on a rampage and you know killing huge
numbers of civilians is not it's
obviously morally wrong but it's also
just not in their strategic interest
right I mean uh because it's it's not
going to buy them anything right and in
fact it's going to cost them right
because people all over the planet are
turning against Israel uh I saw you know
an Israeli think tank today uh that has
been tracking U protests around the
world um gave some figures for what it
looked like uh between October 7th and
October 13th in terms of the number of
uh protests around the world that were
pro-israel versus Pro Palestine and then
it looked at the numbers from U October
13th up to the present and I think the
numbers were 69 9% were Pro Palestinian
in the first six days after October 7th
69% and I think 31% take these numbers
with a grain of salt 31% were pro-israel
so I think it was 69 and
31 um and uh since then since October
13th if you look at the number of
protests around the world 95% have been
Pro Palestinian and 5% have been
pro-israel
uh and what this tells you is that
public opinion around the world has
shifted against Israel and if you look
at some of the demonstrations in places
like London and Washington DC it's truly
amazing the number of people who are
coming out in support of the
Palestinians and uh all this again is
just to support my point that it was
just not smart for Israel to uh launch
this bombing campaign right you can make
it an argument for going after Hamas and
doing it in a surgical way or as
surgical a way as possible uh but uh
that's not what they did and again my
point to you is I think that this
punishment campaign is not going to work
strategically in other words they're not
going to beat the Palestinians into
submission they're not going to finish
off Hamas and at the same time by
pursuing this strategy they're doing
huge damage to their reputation around
the world
well I just uh yeah in the wake of
October
7th given the geopolitical
context I think there's a lot of
Leverage to be the great ethical
superpower that demonstrate power
without killing any
civilians and use that leverage
diplomatic leverage to push forward
something like abrahamic Accords with
more nations with with Saudi Arabia
push for peace
aggressively peace agreements this kind
of stuff economic relationships all this
kind of stuff and thereby pressure the
Palestinian Authority you know towards
um perhaps a two State
solution but I think what you're missing
here just in the Israeli case is that
the Israeli government is not interested
in two-state solution and you want to
remember that Benjamin Netanyahu who
looks very hawkish when you look at him
in isolation doesn't look so hawkish
when you look at him compared to the
rest of the people in his cabinet right
he he he almost looks like a moderate
he's got a lot of people who are way out
to the right of him
and these people and this of course
includes Netanyahu are not interested in
the two-state solution so the question
you have to ask yourself is you if
you're if you're Benjamin Netanyahu and
it's July 7th late in the excuse me
October 7th late in the day what do you
do you're not thinking about a two-state
solution you're thinking about an
occupation that's not going to end and
the question is how do you deal with the
Palestinians given what's just happened
well there's people in the cabinet and
then there's history and history
remembers great leaders and so uh
Benjamin nyaho can look in the streets
of Israel and the see the protests and
think of how history will remember him
and I think a two-state solution is on
the table for a great leader well it was
there was he the person who was gonna
take advantage of it I don't think so
but well he's student history well at
this point what the will see does I mean
it's very at this point it's very
difficult um like you said 95% now or
whatever the number is of protests I
think the the window in which
Israel has the ears of the world it can
do the the big ethical peace act action
towards peace is uh I think has closed
or maybe there's still a Slither but
it's just
the uh the slippery slope of of hate is
has taken off it's quite depressing to
watch I agree 100% unequivocally
depressing but you know of course as you
talk about the the role of you the US
involvement is of critical importance
here for the United
States and the argument you make is that
we should not be involved in
Ukraine at least to the degree we are we
being the United States uh and we should
not be involved in Israel to the degree
we are because it's stretching us too
thin when uh the
big geopolitical contender in the 21st
century with United States is
China that is that a correct
summary yeah I I I think just on Ukraine
we should not have pushed Ukraine to
join NATO sure uh and once the war
started we should have worked overtime
to shut it down immediately March Yeah
March right and and you remember by the
way not to go back to Ukraine in great
detail in the fall early fall of 2022
the war starts February 2022 there March
2022 which we've talked about which is
the negotiations in the fall of 2022 I
think it was in
September uh the ukrainians had won two
major tactical victories one in hiran
and the other in harke and at that point
in time General Millie who was the
chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff
said now is the time to negotiate
because this is the high watermark for
the ukrainians yeah Billy understood
that they things were only going to get
worse and the White House shut Millie
down and said we're not negotiating so
we have blown a number of opportunities
here to head this problem off at the
pass uh and uh but that's my view there
and uh with regard to the Israelis my
only point about Israel is that it would
be better for Israel and better for the
United States if we the United States
were in was in a position the United
States was in a position to put pressure
on Israel from time to time as Steve and
I say in the book we should be able to
treat Israel like a normal country right
the fact is that countries sometimes do
stupid things this includes the United
States and Israel and if Israel is
pursuing a policy that we think is
unwise we should be in a position where
we could put pressure on Israel yeah
that's our argument right but
anyway we goofed both with regard to
Ukraine and with regard to the Middle
East and we're now up to our eyeballs in
alligators in both of those regions and
as you describe my view this is not good
because the area of the most strategic
importance for the United States Today
Is East Asia and that's because China is
there and China is the most serious
threat the United States faces do you
think there will be a war
with China in the 21st century I don't
know uh my argument is there will be
there is right now a serious security
competition and uh at the same time
there is a real possibility of War
whether or not we avoid it is very hard
to say uh I mean we did during the Cold
War we had a serious security
competition from roughly
1947 to
1989 and uh and we thankfully avoided
war probably came the closest in 1962
with the Cuban Missile
Crisis but uh we avoided it and I think
we can avoid it here is it for sure no
you've said that China won't move on
Taiwan militarily in part because it's
uh as you said amphibious operations are
difficult why will China not move on
Taiwan is in your
sense uh in the near future well it's
because there's this body of water
called the Taiwan straigh which is a big
body of water and getting across water
uh is very difficult unless you can walk
on water so geography still has a role
to play in the 21st century oh yeah I
think geography is very important big
bodies of water really matter yeah in an
Ideal World you'd like to have the
Pacific Ocean between you and any
potential adversary you know 6,000 miles
yes 6 ,000 miles of water hard to get
across yes I if you're a country and I'm
a country and there's land between us I
can take my Panzer divisions and I can
go right across the land and get into
your country or attack your country and
you of course can take your Panzer
divisions and come across that same
piece of land but if there's a big body
of water between us your Panzer
divisions can't go across the water and
then the question is how do you get them
across the water and that's very tricky
and in a world we have lots of
submarines and you have lots of aircraft
and you have missiles that are landbased
that can hit those surface ships it is
very very hard to you know to attack
across a body of water and all you have
to do is think about uh Normandy you
know the American invasion of Normandy
June 6th 1944 coming in on Omaha Beach
right uh oh boy that was really
difficult but there is a growing
asymmetry of military power there that
even though it's difficult that is
correct so I I guess that is correct so
I recently had a conversation with Elon
Musk and and he
says
that uh you know China is quite serious
about the one China policy and it seems
inevitable that Taiwan will have to be
if you look at this
pragmatically in the 21st century it
seems inevitable that Taiwan will have
to be a part of China and so we can get
there either diplomatically or
militarily like
um what do you think about the
inevitability of that kind of idea when
a nation says this is a top
priority for us
um what do you think about them meaning
it and what do we do about that
there's no question it's a top priority
for them and there's no question they
mean it but it's also a top priority for
us not to let them take Taiwan why
exactly because it's an important
strategic asset uh many people will say
it's because taiwan's a democracy but
that doesn't matter that
much uh it's
because uh of two strategic reasons the
first is that uh if we were to let
Taiwan go it would have hugely negative
consequences for our alliance structure
in East Asia to contain China we need
allies we have an alliance structure and
our allies Japanese South
Koreans Filipinos
Australians they're all counting on us
to be there for them and if we say we're
not going to defend Taiwan the Chinese
attack they're going to say I bet if the
Chinese attack us the American Amer an
won't be there for us uh so the it would
have
uh a damaging effect on our allian
structure which we cannot afford because
because containing China is a wicked
problem it's a powerful State you were
getting to this before when you talked
about China versus Taiwan so that's the
first reason second reason is you want
to bottle up the Chinese Navy and the
Chinese Air Force inside the first
island chain you don't want to let them
get
out uh into the Pacific you don't want
them dominating the Waters of East Asia
you want to bottle them up again inside
the first island chain and you can only
do that if you control Taiwan you don't
control Taiwan they get out into the
Philippine Sea into the Pacific and the
Western Pacific and cause all sorts of
problems well you saying all that you've
also said the century of humiliation
Japan and the United States are source
of that humiliation for
China don't you think they see the other
side of that absolutely and in the
interest of avoiding a World
War I guess the question is uh how do we
avoid a World War it
doesn't um seem like the military
involve involvement in the conflict
between China and Taiwan is the
way well I I don't want there's no good
answers here I'm just saying there are
no good which is the the less bad option
well what you want to do is you want to
make sure that you
deter uh China from invading Taiwan you
want to avoid a war you and I are in
complete agreement on that we don't want
a war but we want to contain China we do
not want to let China dominate Asia that
that's what the Americans are
principally concerned with here and it's
what China's neighbors are principally
concerned with this includes the
Japanese the South South Koreans
Filipinos Australians and the Taiwanese
we they don't want and we don't want
China to dominate the region so we have
to contain it but at the same time and
this should be music to your ears we not
only want to contain it we want to make
sure we don't end up in a shooting match
with the Chinese because this could be
disastrous so you have to have a very
smart policy you have to build powerful
military forces and you have to make
sure you don't do anything that's
provocative netive on Taiwan for example
the last thing you want is for the
Taiwanese government to declare its
independence because the Chinese have
said if Taiwan does that we'll go to war
and of course we don't want that so my
view is you want to smartly build up
your military forces and you want to do
everything you can to contain China uh
and at the same time not be
provocative so a big component of that
is making
sure your military the US military is
bigger than the Chinese
military not necessarily uh it's an
interesting
question uh a lot of people think that
to make deterrence work right you have
to be able to beat the Chinese and
therefore you need a much bigger
military uh and I don't think over time
that's possible right I think it's
probably not even possible now to beat
the Chinese in a war over Taiwan or in a
war in the South China Sea I think what
you want to do is make it clear to the
Chinese either that there will be no
winner in other words you don't have to
win but you want to make sure they don't
win okay it's it's it's a lose
lose U proposition if they go to war
over Taiwan or what have you uh and if
you can't do that right you think that
they're so powerful that they're
ultimately going to win you want to
convince them that Victory would be a
pic victory in other words they would
pay a God awful price to win the war you
follow what I'm saying so excuse me the
best strategy for deterence is you win
China loses second best strategy is a
stalemate nobody wins third best
strategy is they win but they pay a god-
awful price and the fourth possibility
which you don't want is they win quickly
and decisively right uh if that's the
case then you don't have much
deterrence what is a world with China is
the sole dominant superpower look like I
mean a little bit underlying our
discussion is this kind of idea that us
is the good guys and China is the bad
guys first of all you know the you know
dividing the world into good good guys
and bad guys seems to
somehow miss the Nuance of this
whole human civilization project we're
undertaking but what does the world look
like where China is the dominant sole
superpower in a unipolar
world well I I don't tend to think of
the world in terms of good guys and bad
guys as a good realist I I think that
you know states are States they're all
black boxes you know I don't
discriminate between democracy and
autocracies but having said that I am an
American right and as an American I'm
interested in the security of my country
the survival of my country so I want the
United States to be the most powerful
state in the world which means I want
the do United States to dominate the
Western Hemisphere I want us to be a
regional hedgemon and I want to make
sure that China does not dominate Asia
the way we dominate the Western
Hemisphere
it's not because I think we're the good
guys and they're the bad guys uh if I
were Chinese and I were in Beijing and I
were XI jinping's National Security
advisor I'd tell him what we got to do
is make sure we dominate the world or
dominate our region and then do
everything we can to undermine America's
position in the Western Hemisphere right
that that be my view uh so I guess you
could say I do view the world in terms
of good guys bad guys cuz I'm an
American and more like us and Them
versus yeah it's us and them that's
that's a nice way to put it yeah it's US
versus them not so much good guys versus
bad guys is it possible to have a stable
peaceful world with a good balance of
power with where it's China and us as
superpowers you it's a bipolar world no
longer unipolar yeah okay so you're
hypothesizing a world where they
dominate Asia yeah and we dominate the
Western Hemisphere I I believe there
would be uh a great deal of security
competition intense security competition
between those two superpowers the
definition of intents matters here so it
could be
small small military conflicts or it
could be extremely large unstable
military conflicts right well conflict
let's use the word War okay so I I
distinguish between security competition
and War and what I'm telling you is
you'll have an intense security comp
competition where there's no shooting or
if there's shooting it's mainly proxies
that are doing the fighting much like
the Vietnam War right uh or you could
have a case where one of those
superpowers was involved in a war
against a proxy of the other superpower
Korean War think the Korean War the
United States fought the Chinese who
were allied with the Soviets at the time
mhm but uh a war between the United
States and China just like a war between
the United States and the Soviet Union
during the Cold War that's what you
really want to avoid avoid so I think
you'd have an intense security
competition right you'd have wars
involving proxies of each of those two
superpowers and you would probably have
some Wars where one of the superpowers
was involved in a proxy right with the
other super one of the super other
superpowers proxies so it seems likely
then if that's the case then it would be
Taiwan is the proxy and us fighting
China through the proxy of Taiwan what
yeah well that would assume the United
States but you want to remember you're
hypothesizing a situation where China
dominates Asia oh already has dominated
yes it's already dominated Taiwan uh I
see we we well where do you find the
proxies austr the Middle East could be a
good case oh wow Persian Gulf right oh
boy and then our discussion of Israel
becomes even more dramatically yeah well
Israel Israel gets involved I think I
think in this scenario if you're talking
about a us China
competition right and you're talking
about the Middle East I think it's the
gulf it's it's the Saudis the Iranians
the Iraqis it's the oil don't you think
it could be Israel versus Iran with
some very 1984 kind of dramatic
Partnership of Iran Russia and China
versus is United States Europe and um
Israel I think that's possible yeah I
think that's possible yeah now that I I
mean I hadn't thought about it uh until
you said it but yeah I think that that
that is possible is isn't that
terrifying yeah well that you know in
your scenario where China already
dominates Asia and we dominate the
Western Hemisphere uh I think you start
talking about where the most likely
places uh that the United States and
China go
head-to-head or or fight through proxies
uh I think it is the goal for the Middle
East and the scenario that you
posit I mean one one question I
have I don't know about you but for me
unlike with the Soviet
Union and I know I was born there but
even outside of that the cultural
Gap the the the loss in Translation the
communication gap between China and the
United States seems to be much greater
than that of what was the former Soviet
Union and the United
States I see two cultures intermingling
and communicating as one of the ways to
deescalate future
conflict it's an interesting question I
mean it it is sort of an abstract
theoretical level my argument is that
great Powers Act according to realist
dictates and they understand those
realist dictates and uh that can lead to
cooperation or it can lead to uh War uh
it depends U I would say just in the
case of the Soviets a lot of people
describe the Cold War as an ideological
competition above all else it's was
communism
versus liberal democ y or communism
versus liberal capitalism whatever uh I
actually don't believe that I I believe
the Soviets were uh realists to the core
uh I believe Stalin was a realist par
Excellence uh and that ideology did not
matter much in Stalin's foreign policy
and I believe if you look at Soviet
foreign policy uh after World War II you
know throughout the Cold War they were
realists to the core uh and uh and I
think in those days the Americans were
realists right uh a lot of liberal
ideology floating around out there but
the Americans were realists and I think
one of the reasons you avoided a
shooting match between the United States
and the Soviet Union from 47 to uh
89 uh was because both sides I think uh
understood basic balance of power
logic us China competition is somewhat
different first of all the Chinese are
realists to the core uh I I've spent a
lot of time in China I basically have
rock and roll I'm basically a rock and
roll star in China uh the Chinese you're
kind of a big deal in China I love it
the Chinese are my kind of people
they're realists right they speak my
language yeah it's the United States
that is not very realist American
leaders uh have a very powerful liberal
bent and tend not to see see the world
in realist terms I Believe by the way
just going back to our discussion of
NATO expansion I think our inability to
understand that NATO expansion was
anathema to the Soviet to the Russians
was doing large part to the fact that we
just during the unipolar moment didn't
think of international politics from a
realist perspective and didn't respect
anyone who thought about International
politics from a realist
perspective if those various American
Administration starting with the Clinton
administration had put their realest hat
on they would have understood that NATO
expansion into Ukraine was not a good
idea but we had this thoroughly liberal
view of the world that dominated our
thinking and it's gone away somewhat
since we've moved into multipolarity but
not
completely and uh this makes me a little
nervous right to pick up on your point I
mean the United States is thinking about
the world in ways that are somewhat
different than the Chinese Who real is
par exellence so that's fascinating so
the Chinese are
pragmatic uh about thinking of the world
in
um as a competition of military Powers
all the ways in which he described the
realist perspective so that I mean
that's a that's a that's a hopeful thing
right
if uh we can achieve stability and a
balance of powers through that military
competition yeah I I actually think
that's right I think if the United
States just let me talk a little bit
about the United States to get at the
issue you're raising if the United
States pursues a smart containment
strategy given what you just said and I
said about the Chinese I think we will
avoid war the problem with the Americans
is it's not just the
liberalism it's the possibility that we
will pursue a roll back policy in other
words during the Cold War uh we pursued
containment it was whenever anybody
talked about American Grand strategy
towards the Soviet Union was Containment
containment containment we now know from
the historical record that the United
States was not only pursuing containment
it was pursuing rollback we were trying
to roll back Soviet power to put it
bluntly we were trying to wreck the
Soviet Union okay and I would not be
surprised moving forward with regard to
China if the United States pursu is a
serious roll back policy and uh so
you're saying throughout history United
States was always doing that always
where's that from why why can't we
respect the power of other nations
because they may be a threat to us we
well I mean you you don't look you don't
respect the power of other nations you
fear the power of other nations well
fear and respect to Nextdoor neighbors
depending on the neighborhood you're
living in but I I just mean it's it
could be very very counterproductive to
try because if you can empathize with
their if if you assume they're rational
actors you trying to roll back will
create um would lean into the
uncertainty of potential conflict so you
want to avoid the uncertainty of
potential conflict caution right well
yes and no look your point is you want
to empathize you want to be able to put
yourself in the shoes of the other side
yes I agree 100% but with that right
it's very important if you're a first
class strategist to be able to do that
but at the same time there is this
competition for power taking place and
what you want to do is maximize how much
power you have relative to the other
side and the other side wants to
maximize how much power it has relative
to you so you have this competition for
power right uh that's taking place all
the time and that's taking place at the
same time you want to have empathy or
you want to be able to put yourself in
the shoes of the other side so those two
things kind of go together right it just
feels less threatening to build up your
thing versus try to hurt the other
person's thing the other group's thing
right but if you build up your own power
you are building up your capability to
hurt the other side right but like you I
guess you don't rattle the saber just
just work on manufacturing
Sabers well I agree with I I think that
you know the United States you know uh
wants to make sure it has a big stick in
East Asia for purposes of containing
China and avoiding a war right again I
want to be clear I'm not advocating uh
that we start World War I but the point
is you want to have a big stick and you
want to make sure that you don't
overstep your bounds in terms of using
that big stick this is the danger with
rollback yeah right that you get too
aggressive and you precipitate a war
right and you also just have to be very
careful what you say and to go back to
your favorite argument you want to be
able to have empathy or put yourself in
uh the shoes of the other side because
if you do something you want to think
smartly about what that other side how
that other side is going to see your
action and how they're going to react MH
right and and mostly focus on the
carrots have a giant stick laying around
but never mention it just focus on the
carrots well occasionally you have to
mention the stick right no everyone
knows the stick is there there is some
truth in that right I mean yeah uh but
you know and words matter a lot it feels
you know this uh current President
Biden's meeting with Xi Jinping and I
think the words exchanged there are are
really important I have an oce that
leaders can stop Wars just as much as
they can start wars well leaders matter
there's no no question about that no
question but just on on rhetoric you
want to remember that Putin has on more
than one occasion very subtly rattled
the nuclear sword oh yeah and it has
been very effective yeah because Joe
Biden has paid attention and Joe Biden
wants to make sure we don't end up in a
thermonuclear war and thank goodness uh
he's thinking that way so all Putin has
to do is mention the possibility of
nuclear War just to go back to Taiwan
you know a switch areas of the world if
you're interested in containing China
and you're interested in
deterrence and let's go back to those
various scenarios where the Chinese win
we win Chinese win but they do it at a
costly at Great cost one could
argue that that discussion that I laid
out before didn't take into account
nuclear weapons MH and all President
Biden or any of his successors has to do
is just very subtly uh
rattle uh or or or or or employ the
nuclear threat you know
uh and just sort of remind the Chinese
that you know you start a war over
Taiwan it could easily escalate into a
nuclear war you want to understand we
both have nuclear weapons and if either
one of us is put into a desperate
situation
we may turn to those nuclear weapons and
oh by the way XI jingping you want to
understand that we're out here in the
water and using nuclear weapons in the
water it's not that uh it's not the same
as using War uh nuclear weapons on land
so we may very well use them I'm not
saying we will but anyway a little saber
rattling yeah right let me just zoom out
on human history what makes Empires
collapse and what makes them last when
they do
when you look at human history in your
sense thinking about the United States
perhaps as an
Empire I don't view the United States as
an Empire uh what's the What's the defin
so to you Empire is a thing that seeks
expansion
constantly yeah I I think it's a country
uh that incorporates
different uh regions or areas around the
world
uh into sort of a giant sphere of
influence without
incorporating those
territories actually into the state
itself so you had this thing called the
British Empire and it controlled areas
like
India uh uh North
America uh and Kenya just to pick a
couple instances at different points
Singapore would be another example
Australia would be another example so
these were all entities that were part
of the British Empire right and the
United States has taken a stabit Empire
uh after the Spanish American war for
example uh with regard to the
Philippines and Cuba and Puerto Rico but
we never got serious about it there's
never been an American Empire this is
not to say the United States is not an
incredibly powerful country that goes
all around the world building military
bases and stationing troops Here There
and Everywhere but we're not running an
Empire the way the British Empire was
run or the French
Empire uh so the question for me is why
did those Empires go away the why' the
British Empire go away if you ever look
at a map of the world in 1922 after
World War I it's truly amazing how much
of that map is controlled by Britain
right they had a huge Empire and it's
disappeared probably by far the biggest
in terms of area Empire in human history
I think so I think that's right it
almost has to be yeah right right uh
it's crazy crazy yeah it's and then no
longer no longer is the case yeah now I
I'm going be clear the the Americans
have
wielded maybe even greater influence
than Britain did when it had its Empire
but I don't believe we have an Empire
that bears any resemblance to the
British
Empire so the question is what happened
to that British Empire what happened to
the French Empire what happened to the
Belgian Empire what happened to the
Dutch Empire these were countries that
had colonies all over the planet the
Dutch East Indies right Vietnam was you
know French Indochina where where did
those Empires go two factors finished
them
off number one nationalism nationalism
became a very powerful force in the 19th
century it began to rear its head in the
late 18th century and became a very
powerful force in the 19th and certainly
in the 20th can explain nationalism here
nationalism is the idea that these
different nations that were part of the
Empire like the Kenyans wanted their own
State nation state this is my point
about the Palestinians right this is
Palestinian nationalism what is Zionism
Zionism is Jewish nationalism Jewish
nationalism think of Theodore herzl's
famous book it's called the Jewish State
nation state think of the word nation
state that embodies nationalism nation
state Jewish State Palestinians want
their own State two-state solution right
can't beat the Palestinians into
submission right the Indians wanted
their own State The pakistanis Wanted
their own State the Kenyans wanted their
own State Singapore wanted its own State
oh the Americans wanted their own State
this is called the American Revolution y
right so that's the first reason
nationalism that these Empires
disappeared the second reason is that
from a cost benefit analysis uh they no
longer made any sense uh and it was the
coming of the Industrial Revolution once
the Industrial Revolution comes an
Empire is basically an albatross around
your neck I would argue that the British
Empire was an albatross around Britain's
neck in most of the 20th century some my
friends disagree with that and think
there were all sorts of benefits uh from
the British Empire but you want to
remember that in the 20th century the
three countries that really were
powerful were the United States Germany
and the Soviet Union those were the big
three did any of them have an Empire
no that's a good car in the industrial
world yes you don't need you know uh an
Empire right what you need is a powerful
manufacturing base well the the cost
benefit analysis is different before the
Industrial Revolution there's been many
empires there's no question that Empires
uh came and went right I mean yes right
and or you have to do is just look at
the British and the French uh in the
Seven Years War 1756 to
1763 the British win they get Canada
right and that's why you know Quebec
Montreal all these big French speaking
areas are now part of uh Canada right uh
so borders change and you know C
countries got established the United
States being one and remember South
America and Central America were once
completely dominated by the Spanish and
in the case of Brazil the
Portuguese but uh they all in the 19
Century got their
independence right and what I'm saying
to you is in the 19th and in the 20th
century there were two forces that were
really driving the train one is
nationalism and then the other is the
Industrial Revolution which changes the
cost benefit
analysis almost too crazy of a question
but if you
look let me calculate let's say 500
years from now and you you you John M sh
somehow travel through time and are at a
bookstore looking at the uh entire
history of human civilization in a
single book what role does US play like
what's the story of us over the next 100
200 300
years is it a big role small
role well that's a long time if you you
ask me let's just say the next 100 years
yeah that's okay I think that's still
tough that's still tough
but actually you know I think we're in
excellent
shape and here's the reason going back
to the beginning of our conversation you
asked me you know about power and I told
you the two principal building blocks of
Power are population size and wealth
okay and therefore you want to look
around the world and you want to look at
what you think the demographics are of
country like
Britain uh the United
States uh
Iran uh China Russia pick your country
moving forward right what the
demographics look like and how wealthy
of those are those countries likely to
be what you discover very quickly and is
that almost every country around the
world is
depopulating over
time right Russia's going to be much
smaller China's going going to be much
smaller uh 100 years from now than both
of those countries are it's best we can
tell United
States American women are not having
lots of babies these days no question
about that but we have immigration we're
an immigrant culture you're a perfect
manifestation of that you're perfect
you're now an American that's wonderful
we need more people like you right so
when I hear Donald Trump and others
arguing that immigration is a terrible
thing this is
ridiculous immigration is what made us
great right it's when my relatives came
over in the middle of the 19th century
from Germany and Ireland right that's
fascinating like you know because there
you know there's been a huge
concern America and other developed
nations are not having enough children
but you you just made me
realize in the long Arc of History the
United States has gotten really damn
good at integrating immigrants and you
and like helping them flourish the whole
diversity of uh the that makes up
America there's a Machinery of
integrating other
cultures yeah yeah just very quickly on
this that's F Sam Huntington's book who
are we yeah uh which in many ways I I
love that book but it has one
fundamental flaw and a number of people
told him beforehand that that flaw
existed and he didn't fix it but Sam
argues in the book that we have large
numbers of Hispanics in this country and
we're doing a very poor job of
integrating them into the mainstream and
they're not becoming Americans and
because many of them are concentrated in
the southwest of the United States
unlike other ethnic groups that were
spread out all over God's Little Green
Acre right we're going to have uh this
cohesive group of Spanish-speaking
Americans right who we going to want to
break away and the United States is no
longer going to be you know a reasonably
coherent nation
state he's wrong the all the evidence is
that Hispanics are integrating into the
American
mainstream uh more quickly and more
effectively than the European econom uh
the European immigrant groups that came
starting around 183 5 if you look at
immigration from Europe into the United
States leaving aside the original wasps
who came over and founded the place the
immigrants start coming in large numbers
in 1835 and we really don't shut the
door until
1924 right starting this is a crude
overview starting in 1835 and running up
till about
1885 it's mainly Germans and Irish
that's why Germans are the largest
ethnic group to ever come to the United
States and the Irish are right behind
them these are the European ethnic
groups we're talking about then starting
in
1885 uh polls Jews and Italians start
coming right uh and the Germans and
Irish keep coming and this is why Ellis
Island is opened I think it's 1893 Ellis
Island is open because Castle Garden in
New York which had handled all the
previous immigrants coming across the
pond Castle Garden couldn't handle them
all so they opened up Ellis Island
that's why somebody like me I can't find
my distant relatives records in Ellis
Island because they came through Castle
Garden right whereas lots of Jews I know
lots of Italians I know they can find
their relatives records in Ellis Island
because they came through Ellis Island
the point is you had all these
immigrants who came in roughly between
1835 and 1924 when we shut the gates
that's the only time we've ever really
shut the gates in a meaningful way right
and this is what made America great M
right all these people and they made
lots of babies right so in some sense
make America great again means getting
in getting more immigrants in well we
open the gates again in 65 mhm closed
them in 24 open them in 65 I'm over
simplifying the story here because we
didn't completely shut them we almost
completely shut them in 24 opened in 65
and we've had huge numbers of immigrants
flowing in these immigrants who have
been flowing in since 65 are not
Europeans they're not mainly Europeans
they're mainly Hispanics and
Asians if you look at those Hispanics
and Asians they're integrating into the
American mainstream at a much faster and
more effective clip than was the case
with those immigrants who come came in
in the 19th century and early 20th
century the Irish oh my God you know
they were treated horribly there's a
book very famous book that's been
written called when the Irish became
White just think about the title of that
book there was discrimination against
all these groups right and the worst
discrimination of course was against
Chinese Americans right uh but we've
gotten much better and what we should do
moving forward is redouble our efforts
to integrate immigrants into the
American mainstream you know Hispanics
you know Asians of All Sorts because the
fact is that America is rapidly reaching
the point where it's not going to be an
allwhite country right uh I have five
children and two of my children are was
it Generation Z gen
Z gen Z is the last majority
white uh generation right subsequent
Generations are not majority White
uh So for anybody who's bothered by this
I'm not bothered by that but for anybody
who is bothered by this they better get
used to it because Americans aren't
making enough babies that we can
continue to grow uh population wise in a
robust way so we need immigration and
we're an immigrant culture and this is a
great virtue it has been a great virtue
over time there should be a source of
hope not wor
that's my view that's my view and
America when it works is a place that is
very attractive to immigrants and
immigrants can do very well here and and
then the real key moving forward is in
marriage right and you have a huge
amount of in marriage right somebody was
telling me not too long ago that the
highest inar marriage rates in the
United States are among Asian women
Asian-American women Asian women and
anglos right and uh I say
wonderful uh and uh great yeah no the
more love uh is the fastest way to
integrate yeah well you don't what you
want to do is you want to eliminate
difference yes right you want to
eliminate difference right it's like you
know people who say I'm an anti-s semi
right I have two grandsons who Adolf
Hitler would have thrown into a guest
chamber one of whose first name is John
and middle name is Mir shimer right yeah
this is what you want yeah right Steve
Walt's wife and his two children would
have been thrown into a gas chamber by
Adolf Hitler right this is what you want
you want intermarriage now there are
good number of people in some of those
groups especially among Jews who don't
like
intermarriage right but they've lost
because I haven't looked recently at the
data uh the data among um uh for in
marriage rates among uh basically
secular Jews but it used to be around
62% large numbers of Jews marry Guam and
they've lost because of inner marriage
in marriage helps fight tribalism
destructive kind of tribalism exactly
nice calling me an
anti-semite they haven't met my
grandsons my son-in-law nieces that I a
niece that I have nephews that I have
brother-in-laws that I have Jewish right
come on and this this gives a really
nice hopeful view of America is is the
integration of different different
cultures different kinds of peoples that
is a unique property of America yes but
just to go back to where we started it
was not smooth in the beginning all
things are rough in the beginning all
things are rough in the
beginning what advice would you give to
a young person today about how to have a
career they can be proud of or a life
they can be proud of well I think it's
very important to make sure that you do
something in life that really interests
you my mother used to use this phrase
floats your boat you want to do
something that floats your boat or to
use another one of my mother's phrase
phrases you want to get up you want to
do something where you get up out of bed
in the morning with a bounce in your
step right so I I think that you know if
your mother and father want you to be a
lawyer and they're pushing you to be a
lawyer and you don't want to be a lawyer
you want to be a policeman be a
policeman right don't do what other
people want you to do because it's very
important to find a job and occupation
that you really
love uh the second thing I would say and
this has to do with your point about um
humility
uh uh you want to think about the
humility uis index my friend Steve
vanever who teaches at MIT he and I
invented this this concept we call it
the uis humility index and you want to
have a healthy dose of humility but you
also want to have a healthy dose of
ubis you want to think you can change
the world you want to think you can make
things better for yourself you want to
take chances you want to think sometimes
that you know better than other people
do ubis is not a bad thing but at the
same time you have to have humility yeah
you have to understand that a man or a
woman has his or her limits and you want
to listen to other people you want to be
a good listener right uh so always
remember the importance of the uis
humility index and the importance of
having healthy doses of both uus and
humility speaking of humility you're
mortal like all humans are do you Ponder
your immortality are you afraid of it
are you afraid of death I'm not sure I'm
afraid of death uh I I don't want to die
because I enjoy life so much having too
much fun yeah I you know given how
horrible the world is today I hate to I
hate to say that I'm having too much fun
but do I find what I do interesting and
gratifying I I I do uh I just love what
I do uh and I love studying you know
International politics and I love being
intellectually curious about all sorts
of subjects I love talking to you about
this and that uh I mean this is really
wonderful and I often tell people you
know thank goodness I'm only 28 years
old because I do try to behave like I'm
only 28 years old but I am well aware of
the fact that uh as my mother used to
say nothing is forever and that includes
me and when you're 75 going on 76 you
understand that you have a limited
number of years left uh and I find that
depressing um because I've been I've
been very lucky and uh and I feel like
I've won the lottery and uh I'm very
thankful for that and I I'd like to you
know make it last for as long as
possible but uh I do understand that you
know nothing is
forever yeah the finiteness of things
yeah you never think that when you're
young I mean you know you think uh
you're going to live forever and you're
just not going to get old I never
thought this would happen that I would
become 75 years old well you you got you
got so much energy and boldness and
fearlessness and if and an excitement to
you that I'm I'm really grateful to see
that especially given how much I'm sure
you've been attacked for
having uh bold ideas and presenting them
and not losing
yeah not losing that youthful energy is
beautiful to see thank you not becoming
cynical John it's a huge honored to
speak with you that you give me so much
time and so much respect and so much
love I this was a really incredible
conversation thank you so much for
everything you do in the world for
looking out into the world and trying to
understand it and teach us and thank you
so much for talking with a silly kid
like me it my pleasure thank you very
much I thoroughly enjoyed it
awesome thanks for listening to this
conversation with John mimer to support
this podcast please check out our
sponsors in the description and now let
me leave you with some words from
Plato Only The Dead have seen the end of
War thank you for listening and hope to
see you next
time