every star in the sky probably has
planets Y and life is probably emerging
on these planets but I think the
commentarial space Associated to these
planets is so different our causal cones
are never going to overlap or not easily
and this is a thing that makes me sad
about alien life why it's why we have to
create alien life in the lab as quickly
as possible because I don't know if we
are going to be able to be able to
build um
architectures that will intersect with
alien intelligence architectures in
intersect you you don't mean in time or
space time and the ability to
communicate the ability to communicate
yeah my biggest fear in a way is that
life is everywhere but we become
infinitely more lonely because of our
Scaffolding in that commentarial
space the following is a conversation
with Lee Cronin his third time in this
podcast he is a chemist from University
of Glasgow who is one of the most Most
Fascinating brilliant and fun to talk to
scientists I've ever had the pleasure of
getting to know this is Alex Freedman
podcast to support it please check out
our sponsors in the description and now
dear friends here's Lee
Cronin so your big assembly Theory paper
was published in nature congratulations
thanks it created uh I think it's fair
to say a lot of controversy but also a
lot of interesting discussion so maybe I
can try to summarize assembly Theory and
you tell me if I'm wrong okay for it so
assembly Theory says that if we look at
any object in the universe any object
that we can quantify how complex it is
by trying to find the number of steps it
took to create it and also we can
determine if it was built by a process
akin to evolution by looking at how many
copies of the object there are yep
that's spot on y spot on spot on I was
not expecting that okay so let's go
through
definitions so there's a central
equation I'd love to uh talk about but
definition wise what is an
object um yeah an object so from so if
I'm going to try to be as meticulous as
possible objects need to be
finite um and they need to be
decomposable into
subunits all human-made artifacts
objects um is a Planet an object
probably yes in the if you scale out so
an object is finite and countable and
decomposable um I suppose mathematically
but yeah I still I still wake up some
days and go to think to myself what is
an object because it's it's it's a
non-trivial um question persists over
time I'm quoting from the paper here an
object that's finite is distinguishable
so that's a weird adjective
distinguishable we've had so many people
help offering to rewrite the paper after
it came out you wouldn't believe it's so
funny persists over time and is
breakable such that the set of
constraints to construct it from
elementary building blocks is
quantifiable such that the set of
constraints to construct it from
elementary building blocks is
quantifiable the history is in the
objects it's kind of cool right so okay
so what finds the object is it's history
or memory whichever is the sexier word
I'm happy with both depending on the day
okay so the set of steps it took to
create the object so there's a
sense in which every object in the
universe has a history Y and that is
part of the thing that is used to
describe its complexity how complicated
it is okay what is an assembly index so
the assembly index if you to take the
object apart and be super lazy about it
or minimal say what it because you know
it's like you've got a really short-term
memory so what you do is you lay all the
parts on the path and you find the
minimum um number of steps you take on
the path to add the parts together to to
to reproduce the object and that minimum
number is the assembly index is a
minimum bound and it was always my
intuition the minimum bound an assembly
theory was really important and I only
worked out why a few weeks ago which is
kind of funny because I was just like no
this is Sacra sank I don't know why it
will come to me one day and then when I
was pushed by a bunch of
mathematicians um we we we came up with
the the correct physical explanation
which I can get to but it's the minimum
and it's really important it's the
minimum and the reason I knew the
minimum was right is because we could
measure it so almost before this paper
came out we've with published papers
explain how you can measure the assembly
in index of molecules okay so that's not
so trivial to figure out so when you
look at an object we can say a molecule
we can say object more generally mhm to
figure out the minimum number of steps
it takes to create that
object that doesn't seem like a trivial
thing to do so with molecules is it's
not trivial but it is possible because
what you can do and because I'm I'm a
chemist so I'm kind of like I see the
lens of the world for just chemistry um
um I break the molecule apart break
bonds and if you break up if you take a
molecule and you break it all apart you
have a bunch of atoms and then you can
say okay I'm going to then Form B take
the atoms and form bonds and go up the
the chain of events to make the molecule
and that's what made me realize take a
toy example literally toy example take a
Lego object which is broken up of Lego
blocks so you could do exactly the same
thing in this case the Lego blocks are
naturally the smallest they're the atoms
in the actual composite Lego
architecture but then if you maybe take
you know um a couple of blocks and put
them together in a certain way maybe
they have a they offset in some way that
offset is on the memory you can use that
offset again with only a penalty of one
and you can then make a square triangle
and keep going and you remember those
motifs on the Chain so you can then leap
from the the start with all the Lego
blocks or atoms just laid out in front
of you and say right I'll take you you
you connect and do the least amount of
work so it's really like uh the the
smallest um um steps you can take on the
graph to make the object and so for
molecules it came relatively intuitively
and then we started to apply it to
language we've even started to apply it
to mathematical theorems but I'm so well
out of my depth but it looks like you
can take minimum set of axioms and then
start to build up kind of uh
mathematical architectures in the same
way and then the shortest path to get
there is some something interesting that
I don't yet understand so what's the
computational complexity of figuring out
the shortest path in um with molecules
with language with mathematical theorems
it seems like once you have the fully
constructed Lego
Castle or whatever your favorite Lego
world is figuring out how to get there
from the building basic building blocks
isn't like a is that an N hard problem
it's a hard problem it's a hard problem
but actually if you look at it so the
best way to look at it for let's take a
molecule so if the molecule has um 13
bonds first of all take 13 copies of the
molecule and just cut all the bonds so
take cut 12 bonds and then you just put
them in order yeah and then that's how
it works so and you keep looking for
Symmetry and re or or copies so you can
then shorten it as you go down and that
becomes comor quite hard um for some
natural product
molecules um it's comes very hard it's
not impossible but we're looking at the
bounds on that at the moment but as the
object gets bigger it becomes really
hard and but there that's the bad news
but the good news is there are shortcuts
and we might even be able to physically
measure the complexity without
computationally calculating it which is
kind of insane wait wait how would you
do that well in the case of molecule um
so if you shine light on a molecule
let's take it infrared the the molecule
has each of the bonds absorb
the infrared differently in what we call
the fingerprint region and so it's a bit
like a um and because it's quantized as
well you have all these discrete kind of
absorbances and my intuition after we
realized we could cut molecules up in
Mass Spec that was the first go at this
we did it with using infrared and the
infrared gave us an even better
correlation assembly index and we used
another technique as well in addition to
infrared called NMR nuclear magnetic
resonance which tells you about the
number of different gentic environments
in a molecule and that also worked out
so we have three techniques which each
of them independently gives us the same
or tending towards the same assembly
index for molecule that we can calculate
mathematically okay so these are all
methods of mass spectrometry mass spec
you scan a molecule it gives you data in
the form of a Mass Spectrum and you're
saying that uh the data correlates to
the assembly index yeah so how
generalizable is that shortcut first of
all to chemistry and second of all
beyond that cuz that seems like a nice
hack and you're extremely knowledgeable
about various aspects of chemistry so
you can say okay it kind of
correlates but you know the whole idea
behind assembly Theory paper and perhaps
why it's so controversial is that it
reaches
bigger it reaches for the bigger general
theory of objects in the universe yeah
I'd say so I'd agree so I've started
assembly theory of emoticons with my lab
believe it or not so we take emojis yeah
pixelate them and work out the assembly
index for emoji yeah and then work out
how many emojis you can make on the path
of emoji so there's the Uber emoji from
which all other emo em emojis emerge
yeah and then you can so you can then
take a photograph and by looking at the
shortest path on or by reproducing the
pixels to make the image you want you
can measure that so then you start to be
able to take um spatial data now there's
some problems there what is then the
definition of the object how many pixels
um how do you break it down and so we're
just learning all this right now so how
do you compute the how do you begin to
compute the assembly index of a
graphical like a set of pixels on a 2G
plane that form a thing so you would
first of all determine the resolution so
then sure how how what is your XY what
the number on the X and Y plane and then
look at the surface area and then you
take all your emojis and make sure
they're all looked at the same
resolution yes and then we will
basically then um do the exactly the
same thing we would do for cutting the
bonds you'd cut bits out of the Emoji on
and look at the the you'd have a bag of
pixels so um and you would then add
those pixels together to make the
overall emoji wait wait a but like first
of all not every pixel
pix's I mean this is at the core sort of
machine learning and computer vision not
every pixel is that important and
there's like macro features there's
micro features and all that kind of
stuff exactly what like uh you know the
eyes appear in A lot of them the smile
appears in a lot of them so in the same
way in chemistry we assume the bond is
fundamental what we do in there here is
we assume the resolution at the scale of
which we do it is fundamental and we're
just working that out and that you're
right that will change right because as
you take your lens out a bit you it will
change dramatically but it but it's just
a new way of looking at not just
compression what we do right now in
computer science and data one big kind
of um uh um kind of misunder
understanding as assembly theory is
telling you about how compressed the
object is that's not right it's a how
much information is required on a chain
of events because the nice thing is if
you when you do compression in computers
science we're wandering a bit here but
it's kind of worth wandering I think in
you you um assume you have instantaneous
access to all the information in the
memory yeah assembly Theory you say no
you don't get access to that memory
until you've done the work and then
you've done access to that memory you
can have access but not to the next one
and this is how in assembly Theory we
talk about the four universes the
assembly Universe the assembly possible
and the assembly contingent and then the
assembly observed and they're all all
scales in this combinatorial universe
yeah can you explain each one of them
yep so the assembly universe is like
anything goes just this just coment toal
kind of explosion in everything so
that's the biggest one that's the
biggest one it's massive assembly
Universe assembly possible assembly
contingent assembly observed and uh on
the y axis is assembly steps and time
yeah and you know in the x-axis as as
the thing expands Through Time more and
more unique objects appear
so yeah so assembly universe everything
goes y um assembly possible laws of
physics come in in this case in
chemistry Bonds in assembly so that
means those are actually constraints I
guess yes and they're the only
constraints they're the constraints at
the base the way to look at is you got
all your atoms they're quanti you can
just bung them together so then you can
become a kind of so in the way in
computer science speak I suppose the
assembly universe is just like no laws
of physics things can fly through
mountains beyond the speed of light in
in the assembly possible you have to
apply the laws of physics but you can
get access to all the motifs
instantaneously with no effort that
means you could make anything then the
assembly contingent says no you can't
have access to the highly assembled
object in the future until you've done
the work in the past on the causal chain
and that's really the really interesting
shift where you go from assembly um
possible to assembly contingent that is
really the key thing in assembly theory
that says you cannot just have
instantaneous access to all those
memories you have to have done the work
somehow the universe has to have somehow
built a um a system that allows you to
select that path um rather than other
paths and then the final thing the
assembly observed is basically saying oh
these are the things we actually see we
can go backwards now and understand that
they have been created by this this
causal process says wait a minute so
when you say the universe has to
construct the system that does the work
is that like the environment that'll
that that allows for like selection yeah
yeah yeah that's the thing that does The
Selection you could think about in terms
of a Von noyman Constructor first
selection a ribosome uh Tesla plant
assembling Teslas you know the the
difference between the assembly Universe
in Tesla land and the Tesla Factory is
everyone says no Teslas are just easy
they just spring out you know how to
make them all a Tesla Factory you have
to put things in sequence and out comes
a Tesla so you're talking about the
factory yes this is this is really nice
super important point is that when I
talk about the universe having a memory
or there's some magic it's not that it's
that tells you that there must be a
process encoded somewhere in physical
reality be it a cell a Tesla Factory or
something else that is making that
object I'm not saying there's some kind
of woo woo memory in the universe you
know morphic resonance or something I'm
saying that there is an actual causal
process that is being directed
constrained in some way um so it's not
kind of uh just making everything yeah
but Le what's the factory they made the
factory so what what is the so first of
all you assume the laws of physics is uh
just sprung to the existence at the
beginning those are constraints but what
what makes the factory is the
environment that doesn't selection this
is the question of well it's the first
interesting question that I want to
answer out of four I think the factory
emerges in the envir the interplay
between the environment and the objects
that are being built and and here let me
I'll have a go explain to you the the
shortest path so why is the shortest
path important imagine you've got um I'm
going to have to go chemistry for a
moment then abstract it um so imagine
you've got an envir a given environment
that um that you have a budget of atoms
you're just flinging together yep and
the the objective of those atoms that
being flung together in say molecule a
um have to make they have they decompose
so molecules decompose over time so the
molecules um in this environment in this
magic environment have to not die but
they do die there's a there's a they
have a halflife so the only way the
molecules can get through that
environment out the other side let
pretend the environment is a box go in
and out without dying and there's a
there's just an infinite supply of atoms
coming or well a large
Supply the the molecule gets built but
the molecule that is able to template
itself being built um and survives in
the environment will will basically re
Supreme now let's say that molecule
takes 10
steps now and it and it's using a finite
set of atoms right or now let's say
another molecule smart ass molecule we
call it comes in yeah and can survive in
that
environment and can copy itself but it
only needs five
steps the molecule that only needs five
steps because it's Contin both molecules
are being destroyed but they're creating
themselves faster they can be destroyed
you can see that the shortest path
Reigns Supreme so the shortest path
tells us something super interesting
about the minimal amount of uh
information required to propagate that
motif in time and space um and it's just
like a kind of it seems to be like some
kind of conservation law so one of the
intuitions you have is the propagation
of motives in time will be done by the
things that can construct themselves in
the
shortest path yeah so like you can
assume that most of the objects in the
universe are built in the shortest in
the most efficient way that the so big
leap I just took there yeah no yeah yes
and no because there are other things so
in the limit yes because you want to
tell the difference between things that
have required a factory to build them
and just random
processes um but you can find instances
where the shortest path isn't taken for
an individual object individual function
MH um and people go ah that means the
shortest path isn't right and then I say
well I don't know I think it's right
still because
so of course because there are other
driving forces it's not just one
molecule now when you start to now you
start to consider two objects you have a
joint assembly space and it's not now
it's a compromise between not just
making a and b in the shortest path you
want to make a and be in the shortest
path which might mean that a is slightly
longer you have compromise so when you
see slightly more nesting in the
construction when you take a given
object that can look longer but that's
because the overall function is the
object is still trying to be efficient
yeah and this is still very
handwavy um and maybe have no leg to
stand on but we think we're getting
somewhere with that and there's probably
some parallelization yeah right so this
is all this not sequential the building
is I guess when you're when you're
talking about complex objects you you
don't have to work sequentially you can
work in parallel you can get your
friends together and they can yeah these
and the the thing we're working on right
now is how to understand these parallel
processes now there's an in a new thing
we've introduced called assembly depth
and ass assembly depth can be lower than
the assembly index for a molecule when
they're cooperating together because
exactly this parallel processing is
going on and my team have been working
this out in the last few weeks because
we're looking at what compromises does
nature need to make when it's making
molecules in a cell and I I wonder if
you know
I I maybe like well I'm always leaping
out of um my competence but in economics
I'm just wondering if you could apply
this in economic process it seems like
capitalism is very good at finding
shortest path you know every time and
there are ludicrous things that happen
because actually the cost functions been
minimized and so I keep seeing parallels
everywhere where there are complex
nested systems where if you give it
enough time and you introduce a bit of
heterogeneity the system readjusts and
finds a new shorts path but the s path
isn't fixed on just one molecule now
it's in the actual existence of the
object over time and that object could
be a city it could be a cell it could be
a factory but I think we're going Way
Beyond molecules and and my competence
probably should go back to molecules but
hey all right before we get too far
let's talk about the assembly
equation okay how should we do this all
right let me just even read that part of
the
paper we Define assembly as the total
amount of selection NE necessary to
produce an ensemble of observed objects
Quantified using equation
one the equation basically has a on one
side which is the Assembly of The
Ensemble MH and then a
sum from one to n where n is the total
number of unique
objects and then there is a few
variables in there that include the
assembly
index the copy number which we'll talk
about that's an interesting I don't
remember you talking about that that's
an interesting addition and I think a
powerful one has to do with what that
you can create pretty complex objects
randomly mhm and in order to know that
they're not random that there's a
factory involved you need to see a bunch
of them that's that's the intuition
there it's an interesting intuition and
then uh some
normalization what else is it n n minus
one just to make sure that um more than
one object one object could be one of
and random yep and then you have more
than one identical object that's
interesting when when there's when
there's two of a thing two of a thing is
super important especially if the IND
index assembly index is high so uh we
could say several questions here one
let's talk about
selection what is this term selection
what is this term evolution that we're
referring to which which aspect of
darwinian evolution are we referring to
that's interesting here so yeah so this
is probably what you know the paper we
should talk about the paper for a second
the paper did what it did is it kind of
annoyed um we didn't knowy I mean it got
intention and obviously angry people the
angry people were annoyed there's angry
people in the world that's good so what
happened is the evolutionary biologist
got angry we were not expecting that
because we thought Evolution biologies
would be cool I knew that some not many
computational complexity people will get
angry cuz i' kind of been poking them
and maybe I deserved it but I was trying
to poke them in a productive way mhm and
then the physicist kind of got grumpy
because the initial conditions tell
everything the preotic chemist got
slightly grumpy because there's not
enough chemistry in there then finally
when the creationist said it wasn't
creationist enough I was like right I've
done my job the phys well you saying the
physics they
say because you're basically saying that
physics is not enough to tell the story
of how biology emerges I think so and
then they said a few physics is the
beginning and the end of the story
yeah so what happened is the reason why
people put the phone down on the call of
the paper if you if you view reading the
paper like a phone call they got to the
abstract Y and in the abstract it's
first sentence is pretty first two
sentences caused everybody scientists
have grappled with reconciling
biological evolution with the immutable
laws of the universe defined by physics
true right there's nothing wrong with
that statement totally
true yeah these laws under pin life's
origin Evolution and the development of
human culture and Technology yet they do
not predict the emergence of these
phenomena Wow first of all we should say
the title of the paper this is paper was
accepted and published in nature the
title is assembly Theory explains and
quantifies selection and evolution very
humble title and and the the the
entirety of the paper I think uh
presents interesting ideas but reaches
High I am
not I would do it all again this paper
was actually on the pre-print server for
over a year you regret nothing yeah I I
I think yeah I don't regret anything you
and Frank Sinatra did it your way what I
love about being a scientist is kind of
sometimes I'm because I'm a bit dim I'm
like and I don't understand what people
telling me I want to get to the point
this paper says Hey laws of physics are
really cool the universe is
great but they don't really it's not
intuitive that you just run the standard
model and get life out I think most
physicists might go yeah there's this
you know it's not just we can't just go
back and say that's what happened
because physics can't explain the origin
of life yet doesn't mean it won't or
can't okay just to be clear sorry
intelligent designers we are going to
get there second point we say that
Evolution works but we don't know how
Evolution got going so biological
evolution and biological selection so
for me this seems like a simple
so when I mentioned selection and
evolution in the title I think and in
the abstract we should have maybe
prefaced that and said non-biological
selection and non-biological evolutions
and then that might have made it even
more crystal clear but I didn't think
that biology evolutionary biology should
be so bold to claim ownership of
selection and evolution and secondly a
lot of evolutionary biologists seem to
dismiss the origin of Life questions
just say it's obvious and and that
causes a real problem scientifically cuz
because when two different when the
physicists are like we own the universe
universe is good we explain all of it
look at us and the EV biologist say we
can explain biology and the poor
chemistry in the in in the middle going
but hang
on and this paper kind of says hey there
is an
interesting
um disconnect between physics and
biology and that's at the point which
memories get made in chemistry through
bonds and hey let's look at this close
and see we can quantify it so yeah I
mean I never expected the paper to to to
kind of get that much interest in still
I mean it's only been published just
over a month ago now so just to Ling on
the selection what is
the broader sense of what selection
means yeah that's the really good for
selection selection so I think for
selection you need so this is where for
me the concept of an object is something
that can persist in time time and and
not die but basically can be broken up
mhm so so if I was going to kind of
bolster the definition of object so so
if if something can
form and persist for a uh a long period
of time um
under an existing environment that could
destroy other and I'm going to use
anthropomorphic terms I apologize that
weaker objects um or less robust
um then the environment could have
selected that so good chemistry examples
if you took some carbon and you made a
chain of carbon atoms whereas if you
took some I don't know some carbon
nitrogen and oxygen and made change from
those you'd start to get different
reactions and rearrangements so a carb a
chain of carbon atoms might be more
resistant to falling apart uh under
acidic or basic conditions um versus
another set of molecules so survives in
that environment so the acid Pond the
molecule the the molecu the resistant
molecule can get through and and then
then that molecule goes into another
environment so that environment now
maybe being an acid Bond it's a basic
Bond or maybe it's an oxidizing Pond and
so if you've got carbon and it goes in
oxidizing pond maybe the carbon starts
to oxidize and break apart so you go
through all these kind of obstacle
courses if you like given by reality so
selection is the ability happens when an
object survives in an environment for
some time but and this is a thing that's
super subtle the object has to be
continually being destroyed and made by
process so it's not just about the proc
the object now it's about the process
and time that makes it because a rock
could just stand on the mountain side
for four billion years and nothing
happened to it and that's not
necessarily really Advanced selection so
for selection to get really interesting
you need to have a turnover in time you
need to be continually creating objects
producing them what we call Discovery
Time so there's a discovery time for an
object when that object is discovered if
it's say a molecule that can then act on
itself or the chain of events that
caused itself to bolster its formation
then you go from Discovery time to
production time and suddenly you have
more of it in the universe so it could
be a self-replicating molecule and the
interaction of the molecule in the
environment in the War Little Pond or in
the sea or wherever in the bubble could
then start to build a Proto Factory the
environment so really to answer your
question what the factory is the factory
is the environment but it's not very
autonomous it's not very redundant
there's lots of things that could go
wrong so once you get high enough up the
the the hierarchy of networks of
interactions something needs to happen
that needs to be compressed into a
smaller volume and made resistant robust
because in bi techology selection and
evolution is robust that you have error
correction built in you have really you
know there's good ways of basically
making sure propagation goes on so
really the difference between inorganic
a biotic selection Evolution and
evolution and stuff in biology is
robustness um the ability to to kind of
propagate over over in the the ability
survive in lots of different
environments whereas our poor little
inorganic salt molecule whatever just
dies in lots of different environments
so there's something super special that
happens from the inorganic envir
molecule in the environment kills it to
where you've got Evolution and cells can
survive
everywhere how special is that how do
you know those kinds of uh Evolution
factors aren't everywhere in the
universe I I don't and I'm excited
because I think selection isn't special
at all I think what is special is the
history of the environments on Earth
that gave rise to the first cell that
now has you know has taken all those
environments and is now more autonomous
and I would like to think that you know
this
paper could be very
wrong but I don't think it's very wrong
I mean it's certainly wrong but it's
less wrong than some other ideas I hope
right and if allow inspires us to go and
look for selection in the universe
because we now have an equation where we
can say we can look for selection going
on and say oh that's interesting we seem
to have a pro process that's giving
that's giving us High copy number
objects that also are highly complex but
that doesn't look like Life as We Know
It And we use that and say oh there's a
hydrothermal vent oh there's a process
going on this molecular networks because
the assembly equation is not only meant
to identify at the higher end
Advanced selection what you get I would
call in biology you super Advanced
selection and even I you could use the
assembly equation to look for technology
and um God forbid we could talk about
Consciousness and abstraction but let's
keep it primitive molecules and biology
so I think the real power of the
assembly equation is to is to say how
much selection is going on in this space
and there's there's a really simple
thought experiment I could do is you you
know have a little petri dish and on
that petri dish you put some simple food
so the assembly index of all the sugars
and everything is quite low so then and
you put a single Eco cell of e eoli cell
yeah and then you say I'm going to I'm
going to measure the assembly in the
amount of assembly in the box so it's
quite low but the rate of change of
assembly da DT will go vom sigmoidal as
it eats all the food and the number of
coli cells will re will replicate
because they take all the food they copy
themselves the assembly index of all the
molecules goes up up up and up until the
food is exhausted in the box so now the
now the eoli stop I mean Dy is probably
a strong word they stop respiring
because all the food is gone but
suddenly the amount of assembly in the
box has gone up gigantically because of
that one eoli Factory has just eaten
through M lots of other eoli Factory has
run out of food and stopped and so that
looking at that so in the initial box
although the amount of assembly was
really small it was able to replicate
and use all the food and go up and
that's what we're trying to do in the
lab actually is kind of make those kind
of experiments and see if we can spot
the emergence of molecular networks are
producing complexity as we feed in raw
materials and we feed a challenge an
environment you know we try and kill the
molecules and and and really that's the
main kind of idea for the entire paper
yeah and see if you can measure the
changes in the assembly index throughout
the whole system yeah okay what what
about if if I show up to new planet we
go to Mars or some other planet from a
different solar system and how do we use
assembly index there to discover alien
life um in very simply actually if we
let's say we'll go to Mars with a mass
spectrometer with a sufficiently high
resolution so what you have to be able
to do so good thing about Mass speec um
is that you can um select a molecule
from the mass and then if it's high
enough resolution you can be more and
more sure that you're just seeing um
identical copies you can count them and
then you fragment them and you count the
number of fragments and look at the
molecular weight and the higher the
number of fragments the higher the
assembly index so if you go to Mars and
you take a mass spec or high enough
resolution and you can find molecules
I'll give guide on Earth if you could
find molecules say greater than 350
molecular weight with more than 15
fragments
you have found artifacts that can only
be produced at least on Earth by life
now you would say oh well maybe the
geological process I would argue very
vly that that is not the case but we can
say look if you don't like the cut off
on
Earth go up higher 30 100 right because
there's going to be a point where you
can find a molecule with so many
different parts the chances of you
getting a molecule that has a 100
different parts um and finding a million
identical copies you know that's that's
just impossible that could never happen
in an infinite set of universes can you
just Linger on this copy number
thing uh a million different
copies what do you mean by copies and
why is the number of copies
important yeah that was so interesting
and that um
I always understood the copy number was
really important but I never explained
it properly for ages um and it be I kept
having this it goes back to this if I
give you a um I don't know a really
complicated molecule and I say it's
complicated you could say hey that's
really complicated but is it just really
random and so so I realized that
ultimate Randomness and ultimate
complexity are
indistinguishable
until you can um you can see a structure
in the randomness so you can see copies
so copies
implies structure
yeah the factory I mean there's a deep
profound thing in there because like if
you just have a
random random process you going to get a
lot of complex beautiful sophisticated
things mhm what makes
them complex in the way we think life is
complex or um yeah something like a a
factory that's operating under a
selection processes there should be
copies is there like some looseness
about copies
like what does it mean for two objects
to be equal it it's it's all to do with
the the telescope or the microscope
you're using and so at the maximum
resolution so in the nice thing about
the nice thing about chemists is they
have this concept of the molecule and
they're all familiar with a molecule and
molecules you can hold you know in your
hand lots of them identical copies a
molecules actually super important thing
in chemistry to say look you can have a
mole of a molecues an avagadro's number
of molecules and they're identical what
does that mean that means that the
molecular composition the bonding and so
on the configuration is all is is
indistinguishable you can hold them
together you can overlay them so the way
I do it is if I say here's a bag um of
10 identical molecules let's prove
they're identical you pick one out of
the the out of the bag and you basically
observe it using some technique and then
you put it you take it away and then you
pick take another one out if You observe
it using technique you see no
differences they're identical it's
really interesting to get right because
if you take say two molecules molecules
can be in different vibrational
rotational States they're moving all the
time so for this respect identical
molecules have identical bonding in this
case we don't even um talk about
chirality because we don't have a
chirality detector so two identical
molecules in one conception assembly
Theory basically um considers both hands
as being the same um but of but of
course they're not they're different as
soon as you have a chyro distinguisher
detect to detect the left and the right
hand they become different and so it's
to do with the detection system that you
have and the resolution so I wonder if
there's an art in science to the which
detection system is used when you show
up to a new planet yeah yeah yeah so
like you're talking about chemistry a
lot today we have kind of standardized
detection systems right
of how to compare
molecules so you know when you start to
talk about emojis and language and uh
mathematical theorems
and uh I don't know more sophisticated
things at a different scale at a smaller
scale than molecules at are largest
scale the
molecules like what
detection like if if we look at the
difference between you and me lxly are
we the same are we different sure I mean
of course we're different close up but
if you zoom out a little bit will
morphologically look the
same you know height characteristics
hair length stuff like that well also
like the species and yeah yeah yeah and
and also there's a sense why we're both
from Earth yeah I I agree I mean this is
the power of assembly theory in that
regard that you if if you so if
everything so the way to look at it if
you have a box of objects if they're all
if they're all
indistinguishable uh um then using your
Technique you then you what you then do
is you then look at the assembly index
now if the assembly index of them is
really low right and they all they're
all indistinguishable then You' then
it's telling you that you have to go to
another resolution so that would be you
know it's kind of a signing scale it's
kind of nice so got it so those two kind
of are attentional with each other the
co the number of copies and the assembly
index
yeah that's really really interesting so
okay so you show up to your Planet
you'll be doing what I would do Mass
Spec I would bring on a sample of what
like First of all like how big of a
scoop do you take did you just take a
scoop like what like uh so we're looking
for primitive life I would I would look
yeah so if you're just going to Mars or
Titan or Enceladus or somewhere so a
number of ways of doing it so you could
take a large scoop or you go for the
atmosphere and detect stuff so and you
can make a light um a life meter right
so um one of Sarah's colleagues at ASU
Paul Davis keeps calling it a life meter
a life meter which is quite a nice idea
because you think about it if you've got
um a living system that's producing
these uh highly complex molecules and
they drift away and they're in a highly
um kind of
um demanding environment they could be
burnt right so they could just be
falling apart so you want to sniff a
little bit of complexity and say warmer
warmer warmer oh we found life we found
the alien we found we found the alien
Elon Musk smoking a joint in the bottom
of the cave on mars or Elon himself
whatever right you say okay found it so
what you can do is the mass spectrometer
um you could just look for things in the
gas phase or you go on the surface drill
down because you want to find molecules
that are you you've either got to find
the source living system because the
problem with just looking for complexity
is it gets burnt away so in a harsh
environment on on on say on the M
surface of Mars there's a very low
probability that you're going to find
really complex molecules because of all
the radiation and so on if you drill
down a little bit you could drill down a
bit into into a soil that's billions of
years old then I would put in some
solvent water alcohol or something or
take a a scoop put it in put viol make
it volatile put it into the mass
spectrometer and just try and detect
High complexity High abundant molecules
and if you get them hey Presto you can
have evidence of Life mhm wouldn't that
then be great if you could say okay we
found evidence of life now we want to
keep keep the life meter keep searching
for more and more complexity until you
actually find living cells and you get
those new living cells and then and then
you could bring them back to Earth or
you could try and sequence them you
could see that they have different DNA
and proteins go along the gradient of
the life meter how did you build a life
meter let's say we're together starting
new company launch launching a life
music Mass spectrometer would be the
first way of doing it just no no no but
that's that's um that's one of the major
components of it but I'm talking about
like I what if it's a device we got to
and and branding logo we got to talk
that that's later but what's the input
what's the like how do you get to the um
a metered output so I would I would take
a life so my my life meter our life
meter there you go thank you yeah you're
welcome um uh would have both infrared
and MPC so it would have two ports so it
could Shine the Light um and so what it
would do is you would have a a vacuum
chamber and you would have an
electrostatic analyzer and you'd have a
monochromator to producing infrared um
you'd add the S so you'd take a scoop of
the sample put it in the Life meter it
would then add a solvent or heat up the
sample so some volatiles come off the
volatiles would then be put into the
into the mass spectromet into
electrostatic trap and you'd weigh the
molecules and fragment them
alternatively you'd shine infrared light
on them you count the number of bands
but you'd have to in that case do some
separation because you want to separate
in and so in MPC it's really nice and
convenient because you can separate
electrostatically but um you need to
have that can you do it in real time
yeah pretty much pretty much yeah so
let's go all the way back so okay we're
really going get this the the Lexus life
meat Lex and Lee Lex Lee it's a good
it's a good good uh good ring to it all
right so um you have a you have a vacuum
chamber you have a little nose the nose
would have um some a a packing material
so you would take your your sample add
it onto the nose add a solvent or a gas
it would then be sucked up the nose and
that would be separated using Chrome
what we call chromatography and then as
each band comes off the nose we would
then do mass backc and infrared and in
the account in the case of infrared
count the number of bands in the case of
MPC count the number of fragments and
weigh it and then the further up in
molecular weight range for the mass spec
and the number of bands you go up and up
and up from the you know dead
interesting interesting over the
threshold oh my gosh Earth life and then
right up to bat crazy this is
definitely um you know alien
intelligence that's made this life right
you could almost go all the way there
same in the infrared and it's pretty
simple the thing that it's really
problematical is that for many years
decades what people have done and I
can't blame them is they've rather
they've been obsessing about small
biomarkers on that we find on Earth
amino acids like single amino acids or
evidence of small molecules and these
things and looking for those run looking
for complexity they were the Bey of
beautiful thing about this is you can
look for um complexity without Earth
chemistry bias or Earth biology bias so
assembly theory is just a way of saying
hey complexity and abundance is evidence
of selection
that's how our universal life meter will
work complexity in abundance is evidence
of
selection okay so let's apply our life
meter to
Earth
so what you know if we were just to
apply assembly index measurements to
Earth what do what what kind of stuff
are going to be get uh are going to get
what's impressive
L some of the complexity on Earth so we
did this a few years ago in that um when
I was trying to convince NASA and
colleagues that this technique could
work and honestly it's so funny because
everyone's like no ain't going to
work and I was just like because the
chemist was saying of course there are
complicated molecules out there you can
detect that just form randomly I was
like re really that's like that was like
you know as a bit like
a um I don't know someone saying of
course Darwin textbook was just written
randomly by some monkeys and a
typewriter and just for me it was like
really and and and I pushed a lot on the
chemist now and I think most of them are
on board but not totally it re really
had some big arguments but the copy
number CAU there cuz I think I confused
the chemist by saying one off and then
when I made clear about the copy number
I think that made it a little bit easier
just to
clarify chemist might say that of course
out there outside of Earth there's
complex molecules yes okay and then
you're saying wait a minute that's like
saying of course there's aliens out
there like you yeah exactly that okay
exactly but you're you're say you
clarify
that that's actually a very interesting
question and we should be looking for
complex molecules of which the copy
number is two or greater yeah exactly so
on Earth so coming back to Earth what we
did is we took a whole bunch of samples
we and we were running Prebiotic
chemistry experiments in the lab um we
took various inorganic minerals and
extracted them look at the volatile
because there's a special way of
treating minerals and polymers and
assembly Theory where what in this in
our life machine we're looking at
molecules we don't care about polymers
because they don't they're not volatile
you can't hold them they're not how how
can you make if you can't assern that
they're identical then it's very
difficult for you to to to work out if
there undergone selection or they're
just around random mess same with some
minerals but we can come back to that so
basically what you do we got a whole
load of samples inorganic ones we got a
load of we got Scotch whiskey and also
got took arbag which is one of my
favorite whiskies which is very pey and
another whis PD mean is like um so the
way that on on um in Scotland in Isa
which is Little Island the the the the
the scotch the SC the whiskey is led to
mature in barrels and um
the the it said that the Pete you know
the the the complex molecules in the
Pete might find their way through into
the whiskey and that's what gives it
this intense brown color and really
complex flavor it's literally molecular
complexity that does that and so you
know vulka is the complete opposite it's
just pure right the better the whiskey
the higher the assembly index the the
higher assembly index the better the
whiskey that's what I mean I really love
deep PT Scottish whiskies near my house
there is a a one of the the lowland
distilleries called Glen Goin it's still
beautiful whiskey but not as complex so
for fun I took some Glen coin whiskey
andard B and put them into the mass Beck
and measure the assembly index I also
got eoli so the way we do take the kyi
break the cell apart take it all apart
um and also got some beer and and people
were ridiculing us saying oh beer is
evidence of complexity one of the one of
the computational uh comple lexity
people was just
throwing yeah we kind of kind of his
very vigorous in his disagreement of
assembly theory was just saying you know
you don't know what you're doing even
beer is more complicated than human what
we didn't realize is that it's not beer
per se it is taking the yeast extract
taking the extract breaking the cells
extracting the molecules and just
looking at the profile of the molecules
see if there's anything over the
threshold and we also put in a really
complex molecule taxo so we took all of
these but also NASA gave us I think five
samples and they wouldn't tell us what
they are they said no we don't believe
you're going to get this to work and
they really you know they gave us some
super complex samples and they gave us
two fossils one that was a million years
old and one was at 10,000 years old um
SE something from Antarctica seabed they
gave us immersus and meter right and a
few others put them through the system
so I we we took all the samples treated
them all identically put them into Mass
Spec fragmented them counted and in this
case implicit in the measurement was we
um you in Mass backc you only
detect um Peaks when you've got more
than say let's say 10,000 identical
molecules so the copy number is already
baked in but wasn't Quantified which is
super important there this was in the
first paper because I was like it's
abundant of course um and when you then
took it all out we found that the
biological
samples um gave you um molecules that
had an assembly index greater than 15
and all the abiotic samples were less
than 15 and then we took the NASA
samples and we looked at the ones that
were more than 15 or less than 15 and we
gave them back to NASA and they're like
oh gosh yep dead Living Dead living you
got it and um and that's what we found
on Earth um that's a success yeah oh
yeah resounding success um well can can
you uh just go back to the beer and the
eoli so what's the assembly index on
those so what you were able to do is
like the assembly index um of we found
High assembly index molecules origin
originating from the beer sample and the
eoli sample so the yeast and the beer I
mean there there were I didn't know
which one was higher we wouldn't really
do any detail there because now we are
doing that because one of the things
we've done um it's a secret but I can
tell
you I think it's nobody's listening is
that we've just mapped the Tree of Life
using assembly Theory because everyone
said oh that you can't do infant biology
and what we're able to do is so you I
think there's three way well two ways of
doing Tree of Life traff uh well three
ways actually yeah what's the tree of
life so the tree of life is basically um
tracing back the history of life on
Earth all the different species going
back what who evolved from what and it
all goes all the way back to the first
kind of life forms and they Branch off
and like you have plant kingdom the
animal kingdom the fungi Kingdom you
know and different and different
branches all the way up um and the way
this was classically done and I'm no
evolutionary biologists the evolution
biologists are very tell me every day at
least 10 times um I want to be one
though I kind of like biology it's kind
of cool but yeah it's very cool um but
basically what uh what Darwin and Mel
and all these people do is just they
draw pictures right and they they tax
her they just con they were able to draw
pictures and and say and say oh this
look like common classes yeah
then they're artists really they're just
you know but they but they're they're
able to find out a lot right looking at
verbit in verance caman explosion all
this stuff and then um then came the
genomic Revolution and suddenly everyone
used Gene sequencing and Craig vent is a
good example I think he's gone around
the world and his yacht just taking up
samples looking for new species where
he's just found new species of life just
from sequencing it's amazing so you have
taxonomy you have sequencing and then
you can also do a little bit of kind of
molecular um uh kind of archaeology like
you know measure the samples and and
kind of form some inference what we did
um is we were able to fingerprint so we
took a loot of random samples from all
of biology and we use mass spectrometry
and what we did now is not just look for
individual molecules but we looked for
coexisting molecules where they had at
their joint assembly space and where we
where we're able to cut them apart and
and undergo recursion in the M spec and
infer some relationships and we're able
to recapitulate the Tree of Life using
mass
spectroscopy no sequencing and no
drawing all right can you uh try to say
that again with a little more detail so
recreating what does it take to recreate
the Tree of Life what does the reverse
engineering process look like here so
what you do is you take an unknown
sample you it into the mass spec you get
a because this comes from what you
asking like what do you see in ecoli and
so in ecoli you don't just see it's not
it's not it's not the the most
sophisticated um cells on on Earth make
the most sophisticated molecules it is
the coexistence of lots of complex
molecules above a threshold and so what
we realized is you could fingerprint
different life forms so fungi make
really complicated molecules why because
they can't move they have to make
everything on site um whereas you know
some animals are like lazy they can just
go eat the fungi they don't need to make
very much and I um and so what you do is
you look at the so you take I don't know
the fingerprint maybe the top number of
high molecular weight molecules you find
in the sample you fragment them to get
their assembly indices and then what you
can do is you can infer common origins
of molecules you can do a kind of
molecular um um when the reverse
engineering of the assembly space you
can infer common roots and look at
what's called The Joint assembly space
um but what let's translate that into
the experiment take a sample bung it the
MPC take the top say 10 molecules
fragment them and then and that gives
you one fingerprint then you do it for
another sample you get another
fingerprint now the question is you say
hey are these samples the same or
different and that's what we've been
able to do and um by basically looking
the assembly space these molecules
create without any knowledge of assembly
Theory you are unable to do it with a
knowledge of assembly Theory you can con
reconstruct the tree how does how does
knowing if they're the same or different
give you the tree let's go to two leaves
on different branches on the tree right
what you can do by counting the number
of differences you can estimate how far
away their origin was got it and that's
all we do and it just works but when we
realize you could even use assembly
Theory to recapitulate the tree of life
from no sequencing we're like huh so
this this is is looking at samples that
exist today in the world what about like
things that are no longer exist I mean
the tree contains information about the
past I would some of it is gone yeah
yeah absolutely I would love to get old
fossil samples and apply assembly Theory
MPC and see if we can find new forms of
life that have that are no longer aable
to Gene sequencing cuz the DNA is all
gone cuz DNA DNA and RNA is quite
unstable but some of the more complex
molecules might be there might give you
a hint of something new or wouldn't it
be great if you if you find a sample
that's worth really persevering and
doing um you know doing uh the proper
extraction to re to you know PCR and so
on and then sequence it and then put it
together so when the thing dies you can
still get some information about its
complexity yeah and we can and it
appears that you can
um do some dating now there are really
good techniques there's radiocarbon
dating there is um longer dating going
looking at radioactive minerals and so
on and you can also in bone you can look
at the what happens in after something
dies is the IM the you get what's called
ramiz where the the the chirality in the
polymers basically changes and you just
get you get decomposition and the rate
of the deviation from the pure po um uh
um en antima to the mixture you can have
a it gives you a time time scale on it
halflife so you can date when it died I
want to use assembly Theory to see if I
can date use it date death and things
and and Trace the tree of life and also
decomposition of molecules you think
it's possible oh yeah without a doubt it
may not be better than what cuz like the
I was just at a conference where some
brilliant people were looking at isotope
AR wrenchmen and and looking at how life
enriches Isotopes and they're really
sophisticated stuff that they're doing
but I think there's some fun to be had
there because it gives you another
dimension of dating how old is this
molecule um in terms of in or more
importantly how long ago was this
molecule produced by life the more
complex a molecule the more Prospect for
decomposition oxidation reorganization
loss of chirality and all that jazz but
what life also does is it enriches as
you get older the the amount of carbon
13 in you goes up mhm because of the
because of the way the metabol because
of the way the the bonding is in in
carbon 13 so it has a slightly different
strength bond strength and you is called
the kinetic isotope effect so you can
literally date how old you are you know
uh or when you stop metabolizing so you
could date someone's de how old they are
I think I'm making this up this might be
right but I think it's roughly right the
amount of carbon 13 you have in you you
can kind of estimate how how old you are
how
old living or humans are or living or
yeah like you could say oh this person
is 10 years old and this person 30 years
old because they've been metabolizing
more carbon and they've accumulated it
that's the basic idea it's probably
completely wrong time scale signatures
of of chemistry are fascinating so
you've been seeing a lot of
chemistry examples for assembly Theory
what if we zoom out and look at a bigger
scale of an object mhm uh you know like
really complex objects like
humans or living
organisms that are made up of you know
millions or billions of other organisms
how how do
you try to apply assembly Theory to that
at the moment um we're we're we should
be able to do this to morphology in
cells so we're looking at cell surfaces
and really try and extend further it's
just that you know we work so hard to
get this paper out and and people to
start discussing the ideas and I was and
but but it's kind of funny because I
think the PE the the penny is falling on
this so yeah so what's that even what
what's it mean for a penny to be I mean
no the the pennies dropped right because
a lot of people were like it's rubbish
it's rubbish you've insulted me it's
wrong and I'm and you know I mean the
paper got published on the 4th of
October it had 2.3 million engagements
on Twitter right and it's been
downloaded over few hundred thousand
times and someone actually said to me
wrote to me and said this is an example
really bad writing and what not to do
and I was like if all of my papers got
read this much cuz that's the objective
of I have a publishing a paper on people
to read it I want to write that badly
again yeah I don't know what's the Deep
Insight here about the negativity in the
space I think it's probably the immune
system of the scientific Community
making sure that there's no
that gets published that's and and it
can overfire it can do a lot of damage
it can shut down conversations in a way
that's not productive we and I go back I
me answer your question about the
hierarchi and assembly but let's go back
to the reception people saying the paper
was badly written I mean of course we
could improve it we could always improve
the clarity let's go there before we go
to the hierarchy yeah um you know it has
been criticized quite a bit the paper uh
what has been some criticism that you
found most powerful like that you can
understand and can you explain it the
yes the most
exciting criticism came from The
evolutionary biologist telling me that
they thought that that U it origin of
life was a solved problem and I was like
whoa we're really on at something
because it's kinan art and then when you
poke them on that they just said no you
don't understand Evolution and I said no
no I don't think you understand that
Evolution had to occur before biology
and we need there's a gap that was
really for me that
misunderstanding and that that did cause
an immune response which was really
interesting interesting um the second
thing was the fact that physicists the
physicists were actually really polite
right really nice about it but they just
said huh we're not really sure about the
initial conditions thing but this is a
really big debate that we should
certainly get into because you know the
the the emergence of life was not
encoded in the initial conditions of the
Universe um and it can't and I think
assembly Theory shows why it can't
be I'll say
sure you if you could say that again the
the the origin of the the emergence of
life was not and cannot in principle
being encoded in the initial conditions
of the universe just to clarify what we
mean by life is like what high assembly
index objects yeah and this goes back to
your favorite subject what's that
time right so why so why what what does
time have to do with it we I mean
probably we can come back to it later
but I I think think it might be if we
have time but um I think that I've I
think I Now understand how to explain
how um you know lots of people got angry
with the assembly paper but also the the
ramification of this is how time is
fundamental in the universe and and this
notion of commentarial spaces and there
are so many layers on this but um you
have to become an INT I think you have
to become an intuitionist mathema M and
you have to abandon platonic mathematics
and also platonic mathematics has left
physics astray but there's a lot back
there so we can go to the atonic
mathematic okay there's there's A's it's
okay The evolutionary biologist
criticized
because the origin of life is
understood and not it doesn't require an
explanation that involves physics yeah
that's their statement well I mean it
was said they said lots of confusing
statements basically I realized the
evolutionary biology community that were
vocal and some of them were really rude
really spiteful and needlessly so right
because look you know um it I I I didn't
people misunderstand publication as well
some of the people have said how dare
this be published in nature this is you
know how what a terrible journal and and
I and it really and I watch people look
this is a brand new idea that's not only
potentially going to change the way we
look at um biology it's going to change
the way we look at the universe and
everyone's like saying how dare you how
dare you be so grandiose I'm like no no
no this is not hype we're not we're not
like saying we've invented some um I
don't know we've discovered alien in a
closet somewhere just for hype we
genuinely mean this to genuinely have
the impact or ask the question and the
the way people jumped on that was a
really bad precedent for young people
who want to actually do something new
because this makes a bold claim and the
chances
are that it's not correct but what I
wanted to do is a couple of things is I
wanted to make a bold claim that was
precise and testable and correctable not
a wooly another woolly information in
biology argument information touring
machine blah blah blah blah blah a
concrete series of statements that can
be falsified and explored and either the
theory could be destroyed or built upon
well what about the
criticism of you're just putting a bunch
of sexy names on something that's
already
obvious um yeah that's really good so so
um the assembly index of a molecule is
not obvious no one had measure it before
and no one has thought to quantify
selection um complexity and copy number
before in such a primitive
um um quantifiable way I think the nice
thing about this paper this paper is is
a tribute to all well not to all the
people that understand that that biology
does something very interesting some
people call it neg entropy some people
call it think about you know
organizational principles that lots of
people were not shocked by the paper
because they' done it before a lot of
the lot of the arguments we got some
people said oh it's rubbish oh by the
way I had this idea 20 years before I
was
like which one if is it your the rubbish
part or the really revolutionary part so
this kind of plucked two strings at once
it plucked the there is something
interesting the biologies are we can see
around this but we haven't Quantified
yet and what this is a first stab at
quantifying that so the the the the fact
that people said um this is obvious but
it's it's also um so so if it's obvious
why have you not done it sure but uh
there's there's a few things to say
there one
is you know this is um in part of Phil
philosophical framework
because you know it's not like you can
apply this generally to any object in
the universe it's very chemistry focused
yeah well I think you will be able to we
just haven't got there robustly so if we
can say how can we let's go up a level
so if we go up from Level we let's go up
from molecules to cells cuz you jump to
people and I jump to motoc cons and both
are good and and they will be assembly s
cells yeah if we go from so if we go
from um molecules to assemblies and
let's take a cellular assembly a nice
thing about a cell is you can tell the
difference between a UK carot and a pro
carot right the organal are specialized
differently we then look at the cell
surface and the cell surface has
different gellation patterns and these
cells will stick together now let go up
a level in multicellular creatures you
have cellular differentiation now if you
think about how embryos develop you go
all the way back those cells undergo a
differentiation in a causal way that's
biomechanically a feedback between the
genetics and biomechanics I think we can
use a sembly theory to apply to tissue
types we can even apply it to different
cell disease types so that's what we're
doing next but we're trying to walk you
know the thing is I'm trying to LEAP
ahead I want to LEAP ahead to go who we
apply it to culture clearly you can
apply it to memes and culture and we've
also applied assembly
Theory to um
CA and not as you think Cel yeah yeah to
C not just as you think different CA
rules were invented by different people
at different times M and one of my uh
one of my co-workers very talented chap
basically was like oh I can realize that
different people had different ideas or
different rules and they copied each
other and made slightly different bit
different Celler autometer um rules and
they and and looked at them online and
so he was able to refer an assembly
index and copy number of rule whatever
doing this thing but I digress but it
does show you can apply it at higher
scale so what do we need to do to apply
assembly Theory two things we need to
agree there's a common set of building
blocks so in a Cell well in a in a
multicellular creature you need to look
back in time so there is the initial um
cell which the creature is fertilized
and then starts to grow and then there
is cell differentiation and you have to
then make that caal chain both on those
so it
requires um development of the organism
in time um or if you look at the cell
surfaces and the cell types they've got
different um um uh features on the cell
what walls and inside the cell so we're
building up but obviously I want to LEAP
to things like emoticons language
mathematical theorems a very large
number of steps to get from a
molecule to uh the human brain yeah um
and I think they are related but in
hierarchies of emergence right so you
shouldn't compare them I mean the
assembly index of a human brain what
does that even mean well maybe we can
look at the morphology of the human
brain say all human brains have these
number of features in common M if they
have those number of and then let's look
at a brain in in a whale or a dolphin or
a chimp panzi or a bird and say okay
let's look at the assembly indices
number of features in these and now the
copy number is just the number of how
many birds are there how many
chimpanzees are there how many humans
are there but then you have to discover
for that the features that you would be
looking for yeah and that means you need
to have a you need to have some idea of
the anatomy but is there an automated
way to discover features um I I guess so
I mean and I think this is a good way to
apply machine learning and image recogn
just to basically characterize things so
apply compression to it to see what
emerges and then use the
thing the features used as part of the
compression as the measurement of uh as
the thing that is searched for when
you're measuring assembly index and copy
number and and the compression has to be
remember the assembly Universe which is
you have to go from assembly possible to
assembly contingent and that jump from
because assembly possible all possible
brains all possible features all the
time but we know that on the tree of
life and also on the lineage of life
going back to Luca the human brain just
didn't spring into existence yesterday
it is a long lineage of brains going all
the way back and so if we could do
assembly Theory to understand the
development not just an evolutionary
history but in biological development as
you grow we are going to learn something
more what uh would be amazing is if you
can use assembly Theory this framework
to show the increase in the assembly
index uh associated with I don't know uh
cultures or pieces of text like language
or images and so on and
illustrate without knowing the data
ahead of time just kind of like you did
with NASA that you're able to
demonstrate that it applies in those
other contexts I mean and that you know
probably wouldn't at first and you have
to evolve the theory somehow you have to
change it you have to expand it you know
um I think so but like that uh I guess
this is as a paper of first step in
saying okay can we create a general
framework for measuring
complexity of objects for measuring life
the complexity of living organisms yeah
that's that's what this is reaching for
that is the first step and also to say
look we have a way of quantifying
selection and evolution in a in a fairly
in a fairly not mundane but a fairly
mechanical way because before now is you
know this it wasn't very the ground
Truth for it was very subjective whereas
here we're talking about clean
observables and there's going to be
layers on that I mean with collaborators
right now we already think we can do
assembly theory on language and not only
that wouldn't it be great if we
can so the if we can figure out how
Under Pressure language is going to
evolve and be more efficient because
you're going to want to transmit things
and again it's not just about
compression it is about um understanding
how you can make the most of the in the
architecture you've already built and I
think this is something beautiful that
Evolution does we're re reusing those
architectures we can't just abandon our
evolutionary history and if you don't
want to abandon your evolutionary
history and you and you know that
Evolution has been happening then
assembly Theory works and I think that's
that's a key comment I want to make is
that assembly theory is great for
understanding where Evolution has been
used the next jump is when we go to
technology cuz of course if you take the
M3 processor um I want to buy I haven't
bought one yet I can't justify it but I
want it at some point the M3 processor
arguably is there's quite a lot of
features a quite a large number the M2
came before it then the M1 all the way
back you can apply assembly Theory to
microprocessor architecture it doesn't
take a huge leap to see that I'm a Linux
guy by the way so your examples go way
over my well whatever is that is that
like a is that a fruit company of some
sort I don't even know
yeah there's a lot of interesting stuff
to ask about language like you could
look
at how would that work you could look at
gpt1 gpt2 gpt3 35
4 and try to analyze the kind of
language it produces I mean that's
almost trying to look at assembly index
of in intelligent systems yeah I mean I
think um the thing about large language
models um and this is a whole hobby
horse I have at the moment m M um is
that obviously they're they're all
about the the the in the evidence of
evolution in the in the in the large
language model comes from all the people
that produced all the language and
that's really interesting and all the
corrections in the in the in the
Mechanical Turk right sure um and and so
that's part of the History part of the
memory of the system exactly so you can
you so so it would be really interesting
to basically use an assembly based
approach to to making language in a
hierarchy right I think is my guess is
that you could we might be a build a new
type of large language model that uses
assembly theory that it has
more understanding of the past and how
things were created well basically the
thing with llms is they like everything
everywhere all at once Splat and make
the user happy so there's not much
intelligence in the model the model is
how the human interacts with the model
but wouldn't it be great if we could
understand how to embed more
intelligence in them in the system what
do you mean by intelligence there like
you seem to uh associate intelligence
with history yeah well memory I think
selection produces
intelligence well you're almost implying
that selection
is intelligence no yeah kind of I would
go that I would go out and live say that
but I think it's a little bit more human
beings have the ability to abstract and
they can break Beyond selection and this
is what why darwinian selection um
because a human being doesn't have to
basically do trial and error like they
can think about say oh that's a bad idea
W do that and then Technologies and so
on so we escaped darwinian Evolution and
now we're on to some other kind of
evolution I guess higher higher level
Evolution and and will will assembly
Theory will measure that as well right
because it's all a lineage okay another
piece of criticism
or by way of question
is how's assembly Theory or maybe
assembly index different from Comm
complexity so for people who don't know
comra complexity of an object is the
length of a shortest computer program
that produces the object as
output yeah I'm I I seem to there seems
to be a disconnect between the
computational approach this so yeah so
comol off measure requires a touring
machine MH requires a
computer um and that's one thing and the
other thing
is um assembly theory is supposed to
trace the process by which life
Evolution emerged right there's a main
thing there there are lots of other
layers so so Kolarov complexity you can
you can approximate Comm grov complexity
but it's not really telling you very
much about the actual
um it's really telling you about like
your dat your data set compression of
your data set sure and so that doesn't
really help you identify the the turtle
in this case as the computer MH and so
what assembly Theory does is I I'm going
to say a trigger warning for anyone
listening who's who loves complexity
Theory I think that we're going to show
that AIT is a very important subset of
assembly Theory because here's what
happens that um I think that assembly
Theory allows us to build um go
understand when with selections
occurring selection produces um
factories and things factories in the
End Produce computers and you can go
then algorithmic information Theory
comes out of that the frustration I've
had with with looking at life through
this kind of information theory is it
doesn't take into account causation so
the main difference between assembly
Theory and all these complexity measures
is there's no C or chain yeah and I
think that's the main the causal chain
is at the at the at the core of uh
assembly Theory exactly and if you're if
you've got all your data in a computer
memory all the data is the same you can
access it in the same way there's you
don't care you just compress it and and
uh you either look at the program
runtime or the shortest program and that
for
me it can it
is
absolutely not capturing What It Is What
It selection does but assembly Theory
looks at objects it doesn't have
information about the object history
it's going to try to infer that
history by uh looking for the shortest
history right the object the object
doesn't like uh have a a Wikipedia page
that goes with it history I would say it
does in a way and it is fascinating look
at so if you've just got the object mhm
and you have no other information about
the object what assembly Theory allows
you to do with just with the object is
to and and the the word infer is correct
I agree infer so you like say well
that's not the that's not the history
but but something really interesting
comes from this the shortest path is
inferred from the object that is the
worst case scenario if you have no
machine to make it so that tells you
about the depth of that object in time
mhm and so what assembly Theory allows
you to do is without considering any
other circumstances to say from this
object how deep is this object in time
if um we just treat the object as itself
without any other any other constraints
and that's super powerful because the
shortest path then says allows you to
say oh this object wasn't just created
randomly there was a process and so
assembly theory is not meant to you know
one up AIT or to ignore the factory it's
just to say it's just to say hey there
was a factory mhm that and how big was
that factory and how deep in time is it
m but it's still
computationally very difficult to
compute uh that history right for
complex objects it it is and becomes
harder one of the thing that's super
nice is that um it constrains your
initial conditions right it constrains
where you're going to be so if you take
say imagine so one of the things we're
doing right now is applying assembly
Theory to drug Discovery MH now what
everyone's doing right now is taking all
the proteins and looking at the proteins
and and looking at molecules do with
proteins why not instead take the mo
look at the molecules that are involved
interacting with the receptors over time
rather thinking about and use the
molecules evolve over time as a proxy
for how the proteins evolved over time
and then use that to constrain your drug
Discovery process you flip the problem
180 and focus on the molecule Evolution
rather than the protein and so you can
guess in the future what might happen so
that so that so you rather than having
to consider all possible molecules you
know where to focus and that's the same
thing if you're looking at in assembly
spaces for an object where you don't
know the entire history but you know
that um you know in the history of this
object is not going to have some other
Motif that there that um it doesn't
apply doesn't appear in the past but
just even for the drug Discovery Point
you made isn't don't you have to
simulate all of chemistry
for uh to figure out how to come up with
con constraints no the molecules and the
no I mean I don't I don't know enough
about protein well this is another thing
that I think causes because this paper
goes across so many boundaries so
chemists have looked at this and said um
this is not a this is not a react this
is not correct reaction it's like no
it's a
graph sure there's there's uh uh
assembly index and shortest path
examples here on chemistry yeah and so
and what you do is you look at the
minimal constraints on that graph of
course it has some mapping to the
synthesis but actually you don't have to
know all of chemistry you just have to
you can build up the constraint space
rather nicely MH um but this is just at
the beginning right there are so many
directions as could go in and as I said
it it could all be wrong but hopefully
it's less wrong what about the little
criticism I saw of do you
uh by way of question do you consider
the different probabilities of each
reaction in the chain so like that there
could be
different when you look at a chain of
events that led up to the creation of an
object doesn't it matter that some parts
in the chain are less likely than others
no it doesn't matter no no well let's go
back so no not less likly but react so
so so no so let's go back to what we're
talk looking at so the assembly index is
the minimal path that could have created
that object probabilistically so imagine
you have all your atoms in a plasma you
got enough energy you got enough um
there's collisions what is the quickest
way you could zip out that molecule with
no reaction constraints how do you
define quickest there then it's just
basically walk on a random graph so you
so we make an assumption that basically
the time scale for forming the bonds so
no I don't want to say that because it's
going to have people getting obsessing
about this point and your criticism is a
really good one what we're trying to say
is like this is this puts a lower bound
on something of course um some reactions
are less possible than others but
actually I don't think chemical
reactions exist oh boy what does that
mean why don't chemical reactions exist
I'm writing a paper right now that that
um I keep being told I have to finish
and it's called the origin of chemical
reactions and it merely says that
reactivity exists as controlled by the
laws of quantum mechanics and reactions
we put names chemist put names on
reactions like so you could have like I
don't know the vitic reaction which is
by you know vitic um you could have the
Suzuki reaction which is by Suzuki now
what are these reactions so these
reactions are constrained by the
following they're constrained by the
fact they're on planet Earth 1G MH 298
Kelvin one bar so these are constraints
mhm um they're also constrained by the
chemical composition of Earth oxygen
availability all this stuff and that
then allows us to focus in our chemistry
so when a chemist does a reaction that's
a really nice compressed shorthand for
constraint application glass flask pure
reagent temperature pressure bom bom bom
bom bom control control control control
control so of course we have Bond
energies this so the bond energies are
kind of intrinsic in a vacuum if you say
so the bond energy you have to have a
bond and so for assembly Theory to work
you have to have a bond which means that
bond has to give the molecule certain
half life so you're probably going to
find later on that some bonds are weaker
and that you are going to miss in Mass
spectr when you count look at the
Assembly of some molecules you're going
to miscount the assembly of the molecule
because it falls apart too quickly
because the bonds just form but you can
solve that with looking infrared so so
when people think about the probability
they're kind of
misunderstanding assembly Theory says
nothing about the chemistry because
chemistry is chemistry and the
constraints are put in by biology there
was no chemist on the origin of Life B
unless you believe in the chemist in the
sky and they were you know like Santa
Claus they had a lot of work to do but
but chemical reactions do not exist in
the constraints that allow chemical
transformations to occur do exist exist
okay okay so it's constraint applic so
it's there's no chemical reactions it's
all
constraint application Y which enables
the
emergence of
Rea of the what's a different word for
chemical reaction uh transformation
transformation yeah like a function it's
a function but no but I love chemical
reactions the shorthand and and and so
the chemists don't all go mad I mean of
course chemical reactions exist on Earth
short hand it's a short handful these
constraints for for right so assuming
all these constraints that we've been
using for so long that we just assume
that that's what was the case in natural
language conversation exactly the
grammar of chemistry of course emerges
in reactions and we can use them
reliably but I do not think the vitic
reaction is accessible on Venus right
and this is useful to remember you know
to to to frame it as constraint
application is useful for when you zoom
out to the bigger picture of the
universe and looking at the chemistry of
the universe and then starting to apply
assembly Theory that's interesting
that's really
interesting but we've also pissed off
the chemist now oh they they're pretty
happy but well most of them
no everybody everybody deep down is
happy I think they're just sometimes
feisty that's how they show that's how
they have fun everyone is grumpy on some
days when when you challenge the problem
with this paper is you what it's like
it's almost like I went to a part it's
like you I do used to do this
occasionally when I was young as go to a
meeting and and just find a way to
offend everyone at the meeting
simultaneously even the even the
factions that don't like each other
they're all unified in their hatred of
you just offending them this paper it
feels like the the person that went to
the party and offended everyone
simultaneously say stop fighting with
themselves and just focused on this
paper U maybe just a little Insider
interesting information what were the
editors of nature like what the reviews
and so on how difficult was that process
this is a pretty like big paper yeah I
mean the so um we when we originally
sent the paper um we sent the paper and
the editor
said um that you know this was like this
was a quite a long process we sent the
paper and the editor gave us some
feedback and said you know I don't think
is that interesting it's not you know or
it's hard it's it's a it's hard concept
and we asked and the editor gave us some
feedback M um and we and Sarah and I
took a year to rewrite the paper was the
nature of the feedback very specific on
like this part of this part or was it
like like what what are you guys smoking
what kind of yeah it was kind of the
latter what you smoking okay and and you
know but polite and there's promise yeah
well the thing is there was the edit was
really critical but in a but in a really
professional way yeah and I mean for me
this was the way science should happen
so when it came back you know know we
had too many equations in the paper if
you look at the preprint they're just
equations everywhere like 23 equations
and when I said to abishek who was the
first author we got to remove all the
equations but my assembly equations
thing AB was like you know no we can't I
said well look if we want to explain
this to people there's a real challenge
mhm and so Sarah and I went through the
I think it was actually 160 versions of
the paper but we basically we got to
version 40 or something we said right
zero it start again so we wrote the
whole paper again we knew the entire
amazing and we just went bit by bit by
bit and said what is it we want to say
and then we sent the paper in um and to
our we expected it to be rejected and
not even go to review and then the we
got notification back it had gone to
review and we were like oh my God it's
so going to get rejected how's it going
to get rejected because the First
Assembly paper that on the MPC we sent
to Nature got went through six rounds of
review and rejected right and there by
by a by a chemist just said I don't
believe you must be committing fraud MH
um a long story probably a boring story
but in this case it went out to review
the comments came back and the comments
were
incredibly
um uh no they were very there were very
deep comments from all the reviewers
there were um and but the but the none
of the but the nice thing was the
reviewers were kind
of very critical but not dismissive they
were like oh really explain this explain
this explain this explain this are you
sure it's not koler off are you sure
it's not this and we went through I
think three rounds of review pretty
quick um and um and the editor went yeah
it's in M but maybe you could just
comment on the whole process uh you've
published some pretty huge papers on all
kinds of topics within chemistry and
Beyond some of them have some little
Spice in them a little spice of crazy
like Tom way says I like my to with a
little Drop of Poison so you know it's
not um a mundane paper so where what's
it like psychologically to go through
all this process to keep getting
rejected to uh to get reviews from
people that don't get the paper or um
all that kind of stuff just from a a
question of a scientist like what what
what is that like um it's uh I think
it's a um I mean this paper for me kind
of
cuz this wasn't the the first time we
tried to publish assembly Theory at the
highest level the nature Communications
paper we on the mass spec on the on the
idea went through went to Nature and got
rejected went through six rounds of
review and got rejected and and it and
it's and I I just was so confused when
the when the chemist said this can't be
possible I do not believe you can
measure complexity using MPC and also by
the way molecules
molecules um complex molecules can
randomly form and we're like but look at
the data the data says and they said no
no we don't believe you and and we went
and and I just wouldn't give up um the
editor and the editor in the end um was
just like different editors actually
right what's behind that never giving up
is like when you're sitting there 10:00
in the evening there's a Melancholy
feeling that comes over you you're like
okay this is rejection number five
or not it's not a rejection but maybe it
feels like a rejection because the you
know the the the comments are that you
totally don't get it like what gives you
strength to keep going
there H I don't
know I don't normally get emotional
about papers but
um
it's not about giving up because we want
to get it published because we want the
glory or anything it's just like why
don't you understand and so
um so what I did so what I would just is
trying to be as as as um as rational as
possible and say yeah you didn't like it
um tell me why and then
um sorry
second silly never get emotional about
papers normally but but you but I think
what we did you just compressed like
five years of Ang from this so it's been
it's been rough it's not just rough it's
like it happened you know I came up with
the assembly equation you know remote
from Sarah in Arizona and the people SFI
I feel like like I was a mad person like
you know the guy in depicted in in a in
a beautiful mind who was just like not
not the actual genius part but
just because I kept writing expanded and
I have no mathematical ability at all
and I was expand I was making these
mathematical expansions where I kept
seeing the same Motif again I was like I
think this is a copy number the same
string as coming again again again I
kept I couldn't do the math and then I
realized the copy number fell out of the
equation and everything collapsed down I
was like oh that works kind of so we
submitted the paper and then when it was
almost accepted right the mass Beck one
and it was astrobiologist said great um
you know a mass spectroscopist said
great and the chemist went nonsense like
biggest pile of nonsense ever fraud you
know and I was like but why fraud and
they just said just because and I was
like well so so and the and I could not
convince the editor in this case the
editor was just so pissed off cuz they
see it as like a kind of a you know uh
you're was of my time and I would not
give up I wrote I went and dissected you
know all the parts and I think although
I mean I got upset about it you know
which kind of embarrassing actually but
but I guess was
beautiful um but it was just trying to
understand why they didn't like it so
they were part of me was like really
devastated and a part of me was super
excited because I'm like huh they can't
tell me why I'm wrong and this kind of
goes back to you know um when I was at
school I was in a kind of learning
difficulties class and I kept going to
the teacher and say you know you know
how what do I do today to prove I'm
smart and they were like nothing you
can't I was like give me a job you know
give me something to do give me a job to
do something to to do as we um and I
kind of felt like that a bit when I was
arguing with the and not arguing there's
no ad hom I wasn't telling the editor
they were idiots or anything like this
or the the reviewers I kept it strictly
like factual
and all I did is I just kept knocking it
down Bit by Bit by Bit by Bit by Bit it
was ultimately rejected and it got
published elsewhere and then um the
actual experimental data so this is kind
of in this paper the experimental
justification was already published so
when we did this one and we went through
the versions and and then we sent it in
and in the end it just got accepted we
were like well that's kind of cool right
this is kind of like you know some days
you had you know the this student sorry
the the the first author was like I
can't believe it God accepted like nor
am I but it's great it's like it's good
and then when the paper was published I
was not expecting the backlash I was
expecting
computational well no actually I was
just expecting one person who been
trolling me for a while about it just to
carry on trolling but I didn't expect
the backlash and then I I wrote wrote to
the editor and apologized and the editor
was like what are you apologizing for
it's a great paper mhm of course it's
going to get backlash you said some
controversial stuff but it's awesome and
so well it's I think it's a beautiful
story of perseverance and the backlash
is just a negative word
for discourse which I think is beautiful
I think you as I said to you know when
it got accepted and people were saying
were kind of like hacking on it and I
was like papers are not gold medals the
reason I wanted to publish that paper
in nature is because it says hey there's
something before biological evolution
you have to have that if you're not a
creationist by the way this is an
approach first time someone has put a
concrete mechanism or sorry a concrete
quantification and what comes next
you're pushing on is a mechanism M and
that's what we need to get to is an
autocatalytic set self-replicating
molecules some other features that come
in um and the fact that this paper has
been so discussed for me is a dream come
true like you it doesn't get better than
that if you can't accept a few people
hating it and the nice thing is the
thing that I really makes me happy is
that no one has attacked the actual
physical content like you you can
measure the assembly index you can
measure selection now so either that's
right or it's well either that's helpful
or unhelpful if it's unhelpful this
paper will syn down and no one will use
it again if it's helpful it will help
people build scaffold on it and we'll
start to converge to a new paradigm so I
think that that's the the thing that I
wanted to see you know my colleagues
authors collaborators and people were
like you've just published this paper
you're a chemist why have you done this
like who are you to be doing
evolutionary theory like well I don't
know I mean sorry did I need to ca
anyone to do anything well I'm glad you
did let me just before coming back to
origin of life and these kinds of
questions uh you mentioned learning
difficulties I didn't know about this so
what what was it like I wasn't very good
at school right um this is uh when you
were very young yeah yeah but in primary
school I U my handwriting was really
poor and apparently I couldn't read and
um and I and my mathematics was very
poor so they just said this is a problem
they identified it my parents kind of at
the time were confused because I was
busy taking things apart buying
electronic junk from the shop trying to
build computers and things um and then
was I got out of when I was I think
about the major transition in my
stupidity like you know everyone thought
I wasn't that stupid when I basically
everyone thought I was faking I like
stuff and I was faking wanting to be it
so I always want to be a scientist so
five six seven years old i' be a
scientists take things apart and
everyone's like yeah this guy wants to
be a scientist but he's an idiot m and
so and so so everyone was really
confused I think at first that I wasn't
smarter than I you know was claiming to
be and then I just basically didn't do
well any the the test I went down and
down and down and down and then um and I
was kind of like huh this is really
embarrassing I really like maths and
everyone says I can't do it I really
like kind of you know physics and
chemistry and all that in science and
people say you're not you can't you
can't read and write and so I found
myself in a learning difficulty class at
the end of primary school and the
beginning of secondary school in the UK
secondary school is like 11 12 years old
M and I remember being put in the in the
remedial class and the remedial class
was basically full of um well two typ
three types of people there were um
people that had quite violent right you
know and there were people couldn't
speak English mhm and there were people
that really had learning difficulty
so
um the one thing I can objectively
remember um was I mean I could read um I
like reading I read a lot um but
something in me I was I'm a bit of a
rebel I refused to read what I was told
to read and and I found it difficulty to
read individual words in the way they
were told but anyway I got caught one
day teaching someone else to
read um uh and they said okay they we
don't understand this I I always knew
want to be a scientist but I didn't
really know what that meant and I
realized you had to go to university and
I thought I can just go University take
curious people like no no no you need to
have these you have to be able to enter
these exams to get this grade point
average and the fact is the exam you've
been entered into you're not you you're
just going to get C D or E you can't
even get a b or c right these are the
ukg DCS I was like oh and I said
can you just put me into the the high
exams I said no no you're going to fail
there's no chance so my my father kind
of intervened and said you know just let
him go in the exams just and they said
he's definitely going to fail it's a
waste of time waste of money and he said
well what if we
paid so they said well okay you didn't
actually have to pay you have to pay if
I failed MH so I took the exams and
passed them fortunately I didn't get the
top grades but I you know I got into a
levels but then that also kind of
limited what I could do at a levels I
wasn't allowed to do a level maths so
what do you mean you weren't allowed
because I I had such a bad math grade
from My GCSE I only had a c but I they
wouldn't let me go into the ABC for math
because of some kind of cour workk
requirement back then so the top grade I
could have got was a c so CD or E so I
got a C and then let me do um uh kind of
as level math which is this half
intermediate but and get to go
University but in the ACT liked
chemistry I had a good chemistry
teachers so in the end I got to
University to do chemistry so through
that kind of process I think for kids in
that situation it's it's easy to start
believing that you're
not uh well how do I put it that you're
stupid and basically give up that you're
just not good at math you're not good at
school so this is by way of advice for
people for interesting people for
interesting young kids right now
experiencing the same thing where was
the place what was the source of you not
giving up
there I have no idea other than um I I
was really I really like not
understanding stuff for me when I not
understand something um I didn't
understand feel like I understand
anything but but now but back then I was
so I remember when I was like I don't
know I I trilled I tried to build a
laser when I was like eight mhm and I
thought how hard could it be
like and I basically I was going to buil
a CO I was going to build a CO2 laser I
was like right I think I need some
partially um coated mirrors I need some
carbon
dioxide and I need a high high high
voltage so I kind of and I was like I
didn't have a and I was so stupid right
I was kind of so embarrassed I to make
enough CO2 I actually set fire and try
to filter the flame oh nice to crap it
off CO2 and I was like completely
completely failed and I bent burnt half
the the garage down so my parents were
not very happy about that but so that
was one thing I was like I really like
first principal thinking and so you know
um so I'm I remember being super curious
and being determined to find answers and
so the kind of when people do a give
advice about this well I ask for advice
about this I don't really have that much
advice other than don't give up and one
of the things I try to do um as a as a
chemistry professor in my group is I I
don't I hire
people that I think that you know I'm
kind of who am I if they're persistent
enough um who am I to deny them the
chance because some you know people gave
me a chance and I was able to do stuff
do you believe in yourself essentially
I like so I love being around smart
people and I love confusing smart people
and when I'm confusing smart people you
know not by stealing their wallets and
hiding it somewhere but if I can confuse
smart people that is the one piece of
hope that I might be doing something
interesting oh that's quite brilliant
like as a gradient to
optimize yeah hang out with smart people
and confuse them yeah and the more
confusing it is the more there's
something there and as long as they're
not telling you're just a complete idiot
and and they give you different reasons
yeah and I mean I'm you know if everyone
CU like with assembly Theory and people
said oh it's wrong and I was like why
and they're like and no one could give
me a consistent reason they said oh
because it's been done before or it's
just Kolar off or it's just there that
and the other so I think the the the
thing that I like to do is and in
Academia it's hard right because people
are critical but I mean you
know the criticism I mean although I got
kind of upset about it earlier which is
kind of silly but silly because
obviously it's hard work being on your
own or with a team spacially separated
like during lockdown and and try to keep
everyone on board and and and and be you
know have some faith
that I've always wanted to have a new
idea and so you know I like a new idea
and I want to I don't want I want to
nurture it as long as possible and if
someone can give me actionable criticism
as why I think I was trying to say
earlier when I was kind of like stuck
for Words give me actionable criticism
you know it's wrong okay why is it wrong
say oh it doesn't your equation's
incorrect for this or your method is
wrong and then so if and so what I try
and do is get enough criticism um from
people to then triangulate and go back
and I've been very fortunate in my life
that I've got great colleagues great
collaborators funders mentors and people
that will take the time to say you're
wrong because and then what I have to do
is integrate the wrongness and go oh
cool maybe I can fix that and I think
criticism is really good people have a
go at me because I'm really critical I'm
like but I'm not criticizing you know
you as a person I'm just criticizing the
idea and trying to make it better and
say well what about this and you know
and sometimes I'm kind of you know my
filters are kind of uh you know trunca
in some ways I'm just like that's wrong
that's wrong that's wrong want do this
and people like oh my God you just told
me you destroyed my life's work I'm like
relax no I'm just like let's make it
better and I think that we don't do that
enough cuz we're we're you know we we're
we're we're either personally critical
which isn't helpful or we don't give any
criticism at all because we're too
scared yeah I yeah the I've seen you be
pretty aggressively critical but it's
every time I've seen it it's the idea
not the person um I I'm sure I make
mistakes on that I mean I I you know I
argue I argue Lots with with lots I mean
argue Lots with Sarah and she's like
kind of shocked I've argued with yasher
in the past and he's like you're just
making yashab B and you're like you're
just making that up I'm like no not not
quite but kind of yeah um you know I had
a big argument with Sarah about time
she's like no time time doesn't exist
I'm like no no time does exist and now
and then as she realized that her
conception of assembly Theory and my
conception assembly Theory were the same
thing necessitated us to abandon
the fact that time is eternal to
actually really fundamentally question
how the universe produces commentarial
novelty so so time is fundamental for
ass Theory um I'm just trying to figure
out where you and Sarah converged I
think assembly theory is fine in this
time right now but I think it helps us
understand that something interesting is
going on so there's and I'm me really
inspired by a a guy called Nick gizen
I'm going to butcher his argument but I
love his argument a lot so so I hope he
forgives me if he hears about it but
basically um if you want free will time
has to be
fundamental and we can go a and um if
you want time to be
fundamental
um you have to give up on platonic
mathematics and you have to use
intuitionist mathematics by the by the
way um and again I'm going to butcher
this but basically
Hilbert said that you know infinite
numbers are allowed and I think it was
Brower said no you can't all numbers are
finite so they kind of like we so let's
go back a step because I was like people
going to say assembly Theory seems to
explain that commentor large commentor
space um allows you to produce things
like life and technology and that large
comori space is so big it's not even
accessible to a sha Carol David Deutch
Multiverse that physicist saying that um
that all of all of the universe already
exist in
time is
probably
provably that's strong
word not
correct the we are going to know that
the universe as it stands the present
the way the present builds the future so
big the universe can't ever contain the
future and this is a really interesting
thing I think Max techmark has this
mathematical Universe he says you know
the universe is kind of like a block
universe and I apologize to Max if I'm
getting it wrong but people think you
can just move you have the stat you have
the initial
conditions and you can run the Universe
um right to the end and go backwards and
forwards in that universe that is not
correct well let me load that in the
universe is not big enough to contain
the future yeah that's why that's it so
that that's another that's a beautiful
way of saying that time is fundamental
yes and and that you can have and that's
what this is why um the ex the law of
the excluded middle something is true or
False only works in the
past is it going to snow in New York
next week or in Austin you might in
Austin say probably not in New York you
might say yeah if you go forward to next
week and say did it snow in New York
York last week true or false you can
answer that question the fact that the
law of the excluded middle cannot apply
to the Future explains why time is
fundamental well I mean that that that's
a good example intuitive example but
it's possible that we might be able to
predict you know whether it's going to
snow if we had perfect information I I
think we you're saying not
impossible impossible so here's why yeah
I'll make a really quick argument and
this argument isn't mine it's it's Nicks
and and a few other people can you can
you explain his view on fundamental on
time being fundamental yeah so I'll give
my view which kind of resonates with his
but basically um it's very simple
actually it would say that free will
your ability to design and do an
experiment uh is exercising Free Will so
he used that thought process I never
really thought about it that way um and
that you actively make
decisions I do think that I used to
think that Free Will was a kind of kind
of consequence of just selection but I'm
kind of understanding that human Free
Will is something really
interesting um and he very much inspired
me but a thing that what Sarah Walker
said that inspired me as well that that
um these will converge is that I think
that the Universe in the universe is
very big huge MH but
actually the own the place that is
largest in the universe right now the
largest place in un is Earth yeah I've
I've seen you say that and boy does
that that's a that's an interesting one
to process what do you mean by that
Earth is the biggest place in the
universe because we have this commentor
scaffolding going all the way back from
Luca so you've have you've got cells
that can self-replicate and then you go
all the way to terraforming the Earth
You' got all these architectures the
amount of selection that's going on
biological selection just to be clear
biological evolution and then you have
multicellularity then animals and
abstraction and when abstraction there
was another kick because you can then
build architectures and computers and
cultures and language and these things
are the biggest things exist in the
universe because we can just Build
architectures That Could naturally arise
anywhere and the further that distance
goes in time and this kind of is just
it's gigantic mhm and from a complexity
perspective yeah okay wait a minute but
I mean I know you're being poetic but
how do you know there's not other earth
like uh like how do you know you're
you're basically saying Earth is really
special it's awesome stuff as far as we
look out there's nothing like it going
on but how do you know there's not
nearly infinite number of places where
cool stuff like this is going on I agree
and I would say I I'll say again that
Earth is the most gigantic thing we know
in the universe commentor we know we
know now now I guess this is just purely
a guess I have no data but other than
hope well maybe not hope maybe no I have
some data um that every star in the sky
probably has planets Y and life is
probably emerging on these planets but
this the amount of contingency that is
associated with life is that I think the
commentarial space associated with these
planets is so different we are never
going to our cones are never going to
overlap or not easily and this is a
thing that makes me sad about alien life
why why we have to create alien life in
the lab as quickly as possible because I
don't know if we are going to be able to
be able to
build um architectures that will
intersect with alien Co intelligence C
and architectures intersect you you know
what I mean in time or space time and
the ability to communicate the ability
to communicate yeah my biggest fear in a
way is that life is everywhere but we
become infinitely more lonely because of
our Scaffolding in that commentor space
because it's so big and so so you're
saying the the constraints created by
the environment that led to the factory
of darwinian
evolution are just like this a little
tiny cone in a nearly Infinite
combinatorial Space so there's other
cones like it and and what why can't we
communicate with other like just because
we can't create it doesn't mean we can't
appreciate the creation right like that
sorry detect the creation I I I truly
don't know but I it's an excuse for me
to ask for people to give me money to
make a planet simulator yeah right if I
can make with a different different like
another Shameless say it's like give me
money I need money this was all long
plug for a planet simulator it's like
you know hey I will be the first in line
to my my my my Rick my Rick garage has
run out of room you know yeah no um and
this is a planet simulator you mean like
a different kind of planet or different
sets of environments and pressures
exactly if we could basically recreate
the selection before biology as we know
it that gives rise to a different
biology we should be a to put the
constraints on where it look in the
universe so here's a thing here's my
here's my dream my dream is that by
creating life in the lab
based upon constraints we understand
like let's like go for Venus type life
or earth type life or something again do
earth 2.0 screw it let's do earth 2.0 an
earth 2.0 has a different genetic
alphabet fine that's fine different um
protein alphabet fine have cells and
evolution all that stuff we will then be
able to say okay life is a more General
phenomena selection is more General than
than what we think is Con the chemical
constraints on life and we can point the
James web another telescope go to other
planets that we are in that zone we are
most likely to con combinatorially
overlap with right so because you know
we Bas so there chemistry looking for
some overlap and then we can then
basically um shine light on them
literally and white look at light coming
back and apply Advanced assembly Theory
to Lang general theory of language that
we will get and say hauh we in that
signal it looks random but there's a
copy number
oh this random set of things that
shouldn't be that looks like a a true
random number generator has
structure as a not com not Kolarov AIT
type structure but evolutionary
structure given by assembly Theory and
we start to um but I would say that CU
I'm a Shameless assembly theorist yeah I
it just feels like the the cone I might
be misusing the word cone here but the
width of the cone is growing gr
faster um is growing really fast to
where eventually all the cones
overlap like even in a very very very
large commentator
space I I it
just but then again if you're saying the
universe is uh also growing very quickly
in terms of possibilities that's re I
hope that as we
build as we build
abstractions the main I mean one one
idea is that as we go to
intelligence intelligence allows us to
look at the regularities around us in
the
universe and that gives us some common
grounding to to discuss with aliens and
and you might be right that that there
we will overlap there even though we
have completely different chemistry
literally completely different chemistry
um um that we will be out to pass
information from one another mhm but
it's not a given and um you know I have
to kind of try and divorce hope and
emotion you know away from what I under
I can logically justify but it's just
hard to Intuit it a world a universe
where
there's nearly infinite complexity
objects and they somehow can't detect
each other but the universe is expanding
but the nice thing is I would say I
would look you see I think KL Sean did
the wrong well not the wrong thing he he
flicked the Voyager probe BR pale blue
dot said look how big universe is I
would have done it the other way around
said look at the Voyager prob that came
from the planet Earth that came from
Luca look at how big Earth is
MHM then it produced that It produced
that yeah and that I think is like
completely amazing and then that should
allow people on Earth to think about
well probably we should try and get um
causal chains off Earth onto Mars onto
the moon wherever whe it's human life or
Martian life that we create it doesn't
matter um but but I think um this
commentarial space tells us something
very important about the Universe um and
and that I realized in assembly theory
that the universe is too big to contain
itself and and I think this is and now
coming back and I want to I want to kind
of change your mind about time because
I'm I'm guessing that you're a time is
just a coordinate yeah so I'm I'm going
to change guessing you're one of those
change your one of those I going change
your mind in real time or at least
attempt oh in real time there you go um
I already got the tattoo so this is
going to be embarrassing if you change
my mind but you can just add you can
just add Arrow time on to it right true
or erase it a bit so um and the argument
that I think that is really most
interesting is like people say the
initial
conditions um specify the future of the
universe okay fine let's say that's the
case for a moment now let's go back to
newtonium mechanics
now the uncertainty principle in
newtonium mechanics is this if I give
you the coordinates of your of an object
moving in
space and the coordinates of another
object and they Collide in space and you
know those initial conditions you should
know exactly what's going to happen
however you cannot specify these
coordinates to infinite Precision now
everyone said you know oh this is kind
of like you know um the chaos ser no no
it's deeper than that here's a problem
with numbers this how this is where
Hilbert and Brower fell
out
um to have the coordinates of this
object a given objects are colliding you
have to have them to infinite Precision
that's what Hilbert says it says no
problem infinite Precision is fine let's
just take that for granted but when the
object is finite and it can't store its
own coordinates what' you do
MH so in principle if a finite object
cannot be specified to infinite
Precision in principle the initial
conditions don't apply well how do you
know it can't store its uh well how do
you store an infinitely long number in a
finite size
well we're using Infinity very Loosely
here no no we're using infinite
Precision I mean not Loosely but very
precisely so you think infinite
Precision is required well let's let's
take the object let's say the object is
a a golf ball mhm golf ball is a few
centimeters in diameter we can work out
how many atoms there are in the golf
ball and let's say we can store numbers
down to Atomic dislocations MH so we can
work out how many atoms there are in the
golf ball and we can store the
coordinates in that golf ball down to
that number but beyond that we can't MH
let's make the golf ball
smaller and and the this is where I
think that we think that we get
Randomness in quantum mechanics and some
people so you can't get random quantum
mechanics deterministic but aha this is
where this is where we realize that
classical mechanics and quantum
mechanics suffer from the same
uncertainty principle and that is the
inability to specify the the initial
conditions to a precise enough degree to
give you determinism the universe is
intrinsically too big and that's why
time exists it's nondeterministic
looking back into the past you can look
at the you can use logical um arguments
because you can say was it true or false
you already know but this is the fact we
are unable to predict the future with
the Precision is not evidence of lack of
knowledge it's evidence the universe is
generating new
things okay so to you first of all
quantum mechanics you can just say
statistically what's going to happen
when two golf balls hit each other
statistically but that but but sure I
can say statistic what's going to happen
but then what they do happen yeah and
and and you keep nesting it together you
can't I mean it goes almost back to look
at look at look at um let's think about
entropy in the universe so how do you
what how do we how do we understand um
entropy change well we could do the look
at or process we can use the aeric
hypothesis um we can also have um um um
we can also have the uh counterfactuals
where we have all the different states
MH and we could even put that in the
Multiverse MH right but both those are
kind of they they're they're
non-physical uh the Multiverse kind of
collapses back to the same problem about
the Precision so all the the what you if
you accept you don't have to have true
and false going forward into the future
um the real numbers are real they're
just they're just're they're observables
we're trying to see exactly where time
being fundamental sneaks in and this
difference between that the the the golf
ball can't
contain its own
position perfectly
precisely if how that leads to time
needing to be fundamental let me I have
a what do you believe do you believe or
do you accept you have free
will yeah I think at this moment in time
I believe that I have free will so then
you you are then you have to believe
that time is
fundamental I understand that's the St
you've made well no that we can
logically follows because if you don't
have free will so like if you're in a if
you're in a universe that has no time
the universe is deterministic if it's
deterministic then you have no free will
I I think the space of how much we don't
know is so vast that saying the universe
is deterministic from that jumping
there's no free will is just too
difficult of a leap no I logically
follows no no I I don't disagree it's
not I'm not saying any I mean it's deep
and it's important all I'm all I'm
saying and it's the difference to it's
actually different to what I've said
before is that if you don't require
platonistic
mathematics and accepts that that
non-determinism is how the universe
looks and that gives us our creativity
and the where the universe is getting
novelty it's kind of really deeply
important in assembly Theory because
assembly starts to actually give you a
mechanism why you go from boring time
which is basically initial conditions
specify everything to a mismatch and
creative time and I hope we'll do
experiments I think it's really
important to I would love to do an
experiment that prove that time is
fundamental and the universe is
generating
novelty um I don't know all the features
of that experiment yet but by you know
having these conversations openly and
getting people to think about the
problem s in a new way better people
more intelligent people with good
mathematical backgrounds can say oh hey
I've got an idea I would love to do an
experiment that that shows that the
Universe I mean universe is too too big
for itself going forward in time and and
I really you know this is why I I really
hate the idea of the boltzman brain the
boltzman brain makes me super kind of
like you know everyone's having a free
lunch it's like saying it's like let's
break all the laws of physics so a
boltman brain is this idea that in a
long enough Universe a brain will just
emerge in the universe as conscious
without and that neglects the causal
chain of evolution required to produce
that brain and this is where the
computational argument really falls down
because the computation is can say I can
calculate probability of a bolts and
brain and I can and they'll give you
probability but I can calculate
probability of a bolts and brain zero
just because the the the space of
possibilities is so large yeah it's like
when we start falling ourselves with
numbers that we can't actually measure
and we can't ever conceive of I think it
I think it it it it doesn't give us a
good explanation and I've become I want
to explain why life is in the universe I
think life is actually novelty minor not
I mean life basically Minds novelty
almost from the future and makes it
actualizes in the
present okay life is a novelty
minor uh from the future that is
actualized in the present
y I think so novelty minor first of all
novelty what's the origin of novelty
when you go from boring time to creative
time where's that is it as simple as as
Randomness like you're referring to um I
I am really struggling with Randomness
because I had a really good argument
with Yasha about Randomness Nisa said
Randomness doesn't give you free will
that's insane because You' just be
random but I think and I think he's
right at that level yeah but I don't
think we I don't think he is right on
another level and it's not about
Randomness it's about it's about
constrained I'm going to sound like
constrained opport I'm making this up as
I go along so making this up constrained
opportunity so what I mean is like so
you have to have so that the novelty
what is novelty you know this is why I
think is the funny thing
you ever want to discuss AI why I think
everyone's kind of gone AI mad is that
they're
misunderstanding um novelty but let's
think about novelty ask what is novelty
so I think novelty is a genuinely new
configuration that is not predicted by
the P past right and that you discover
in the present right and um that is
truly different right now everyone says
that some people say that novelty
doesn't exist it's always with precedent
I want to do experiments that show that
that is not the case and it goes back to
a question you asked me a a few moments
ago which is where is the factory yeah
right because I think the same mechanism
that gives us a factory gives us novelty
and I think that that is that is why I'm
so deeply hung up on time I mean of
course I'm wrong but how wrong and I and
I think that that life opens up that
commentarial space in a way that the the
our current laws of physics or the what
as contrived in a deterministic initial
condition Universe even with the get out
of the Multiverse David Deutsch style
which I love by the way but I don't
think is
correct um but it's it's it's kind it's
really
beautiful Multiverse the the David
Deutsch's conception of the Multiverse
is kind of like given um but I think the
the problem with wave particle duality
and quantum mechanics
is not um about the Multiverse it's
about understanding how determined the
past is well I don't think just think
that actually this is a a discussion I
was having with Sarah about that right
where she was like oh I think we we'd
been debating this for a long time now
um about how we how do we reconcile
novelty determinism
indeterminism so okay just to clarify
you both you and Sarah think the
universe is not deterministic
uh I'm I won't speak for Sarah but I
roughly I I think that the
Universe I think the universe is
deterministic looking back in the P back
in the past right but undetermined going
F going forward in the future so I'm
kind of having my cake and eat it eating
it here this is because I fundamentally
don't understand Randomness right as
Yasha told me or other people told me
but if I adopt a new view now which
um the new view is the universe is just
net deterministic but I'd like to refine
that and say the universe appears
deterministic going back in the past but
it's but it's undetermined going forward
in the future so how can we have a
determinist a universe that has
deterministically looking rules that's
non-determined going into the future
it's this breakdown in Precision in the
initial conditions and we have to just
stop using initial conditions and start
looking at
trajectories and how how um the comori
space behaves in expanding Universe in
time and space and assembly Theory helps
us quantify the transition to biology
and biology appears to be novelty mining
because it's making crazy stuff you know
um that that we are unique to earth
right there are objects on Earth that
are unique to Earth they will not be
found anywhere else because you can do
the commentarial math uh what was that
statement you made about life is novelty
mining from the future yeah yeah what's
the what's what's the little element of
time that you're introducing so what I'm
kind of meaning is cuz the future is
bigger than the present in a
deterministic universe how do you go
from the how do how do the how do the
states go from one to another I mean
there's a mismatch right yeah so so that
must mean that you have a little bit of
indeterminism whether that's Randomness
or something else I don't understand I
want to do experiments to formulate a
theory to refine that as we go forward
that might help us explain that and um
and I think that's why I'm so
um determined to try and crack the the
non-life tolife transition looking at at
networks and molecules and that might
help us think about it the mechanism but
certainly the future is bigger than the
past in in my conception of the universe
and some conception of the universe and
by the way that's not obvious right
that's where was just kind of the future
being bigger than the
past well that that's one statement and
the statement that the universe is not
big enough to contain the future is
another statement yeah yeah yeah yeah I
that one is a big one I that one's a
really big one I think so I think it but
I think it's
entirely because look we have the second
law and right now I mean I'm we don't
need the second law if the future's
bigger than the past it follows
naturally right so why are we
retrofitting all these these sticking
plasters onto our reality to hold on to
a Timeless Universe yeah but that's
because it's kind of difficult to
imagine the universe
that's that can't contain the future but
it's not really exciting it's very
exciting but
it's it's hard uh I mean we're we're
humans on Earth and we have a very kind
of four dimensional conception of the
world of 3D plus time it's just hard to
Inuit it a world where what does that
even mean a universe that can't contain
the
future yeah it's kind of it's kind of
crazy but obvious weird I mean I suppose
it sounds obvious yeah if it's true but
the nice thing is you can so what I I
mean so the reason why assembly Theory
turned me onto that was that you let's
let's just start in the present and look
at all the complex molecules and go
backwards in time and understand how
evolutionary processes go gave rise to
them it's not in it's not at all obvious
the taxo which is a complex one of the
most complex natural products produced
by biology was going to be invented by
biology it's a accident you know taxo is
unique to Earth there's no taxo
elsewhere in the universe and taxo was
not decided by the initial conditions it
was decided by this kind of the this
interplay between the so the past simply
is embedded in the present it gives some
features but why the past doesn't map to
the future why one to one is because the
universe is too big to contain itself
that gives space for creativity novelty
and and un some things which are
unpredictable well okay so given that
you're disrespecting the power of the
initial conditions uh let me ask you
well so how do you explain that
cellometer are able to produce such
incredible complexity given just basic
rules and basic initial conditions I
think that that you you this falls into
the Brower um Hilbert trap mhm so how do
you get a cellular autometer produced
complexity you have a computer you
generate a display and you map the
change of that in time mhm there are
some Casa repeat like functions like
it's fascinating to me that for pi there
is a there is a Formula where you can go
to the the millionth decimal place of Pi
and read out the the the number without
having to go there but there are some
numbers where you can't do that you have
to just crank through there's um whether
it's wol framan computational
irreducibility or some other thing well
doesn't matter but these
Casa that complexity is that just
complexity or a number that is basically
you're mining that number in time mhm um
you know is that just a display screen
for that number that function well can't
you say the same thing about the
complexity on Earth then no because the
complexity on Earth um has a copy number
and an assembly index associated with
that that CA is just a number
running you don't think it has a copy
number wait wait a minute well it it
does in the human where where we're
looking at humans producing different
rules but then it's nested on selection
so those Casa are produced by selection
yeah I mean the ca is such a a
fascinating pseudo complexity generator
what I would love to do is understand um
quantify the degree of surprise in a CA
right it long enough but what that I
guess that means is we have to
instantiate we have to have a number of
experiments where we're generating
different rules and running them time St
steps but ah got it ca are mining
novalty in the F from the you know in
the future by iteration right and you're
like oh that's great that's great you
didn't predict it some rules you can
predict the what's going to happen other
rules you can't so for me if anything CA
are evidence that the the universe is
too big to contain itself because
otherwise you'd know what the rules are
going to do forever
more right I guess you were saying that
the physicist just saying that all you
need is the initial conditions and the
rules of
physics uh is somehow missing the bigger
picture AB yeah and you know if you look
at CA all you need is the initial
condition and the and the rules and then
run the thing you
need three things you need the initial
conditions you need the rules and you
need time iteration to mine it out
without the coordinate you can't get it
out sure and that's that that to use fun
and you can't predict it from initial
conditions if you could then it' be fine
and that time is res Foundation of uh
it's the history the memory of each the
things that created it has to have that
memory of all the things that led up to
it I think it's a yeah you have to have
the resource yeah cuz time is a
fundamental resource and and um yeah I'm
becoming I think I had a major
um uh Epiphany about Randomness but I
keep doing that every two days and then
it goes away again it's random you're
you're a Time
fundamentalist you should be as well if
you believe in Free Will yeah the only
conclusion is there is time is
fundamental otherwise you cannot have
free will it logically
follows
well my my the foundation of my belief
and Free Will is just
uh is is uh observation driven
but that's I think if you use
logic it's
like logically seems like the universe
is
deterministic looking backwards in time
and that's correct universe is and then
everything else is is a is is a kind of
leap it requires a
leap I mean I I I think that
um it's kind of this is what I think
machine learning was going to provide a
big a chunk of that right CU um it to
help us explain this so the way I'd say
if you take that's interesting why well
let's let's let's just um my favorite
one one is because I'm I'm the AI
doomers are driving me mad and AI the
fact that we don't have any intelligence
yet I call AI autonomous informatics
just to make people grumpy yeah um and
you're saying we're quite far away from
AGI I think that we have no conception
of intelligence and I think that we
don't understand how the human brain
does what it does does I think that we
are neurosciences making great advances
but I think that we have no idea about
AGI so I am a technological I guess
Optimist I believe we should do
everything the whole regulation of AI is
nonsensical I mean why would you
regulate EXL other than the fact that
clippy should come back and I love XL 97
because we can play um you know we can
do the flight flight simulator uh I'm
sorry in Excel yeah have you not played
the flight simulator in in Excel may7
yeah
what does that look like it's like
wireframe very very basic but basically
I think it's x0 y0 shift and it opens up
and you can play the fight simulator oh
wow wait wait is it using Excel Excel
Excel 97 okay I resurrected it the other
day and saw clippy again for the first
time in a long time well clippy is
definitely coming back but you're saying
we don't have a a great understanding of
what is intelligence what is the
intelligence I am very frustrated
underpinning the human mind I'm very
frustrated by the way that um we're AI
dooming right now and people are
bestowing some kind of magic now um
let's go back a bit so you said about
AGI are we far away from AGI yes I do
not think we're going to get to AGI
anytime soon I've seen no evidence of it
and the AI Doom scenario is nonsensical
in the extreme yeah um and the reason
why I think it's nonsensical but it's
not non
so and don't think there isn't things we
should do and be very worried about
right I mean there are things we need to
worry about right now what AI are doing
whether it's fake data fake users right
I want authentic people or authentic uh
um data I don't want everything to be
faked and I think it's a really big
problem and I'm absolutely want to go on
the record to say I really worry about
that what I'm not worried about is that
some fictitious entity is going to turn
us all to paper clips or detonate
nuclear bombs I don't
know maybe I don't know anything you
can't think of why is this is a and I'll
I'll take a very simple series of
logical
arguments and and this is the the the AI
doomers are have not had the correct and
this is had not had the correct they do
not have the correct
epistemology they do not understand what
knowledge is and until we understand
what knowledge is they're not going to
get anywhere because they're applying
things falsely so let me give you a very
simple argument people talk about the
probability P Doom AI um I can we can
work out the probability of a asteroid
hitting the planet why because it's
happened before we know the mechanism we
know that there's a gravity well or that
you know space time is bent and stuff
Falls in we don't know the probability
of AGI because we have no mechanism so
let me give you the another one which is
like I'm really worried about AG what's
ag ag is anti-gravity one day we could
wake up and anti-gravity you know it's
discovered we're all going to die the
atmosphere is going to float away we're
going to float away we're all doomed
what is the probability of AG we don't
know because there's no NE mechanism for
AG do we worry about it no and I don't
understand the current um reason for
these for the for certain people in
certain areas to be generating this
nonsense I think they're not doing it
maliciously I think we're observing the
emergence of new religions how religions
come because religions are about kind of
some control so you got The Optimist
saying AI is going to cure us all and AI
is going to kill us all what's the
reality well we don't have ai we have
really powerful machine learning tools
and they will allow us to do interesting
things and we need to be careful about
how we use those tools in terms of
manipulating human beings and faking
stuff right right uh well let me uh let
me try just sort of Steal man the ey
dummer's argument and actually I don't
know it are AI doomers in the owski camp
saying it's definitely going to kill us
because there's a spectrum 95% I think
is the limit yeah 95% plus that's no not
not plus I think I don't know I was
seeing on Twitter today various things
but I think yakow is yak Kowski is at
95% but to belong to the AI dumer Club
is there a threshold I don't know what
the membership maybe and what are the
fees I think well I saw I think Scott
arenson like I was quite surprised had
put two I I saw this online so it could
be wrong so sorry if it's wrong um says
2% but the thing is if you were to go if
you if someone said there's a 2% chance
you're going to die going into the lift
would you go into the lift in the
elevator for the American English
speaking audience uh well no not for the
elevator so I would say anyone higher
than 2% I mean like I I mean I think
there's a zero% chance of AGI Doom zero
just to push back on the on the
argument we're at n of zero on the AGI
we can see on Earth that there's
increasing ing levels of intelligence of
organisms we can see what humans with
extra intelligence were able to do to
the other species so
that is uh a lot of
samples of data what a Delta and
intelligence gives you when you have an
increase in intelligence how you're able
to dominate a species on Earth and so
the idea there is that if you
have a a being that's 10x smarter than
humans
we're not going to be able to predict
what that's going to with that being is
going to be able to do especially if it
has the power to hurt humans which you
can imagine a lot of trajectories in
which the more benefit AI systems give
the more control we give to those AI
systems over our power grid over uh our
nuclear weapons or weapons of any sort
and then it's hard to know what a Ultra
intelligence system would would be able
to do in that case you don't find that
convincing I think this is I would I
would fail that argument 100% here's a
number of reasons to fail it on first of
all um we don't know where the intention
comes from the problem is that people
think they keep you know watching all
the huers online with the prompt
engineering and all this stuff where
when I talk to a typical AI computer
scientist they keep talking about the AI
is having some kind of decision-making
ability that is a category error
the decisionmaking ability comes from
human beings we have no understanding of
how humans make decision we've just been
discussing Free Will for the last half
an hour right we don't even know what
that is so the intention I totally agree
with you people who intend to do bad
things can do bad things and we should
not let that risk go that's totally here
and now I'm do not want that to happen
and I'm happy to be regulated to make
sure that systems I generate whether
they're like computer system systems or
you know I'm working on a new project
called X called cam
mackina nice well done yeah yeah which
is basically
a um for people who don't understand the
point that xar is a great uh film about
I guess AGI embodied and chem is the
chemistry version of that and I only
know one way to embody intelligence
that's in chemistry and human brains so
category era number one is agency they
have agency category era number two is
saying that assuming that anything we
make is going to be more intelligent now
you didn't say super intelligent I'll
put the words into our mouth here super
intelligent that I think that um there
is
no no reason to expect that we are going
to make systems that are more
intelligent more capable you know when
people play chess computers they don't
expect to win now right they just the
chess computer is very good at chess
that doesn't mean it's super intelligent
so I think that super intelligence I
mean I think even Nick Bostrom is is
pulling back on this now cuz he invented
this so I see this a lot when did see
first happen Eric Drexler nanot
technology atomically precise ma
machines he came up with a world where
we had these atom cogs everywhere they
were going to we're going to make self
replicating Nanobots not possible why
because there's no resources to build
these self-replicating Nanobots you
can't get the Precision it doesn't work
it was a major category error in Def
taking engineering principles down to
the molecular level the only functioning
molecular technology we know sorry the
only functioning nanomolecular
technology we know produced by Evolution
there so now let's go forward to AGI
what is Agi we don't know it's super it
can do this so humans can't think that I
would argue the only agis that exist in
the universe produced by Evolution and
sure we may be a to make our working
memory better we might be a be able to
do more things the human brain is the
most compact Computing unit in the
universe uses 20 watts it's a uses a
really limited volume it's not like a
chat GPT cluster which has to have
thousands of Watts model that's
generated and has to be corrected by
human beings you are autonomous and
embodied intelligence so I think that
there are so many levels that we're
missing out we've just kind of went oh
we've discovered fire oh gosh the
planet's just going to burn one day
randomly m i mean I just don't
understand that leap there are bigger
problems we need to worry about so what
is the motivation why are these people
let's assume they have their Earnest
have this conviction well I think it's
just it's kind of they're making leaps
that they're trapped in a virtual
reality that isn't reality well I mean I
can continue a set of arguments here but
also it is true that
ideologies that fear Monger are
dangerous because you can then
use it to control to to regulate in a
way that uh halts progress to control
people and to uh to cancel people all
that kind of stuff so you have to be
careful because you reason ultimately
wins right but there there is a lot of
concerns with super intelligent systems
very capable systems when you I think
when I when you hear the word super
intelligent you're hearing like it's
smarter than humans in every way that
humans are smart but
the paperclip manufacturing system
doesn't need to be smart in every way
just need to be smart in a set of
specific ways and the more uh capable
the ad systems become the more you could
see us giving them control over like I
said our power grid a lot of aspects of
human life and that means they will be
able to do more and more damage when
there's unintended consequences that
come to life
I I think that that's right that the
unintended consequences we have to think
about and I'm that I fully I fully agree
with but let's go back a bit sentient I
mean I'm again I'm far away from my
comfort zone and all this stuff but hey
let's talk about it because I give
myself a qualification in yeah we're
both qualified in sentients I think yeah
as much as anyone else I think the
paperclip scenario is just such a poor
one because let's think about how that
would happen um and also let's think
about we are being so um
unrealistic about how much of the
Earth's surface we have
commandeered you know for paper M clip
manufacturing to really happen I mean do
the math it's like it's it's not going
to happen there's not enough energy
there's not enough resource where they
all going to come from I think that what
happens in evolution is really it why is
why is a killer virus not killed out all
of not killed all life on Earth what
happens is sure super killer viruses
that kill the ribosome have emerged but
you know what happens they nuke a small
space and because they can't propagate
they all die so there's this interplay
between evolution and propagation right
and death and so in evolution you don't
think it's possible to engineer for
example sorry to interrupt but like a
perfect virus no there's deadly enough
no nonsensical okay I think that just
wouldn't again it wouldn't work it was
too deadly it would just kill the radius
and not replicate it yeah I mean but you
don't think it's possible to get a I
mean if you were super I mean I if you
were it not kill all of life on Earth
but kill all humans there's not many of
us there's only like 8
billion there there's so much more ants
I mean I don't I so many more
ants and they're pretty smart I think we
the nice thing about what we where we
are I would love for the AI crowd to
take a leaf out of the book of the
biowarfare chemical warfare
crowd um I mean not love because
actually people have been killed with
chemical weapons in the first and second
world war and people and bioweapons have
been made and you know we can argue
about covid-19 and all this stuff let's
not go there just now but I think there
is a consensus that some certain things
are bad and we shouldn't do them right
and um and sure it would be possible for
a bad actor to to engineer something bad
but the LI the damage would be we would
see it coming and we would be able to do
something about it uh um
now I I guess what I'm trying to say is
when people talk about doom and they
just when you ask them for the mechanism
they just say um you know they just make
something up I'm I mean in this case I'm
Yan laon I think he put out a very good
point about trying to regulate jet
engines before we've even invented them
yeah and I think that's what I'm saying
I'm not saying we should I just don't
understand why these guys are going
around making literally making stuff up
about all dying yeah when basically we
need to actually really focus on now
let's say there's some actors are
earnest right let's say owski is Being
Earnest right and he really cares but
then but he loves it goes and then
you're all going to die it's like you
know why don't we try and do the same
thing and say you could do this and then
you're going to be happy forever after
yeah you know well I I think uh there's
several things to say there uh one I
think there is a role in society for
people that say we're all going to die
because I think
uh it filters through as a message as a
viral message that gives us the proper
amount of uh concern okay right meaning
not the it's not 95% but when you say
95% and it filters through Society it'll
give an average of like a
0.3% an average so it's nice to have
people that are like we're all going to
die then we'll have a proper concern
like for example I do believe we're not
properly concerned about the threat of
nuclear weapons currently like that that
it just seems like people have forgotten
that that's a thing and you know there's
a war in Ukraine with the nuclear power
involved there's nuclear Powers
throughout the world and it just feels
like we're on the brink of a potential
World War to a percentage that I don't
think people are properly calibrating
like in their head we're all thinking
it's a Twitter battle that's opposed to
like actual threat so like it's nice to
have that kind of level of concern but
to me like what I when I hear AI doors
what I'm imagining is with unintended
consequences a potential situation
where uh let's say 5% of the world
suffers deeply because of a mistake made
of unintended consequences I don't
imagine the entirety of human
civilization dying but there's could be
a lot of suffering if this is done poor
I I understand that and I'm I kind of I
guess I mean I'm involved in the whole
hype cycle like why what I would like us
to I don't want us to so what's
happening right now is there seems to be
so let me let's say having some people
saying ai ai Doom is a worry fine let's
give them that but it what seems to be
happening is there seems to be people
who don't think AI is doing they're
trying to use that to control regulation
and to push people to regulate where
which which stops humans generating
knowledge and I am an advocate for
generating as much knowledge as possible
mhm when it comes to nuclear weapons I
grew up in the 70s and ' 80s where the
nuclear Doom a lot of adults were really
had existential threat almost as bad as
now with AI Doom they were really
worried right there was some great well
not great there was some hor horrific
documentaries I think there's one called
Freds that was generated in the UK which
was like it was terrible it was like so
scary um and I think that the correct
thing to do is obviously get rid of
nuclear weapons but let's think about
unintended consequences we've got rid
of such SEC we got rid of all the sulfur
particles in the atmosphere right all
the all the s and what's happened in the
last couple of years is global warming
has accelerated because we've cleaned up
the atmosphere too
much so sure I mean the same thing if
you get rid of nuclear weapons you're
going exactly that's my point is if so
what we could do is if we actually
started to put the AI in charge which is
I really like an AI to be in charge of
all world politics and this sounds
ridiculous for a second hang on but if
we could all agree on the the aers just
woke up yeah yeah yeah on that statement
but I really don't like politicians who
are basically just looking at local
sampling but if you could say globally
look here's some gain Theory here
there's how what is the minimum number
of nuclear weapons we need to distribute
around the N the world to everybody to
basically reduce War to zero I mean just
the Start experiment of the United
States and China and Russia and major
nuclear Powers get together and say all
right we're going to distribute nuclear
weapons every single nation on Earth
Yep oh boy I mean that has a probably
greater than 50% chance of eliminating
major military conflict yeah yeah but
it's not 100% but it but I don't think
anyone will use them because I think I
think and look what you've got to try
and do is like for to qualify for these
nuclear weapons
I this is a great idea the game theorist
could do this right I think the question
is this I I really buy your question we
have too many nukes um from just from a
feeling point of view that we've got too
many of them so let's reduce the number
but not get rid of them because we'll
have too much conventional Warfare so
then what is the minimum number of
nuclear weapons we can just Shute around
to to remove what hum humans hurting
each other is something we should stop
doing it's in it's not out with our our
conceptual capability but right now what
about the Nations certain nations are
being um exploited for their natural
resources in the future because for a
short-term gain because we don't want to
generate knowledge and and so if
everybody had an equal doomsday
switch I I predict the quality of life
average human will go up faster I am an
optimist and I believe that humanity is
going to get better and better and
better that we're going to eliminate
more problems um but I think yeah let's
but uh the probability of a bad
actor of one of the Nations setting off
a nuclear
weapon I mean you have to you have to
integrate that into the but we we get we
distribute the N nukes like population
right we give what we do is we can't
believe but anyway let's let just go
there they say so if a if a small nation
with a couple of nukes uses one because
they're a bit bored or annoyed they're
going to they the likelihood that they
are going to be pummeled out of
existence immediately is 100% mhm and
yet they've only they've only nuked one
other city I know this is crazy and I
apologize for well no no I think this
just to be clear we're just having a
thought experiment that's interesting
but you know there's terrorist
organizations that would take that would
take would take that trade yeah I mean
we have to ask ourselves a question of
how many Which percentage of humans
would be suicide bombers essentially
where where they would sacrifice their
own life to to uh because they hate
another group of people and that I
believe it's a very small fraction but
is it large enough to uh if you give our
nuclear weapons I can predict a future
where we take all nuclear material and
we burn it for energy right as because
we're getting there and the other thing
you could do is say look there's a gap
so if we get all the countries to sign
up to the virtual nuclear agreement
where we all exist we have a simulation
where we can nuke each other in the
simulation and the and the economic
consequences are
catastrophic sure in the simulation I
love it it's not going to kill all
humans it's just going to have economic
conse I don't know I just made it up it
seems like it's interesting I mean it's
but it's interesting whether that would
have as much power on human psychology
as actual physical nuclear exp think so
it's possible but people don't take
Economic Consequences as seriously I
think as actual nuclear weapons I think
they do in Argentina and they do in
Somalia and they do in a lot of these
places where no I I think this is a
great idea I'm a strong Advocate now for
so what have we come up with burning
burning all the nuclear material to have
energy and before we do that because mad
is good mutually assured destruction is
very powerful let's take it into the
metaverse and then get people to kind of
um uh subscribe to that and if they
actually nuke each other even for fun in
the metaverse there are dire
consequences yeah yeah so it's like a
video game we all to join this metaverse
video game yeah I can't dire economic
consequences I don't know how and uh
it's all run by AI as you mentioned
which so the AI doomers is are really
terrified at this point no they're happy
they have a job for another 20 years
right oh you're mry yeah yeah yeah we
got I'm a Believer in equal employment
you've
mentioned that uh what you
call K makina yeah yeah so you've
mentioned that uh a chemical brain is
something you're interesting
creating and uh
that's a way to get conscious AI
soon can you explain what a chemical
brain is I want to understand the
mechanism of intelligence has gone
through Evolution right because the way
that the way that um intelligence was
produced by Evolution appears to be the
following origin of Life
multicellularity
Locomotion senses once you can start to
see things come coming toward you and
you can remember the the past and
interrogate the present and imagine the
future you can do something amazing
right so and I think only in recent
years did humans become Che
incomplete right
yeah yeah right we'll go and so that Che
incompleteness kind of gave us another
kick up um but our ability to process
that
information um is produced in a wet
brain and and I think that we are not
getting going to we do not have the
correct Hardware architectures to have
the domain flexibility and the inte or
the ability to integrate information and
I think
intelligence um also comes at a massive
compromise of data right now we're
obsessing about getting more and more
data more and more processing more and
more tricks to get dopamine hits so
we're going to when we look back on this
going oh yeah that was really cool cuz
when I chat as chat GPT it made me it
made me really feel really happy MH I
got a hit from it but actually it just
exposed how little intelligence I use in
in every
moment because I'm easily fooled so what
I would like to do is to say well hey
hang on what is it about the brain so
the brain has this incredible
connectivity and it has the ability to
um you know as I said earlier about my
nephew you know I just I went from Bill
to Billy and he went home right Leroy
like how did he make that leap that he
was able to basically without any
training I extended his name he went G
he doesn't like he wants to be called
Bill he went back and said you like to
be called Lee I'm going to call you
Leroy um so human beings have a m
brilliant ability or intelligent beings
appear to have a brilliant ability to
integrate across all domains all at once
and to synthesize something which allows
us to generate knowledge and and
becoming cheing
complete on our own I don't although AI
are built in cheing complete things
they're their thinking is not true and
complete in that they are not able to
build Universal
explanations and that lack of universal
explanation means that they're just
inductivist inductivism doesn't get you
anywhere in not not it's just basically
a party trick MH it's like you know the
the I like the um I think it's in the
fabric it from David Deutsch where
basically you know the farmer is feeding
the chicken every day and the chicken's
getting fat and happy and chicken's like
I'm really happy every time the farmer
comes in and feeds me and then one day
the farmer comes in and doesn't instead
of feeding the chicken just Rings its
neck you know and that's kind of and had
the chicken had an alternative
understanding of why the farmer was
feeding it it's interesting though
because we don't know what's special
about the human mind that's able to come
up with these kind of
generalities uh this Universal theories
of things and come up with novelty I can
imagine because you gave an example you
you know about William and Leroy
I I feel
like example like that we'll be able to
see in future versions of large language
models we'll be really really really
impressed by the humor the
insights all of it because it's
fundamentally trained on all the
incredible humor and insights that's
available out there on the internet
right so we'll be impressed I think
we'll be impressed oh I'm impressed
right I'm impressed increasingly so but
we're mining the past yes and what the
human brain appears to be able to do is
mind the future yes so novelty it is
interesting whether these large language
models will ever be able to come up with
something truly novel I can show on the
back of a piece of paper why that's
impossible and it's like the problem is
that and again these are domain experts
kind of bullshitting each other the term
generative yes right average person
think oh it's gener no no no if look if
I take the numbers between zero and
1,000 and I train a model to pick out
the prime numbers by giving them all the
prime numbers between zero and a th he
doesn't know what a prime number is
occasionally if I can cheat a bit it
will start to Guess that that it never
will produce anything out with the data
set because you mind the past the thing
that I'm getting to is I think that
actually current machine learning
Technologies might actually help reveal
why time is fundamental it's like kind
of insane because they tell you about
what's happened in the past but they can
never help you understand what's
happening in the future without training
examples sure if that thing happens
again it's like um so I think so let's
think about what large language models
are doing we have the we have the Lang
we have all the internet as we know it
you know language but also they're doing
something else we're having human beings
correcting it all the time those models
are being corrected um
steered
corrected modified tweaked is well yeah
but I mean
cheating well you could say that
training on human data in the first
place is cheating well let me human is
in the loop sorry it's in yes so human
is definitely in the
loop uh but it's not just human is in
the loop a very large collection of
humans is in the loop look turn and that
could
be I mean to me it's not intuitive that
you said prime numbers that the system
can't generate an
algorithm right
that the algorithm that can generate
prime numbers or the algorithm that can
tell you if a number is prime and so on
and generate algorithms that generate
algorithms that generate algorithms that
I I can that start to look a lot like
like human reasoning you know I don't
think I think again we can show that on
a piece of paper that sure I think there
has you have to have so this is the
failure in epistemology like I'm I'm
glad I even can say that word let know
what it means you said it multiple times
I know it's like three times now without
failure quit while you're ahead just
don't say it again you did really well
thanks so I but I I think the so what is
reasoning so coming back to chemical
brain if I could basically if I could
show that in a cuz I mean I'm never
going to make an intelligence in in cam
mackina because we don't have brain
cells they don't have gal cells they
don't have neurons but if I can make if
I can take a matri a gel and engineer
the gel to have it be a hybrid hardware
for rep reprogramming which I think I
know how to do I will be to process a
lot more information and train train
models billions of times cheaper and use
cross domain main knowledge and there's
certain techniques I think we can do but
it's still missing though the the
abilities of human beings have had to
become true and complete and so I guess
the question to to give back at you and
I it's like how do you tell the
difference between trial and
error um and the generation of new
knowledge I think the way you can do it
is this is that you come up with a a
theory an explanation inspiration comes
from out yeah and then you then test
that and then you you see that's going
towards the truth and human beings are
very good at doing that in and the
transition between philosophy
mathematics physics and Natural Sciences
where and I think that we we can see
that where I get confused is why people
misappropriate the term artificial
intelligence to say hey there's
something else going on here because I
think you and I both agree machine
learning is really good it's only get
better we're going to get happier with
the outcome
but why would you ever think the model
was
thinking or reasoning reasoning requires
intention and the intention if the model
is reasoning the intentions come from
the
prompter and the intention has come from
the person who programmed it to do it so
I I um but don't you think you can
prompt it to have intention basically
start with the initial conditions and
get it going where the you know
currently large language models Chad
GPT only talks to you when you talk to
it there's no reason why you can't just
start it talking but but those initial
conditions came from someone starting it
yes and that CS all chain in there so
that intention comes from the outside I
think that there is something in that
causal chain of intention that's super
important I I don't dis agree we're
going to get to AGI it's a matter of
when and what Hardware I think we're not
going to do it in this hardware and I
think we're unnecessarily fet azing
really cool outputs and dopamine hits
because obviously that's what people
want to sell
us well but there could be I mean AGI is
is a loaded term but there could be
incredibly super in
impressive intelligence
systems on the way to AGI so these large
language models I mean if if it appears
conscious if it appears super
intelligent uh who would to say it's not
I agree but I the super intelligence I
want I want to I want to be able to have
a discussion with it
about um coming up with fundamental new
ideas that generate knowledge and if
this if the superintelligence generate
comine novelty from the future that I
didn't see in its training set in the
past I would agree that something really
interesting is coming on I'll say that
again if the if the intelligent system
be a human being a chat chat B something
else is able to produce something truly
novel that we I could not predict even
having full audit trail from the past
then I'll be sold well so we should be
clear that it can currently produ it can
currently produce things that are in a
shallow sense novel that are not in the
training set but you're saying truly
novel I think they are in the training
set
I think everything it produces comes
from a training set there might be inter
there's a difference between inter
novelty and interpolation we do not
understand where these leaps come from
yet that is what intelligence is I would
argue those leaps and some people say no
it's actually just what will happen if
you just do cross domain training and
all that stuff and that may be true and
I may be completely wrong but right now
the human mind is able to mine novelty
in a way that artificial intelligence
systems cannot and this is why we still
have a job and we're still doing stuff
and you know I used chat GPT for a few
weeks oh this is cool and then it took
me too I had to I well what happened is
it took me too much time to correct it
then it got really good and now they've
they've done something to it it's not
actually that good yeah right I don't
know what's going on censorship yeah so
I mean that's interesting but it will
push us humans to uh characterize
novelty better like characterize the the
novel like what is novel what is truly
novel what's the difference between
novelty and interpolation I think that
this this is the thing that makes me
most excited these Technologies is
they're going to help me demonstrate to
you that time is fundamental and un
future is bigger than the than the than
the the present which is why we we are
human beings are quite good at um
generating novelty because we have to
expand our data set and and to cope with
unexpected things in our environment our
environment throws them all at us again
we have to survive in that environment
and I mean I I I Never Say Never I would
be very interested in how we can get um
cross main training cheaply in chemical
systems cuz I'm a chemist and brain the
only sentient thing I know of as a human
brain but maybe that's just me being
boring and predictable and not Noel Yeah
you mentioned uh GPT for electron
density so a GPT like system for uh
generating molecules that can Bine to
host automatically I mean that's that's
interesting that's really interesting
applying this same kind of transform
mechanism yeah for I mean this is one of
it goes my team I try and do things that
are non obvious but non obvious in
certain areas and one of the things I
was always asking about in chemistry
people like to represent molecules as
graphs and it's quite difficult it's
it's really hard in a if you're doing Ai
and chemistry you really want to
basically have good representation you
can generate new molecules are
interesting and I was thinking well
molecules aren't really graphs and
they're not continuously
differentiable could I do something that
was continuously differentiable was like
well molecules are actually made up of
electron density so I got thinking say
well okay could there be a way where we
could just basically take a um take a
database of readily solved electron
densities for in millions of molecules
so we took the electron density for
millions of molecules and just train the
model to put to learn What electron
density
is and so what we built was a system
that you literally could give it a let's
say you could take a protein that has a
particular active site or you know a cup
with a certain hole in it you pour noise
into it and with a GPT you turn the
noise into electron density and then in
this case it hallucinates like all of
them do but the hallucinations are good
because it means I don't have to train
on such a large num such a huge data set
because these data sets are very
expensive because how do you produce it
so so go back a steps you've got all
these molecules in this data set but
what you've literally done is um a
quantum mechanical calculation we've
produced electron densities for each
molecule so you say oh this
representation of this molecule has
these electron densities associated with
it so you know what the representation
is and you train the neural network you
know what electron density is so then
you give it an unknown pocket you pour
in noise and you say right produce me
electron density it produces electron
density that doesn't look ridiculous and
what we we did in this case is we
produce electron density that um
maximizes the electrostatic potential so
the stickiness but minimizes the what we
call the steric hindrance so the
overlaps is repulsive so you know make
the perfect fit and then we then used a
kind of
a kind of like a chat GPT type thing to
turn that electron density into what's
called a smile a smile string is a is a
is a a way of representing a molecule
and letters mhm and then we can then so
it just generates them then just
generates them and then the other thing
is then we bung that into the computer
and then just makes it yeah the the
computer being the thing that right
robot we've got that can basically just
do chemistry yeah so kind of we kind of
got this endtoend drug Discovery machine
where you can say oh you want to buy to
this active site here you go I mean it's
a bit leaky and things kind of break but
it's it's a proof of principle well were
the hallucinations what are those
still uh accurate well the
hallucinations are really great in this
case cuz in the case of a large langage
model the hallucinations just like just
make everything up to when it doesn't
just make everything up but it gives you
an output that you're plausibly
comfortable with thinks you're doing
prob istically the problem on these
electron density models is it's very
expensive to solve a shreding equation
going up to many heavy atoms and me and
large molecules and so we wondered if we
trained the um the the system on up to
nine heavy atoms whether it would go
beyond nine and it did it started to
generate molecules for 12 no problem
they look pretty good and I was like
well this hallucination I will take for
free thank you very much because it just
basically um this is a case where
interpolation extrapolation worked
relatively well um and we were able to
generate the really good molecules and
then what we were able to do here is and
this is a really good point what I was
trying to say earlier
that we were able to generate new
molecules from the known data set that
would bind to the the host so a new
guest to bind were these truly novel not
really because they they were
constrained by the host were they new to
us yes so I do well understand I can
concede that machine Learning Systems um
artificial intelligence systems can
generate new entities but how novel are
they it remains to be
seen yeah and how novel the things that
humans generate is also difficult to uh
quantify they seem
novel that's what a lot of people say
like you know
so the way to really get to genuine
novelty and assembly Theory shows you
the way is to have different causal
chains overlap and this really this
really um resonates with the the the
time is fundamental argument and if
you're bringing together um a couple of
object objects with different initial
conditions coming together when they
interact the more different their
histories the more novelty they generate
in time going forward and so it could be
that genuine novelty is basically about
mix mix it up a little and the human
brain is able to mix it up a little
little and all that stimulus comes from
the environment but all I think I'm
saying is the universe is deterministic
going back in time non-deterministic
going forward in time because the future
is too the universe is too big in the
future to contain in the present
therefore these collisions of known
things generate unknown things that then
become part of your data set and don't
appear weird that's how we give
ourselves Comfort the past looks
consistent with this initial condition
hypothesis but actually we generating
more and more novelty and that's how it
works
simple so it's hard to quantify novelty
looking backwards I mean the no the
present and the future are the novelty
generators but I I like this whole idea
of mining novelty I think it is um it is
going to reveal why the limitation of
current AI is a bit like the printing
press right everyone thought that when
book when the printing press came that
writing books is going to be terrible
that you had evil spirits and all this
they were just
books and same would be with AI yeah but
there I think there just the scale you
can achieve in terms of impact with AI
systems is pretty nerve-wracking but but
that's what the big companies want you
to
think but not like in terms of Destroy
All Humans but you can have major
consequences and the way social media
has had major consequences both positive
and negative and so you have to kind of
think about it and worry about it but
yeah people that fear Monger you know my
P Theory yeah for this you want to know
yeah is I think that um a lot of and
maybe I'm being and I think I really do
respect um you know um a lot of the
people out there who are trying to have
discourse about the positive future so
open AI guys meta guys and all this and
what I wonder if they're trying to cover
up for the fact that social media has
had a pretty disastrous effect on some
level and they're just trying to say oh
yeah we should do this cuz and then
could covering up for the fact that we
have got some problems with you know
teenagers and Instagram and Snapchat and
you know all this stuff and maybe
they're just overreacting now yeah it's
like oh yeah sorry we made the bubonic
plate and gave it to you all and you're
all dying and oh yeah but look at this
over here is even worse yeah there's a
there's a little bit of that but there's
also not enough celebration of the
positive impact that all these
technologies have had tend to focus on
the negative and tend to
forget the in part because it's hard to
measure like it's very hard to measure
the positive impact social media had on
the world yeah I I agree but if what I
worry about right now is like I'm really
I do care about the ethics of what we're
doing and the one of the reasons why I'm
so open about the the things we're
trying to do in the lab make life look
at intelligence all this is so people
say what are the consequences of their
and you say what the consequences of not
doing it and I think that um what I what
worries me right now in the present is
lack of authenticated users and
authenticated data and and human users
yeah
human I still think that there will be
AI agents that appear to be conscious
but they would have to be also
authenticated and labeled as such
there's too much there's too much value
in that you know like friendships with
AI systems there's too too much
meaningful human experiences to have
with the a systems that I just but
that's like a tool right it's a bit like
a meditation tool right some people have
a meditation tool makes them feel better
but I'm not sure you can ascribe
sentience and legal rights to a chatbot
that makes you feel less
lonely uh sentience yes I think legal
rights no I think it's the same you can
have a really deep meaningful
relationship with a dog and the dog
senent yes the chat Bots not right now
using the technology we use is not going
to be s
in this is going to be a fun continued
conversation on Twitter that I look
forward to
uh since you've had also from another
place some debates that were inspired by
the assembly Theory paper let me ask you
about God is there any room
for Notions of God in assembly Theory um
who God yeah I I don't know what God is
a I mean so God exists in our minds
created by
selection so human beings have created
the concept of God in the same way that
human beings have created the concept of
super
intelligence sure but does it does it
mean does it
not it still could mean that that's a
projection from The Real World where
like we're just assigning words and
Concepts to a thing that is
fundamental to the real world that there
is something out there that is a
creative Force underlying the Universe
um I think the universe there is a
creative force in the universe but I
don't think it's it's Senti in I I mean
I think the so I do not understand the
universe so who am I to say you know
um that that God doesn't exist I am an
atheist but I'm not an angry atheist
right I have lots of I have lots of
there are some people I know that are
angry atheists and say you know CR say
that religious people are stupid I don't
think that's the case um I have faith in
some things because I don't I mean when
I was a kid I kept like you know like I
need to know what the charge of electron
is like I can't measure the charge on
electron that was you know I was just
gave up and had Faith okay you know
resistors worked so when it comes
to I want to know why the universe is
growing in the future and what humanity
is going to become and I've seen that
the the acquisition of
knowledge via the generation of novelty
to produce technology has uniformly made
humans lives better I would love to
continue that
tradition
and you said that there's that creative
Force do do you think just to think on
that point do you think there's a
creative Force like is there like a
thing like a
driver that's like
that's creating stuff yeah I think that
so I think that and where what what is
can you describe it like mathemat well I
think selection I think selection
selection is the force selection is the
force in the universe it creates
novelty so is selection somehow
fundamental like what what yeah I think
Persistence of objects that could Decay
into nothing through operations that
maintain that structure I mean think
about it if um is it's it's amazing that
things exist at all that we're just not
a big commentarial mess yes so the fact
and they exist and they a thing that
exists persistent time yeah may I mean
let's think maybe the universe is
actually in the present the things
everything that can exist in the present
does
exist well that would mean it's
deterministic right no I I think the
universities might so the universe
started super small the past was
deterministic there wasn't much going on
and it was able to mine mine mine mine
mine and so that the process I mean is
um somehow
generating um universes
basically I can't put I'm trying to put
this into did you just say there's no
free will though no I didn't say that if
sorry I said there is Free Will I think
I think I I I'm saying that free will
occurs at the boundary between
the the future the past and the future
yeah I got you but everything that can
exist does exist everything that is so
everything that's possible to exist at
this so no I'm really put there's a lot
of loaded words there in there's a time
element loaded into that I I think that
the universe is able to do what it can
in the present right yeah and then I
think in the future there are other
things that could be possible we can
imagine lots of things but they don't
all happen sure so what that's what I
sneak in Free Will right there yeah so I
guess what I'm saying is what what what
exists is a com is a convolution of the
past with the present and the Free Will
going into the future well we can still
imagine stuff right we can imagine stuff
that never happen and it's amazing Force
because you're imagin this is the the
most important thing that we don't
understand is our imaginations can
actually change the future in a tangible
way which is what the the initial
conditions in physics cannot predict
like your imagination has a causal
consequence in the future isn't that
weird too
yeah how do
you it breaks breaks the laws of physics
as we know them right
now yeah so you think the imagination
has a causal effect in the future yeah
but it does exist in there in the head
there must be a lot of power in whatever
is going on there could be a lot of
power whatever's going on in there if we
then go back to initial conditions yeah
and that is simply not possible that can
happen but if we go into if we go into a
universe where we accept that there is a
finite ability to represent numbers and
you have rounding well not rounding
errors you have some the S what happens
the your ability to make decisions
imagine and do stuff is at that
interface between the certain and the
uncertain it's not as Yasha was saying
to me Randomness goes and you just you
know randomly do random stuff it is that
you are set free a little on your
trajectory Free Will is about being able
to explore on this narrow
trajectory um that allows you to build
you have a choice about what you build
or that choice is uh you interacting
with a future in the
present what do you is most beautiful
about this whole thing
the
universe the the the fact it seems to be
very undecided very open mhm and the
fact that
um every time I think I'm getting toward
an answer to a question there is so many
more questions that make the the chase
you know um do you hate that it's going
to be over at some point for you no I I
well for me I don't so I I I I think if
you think about it is it over Newton
now Newton has had causal consequences
in the future we discuss him all the
time his ideas but not the person the
person just had a lot of causal power
when he was alive but oh my God one of
the things I want to do is leave as many
Easter eggs in the future when I'm gone
to go oh that's cool would you be very
upset if somebody made a like a good L
large language model that's fine tuned
to Lee cor it would be quite boring
because I mean I mean I I'm no novelty
generation I I mean if it's a faithful
representation of what I've done in my
life that's great that's that's a
interesting artifact but I think the
most most interesting thing about
knowing each other is we don't know what
we're going to do next
sure sure I mean within some constraints
I've got you know you might I I can
predict some things about you you can
predict some things about me but we
can't predict everything everything and
it's because we can't predict everything
is why we're exciting to come back and
discuss and see it's so yeah I'm I'm I'm
I'm kind of H I'm happy that it'll be
interesting that some things I've done
can be captured but I'm pretty sure that
my angle on mining novelty for the
future will not be
captured
yeah
yeah so that that's what life is is just
uh some novelty generation and you're
done each one of us just gener a little
bit or have the capacity to at least I
think life is a selection produces life
and life affects Universe in the
universes with life in them are
materially physically fundamentally
different than universes without life
and that's super interesting and I I
have no beginnings of understanding I
think maybe this is like in a thousand
years there'll be a new discipline in
the humans we yeah of course this is how
it all works right and um in retrospect
it will all be obvious I
I think assembly theory is obvious
that's why a lot of people got angry
right they were like oh my God this is
such nonsense yeah you know like oh yeah
no actually it's not quite but the the
writing is really
bad well I can't wait to see where it
evolves uh Le and I I'm glad I get to
exist in this universe with you you're a
fascinating human this is always a
pleasure I hope to talk to you many more
many more times and I'm a huge fan of
just watching you create stuff in this
world and thank you for talking today
it's a pleasure as always Lex thanks for
having me on thanks for listening to
this conversation with Lee Ronin to
support this podcast please check out
our sponsors in the description and now
let me leave you with some words from
Carl Sean we can judge our progress by
the courage of our questions and the
depth of our answers our willingness to
embrace what is true rather than what
feels good thank you for listening and
hope to see you next time